<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LSE Law Review Blog - Articles</title>
    <description>A student-run law journal seeking to provide a platform for high quality legal scholarship.</description>
    <link>
    </link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Individualisation in Contractual Interpretation</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/05/individualisation-in-contractual-interpretation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/05/individualisation-in-contractual-interpretation/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Jogee and ‘West Side Story’- Still Unresolved Endings? </title>
        
          <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/05/jogee-and-west-side-story-still-unresolved-endings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/05/jogee-and-west-side-story-still-unresolved-endings/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Elgizouli v Secretary of State for the Home Department : Redefining the scope of common law constitutional rights?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/04/elgizouli-v-secretary-of-state-redifining-the-scope-of-common-law-constitutional-rights/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/04/elgizouli-v-secretary-of-state-redifining-the-scope-of-common-law-constitutional-rights/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Rethinking the concept of the Rule of Law in Modern Britain</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/04/rethinking-the-concept-of-the-rule-of-law-in-modern-britain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/04/rethinking-the-concept-of-the-rule-of-law-in-modern-britain/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Schrems II - Implications for Data Flows Post Brexit</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/04/schrems-II-implications-for-data-flows-post-brexit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/04/schrems-II-implications-for-data-flows-post-brexit/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>My Body, My Choice: How Might Artificial Wombs Endanger the Viability Doctrine? Limits to Abortion, Criminalisation and Reconciling the Maternal/Fetal Balance</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;i-introduction&quot;&gt;I. Introduction&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/04/my-body-my-choice/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/04/my-body-my-choice/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Building the Conscience of Humankind: An Analysis of the Use of Selective Imagery on the 75th Anniversary of International Criminal Justice</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/03/building-the-conscience-of-humankind/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/03/building-the-conscience-of-humankind/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The European Court of Human Rights, the Margin of Appreciation and European Consensus: Strengthening or Diluting Minority Rights?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/03/european-court-of-human-rights-the-margin-of-appreciation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/03/european-court-of-human-rights-the-margin-of-appreciation/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Investor-State Dispute Settlement: Understanding the System's Legitimacy Crisis in Constitutional Terms</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/02/investor-state-dispute-settlement/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/02/investor-state-dispute-settlement/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Airlines, Railways and UNIDROIT: Erasing the COVID Footprint</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2021/01/airlines-railways-and-unidroit-erasing-the-covid-footprint/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/01/airlines-railways-and-unidroit-erasing-the-covid-footprint/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Unintentional Transmission of Disease Revisited – a Tort Law Perspective on COVID-19</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/11/unintentional-transmission-of-disease-revisited/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/11/unintentional-transmission-of-disease-revisited/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title> 'Keep the Powder Dry': The Court of Appeal in Fearn v Tate Gallery</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;It is safe to say that the claimants in &lt;em&gt;Fearn v Tate Gallery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, owners of multi-million pound, highly exclusive London flats, are not among the neediest of those who have applied to human rights law for help. However, the decision of Mann J in the High Court,&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline2&quot; href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; while focusing primarily on the tort of nuisance, did raise an issue under the Human Rights Act 1998 (HRA) of considerable importance – horizontal effect&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline3&quot; href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, and the development of the common law in accordance with human rights under the European Convention on Human Rights (ECHR).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/09/keep-the-powder-dry-the-court-of-appeal-in-fearn-tate-gallery/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/09/keep-the-powder-dry-the-court-of-appeal-in-fearn-tate-gallery/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A Tale of Two Communities: Inequality and the Right to Water in Hudorovič and Others v Slovenia</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-case-note-on-hudorovič-and-others-v-slovenia&quot;&gt;A case note on &lt;em&gt;Hudorovič and Others v Slovenia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/08/a-tale-of-communities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/08/a-tale-of-communities/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The ECJ's Judgements on 'Gmail' and 'Skype Out': A Critical Review</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-critical-review-of-the-ecjs-judgments-on-gmail-and-skype-out&quot;&gt;A critical review of the ECJ’s Judgments on ‘Gmail’ and ‘Skype Out’&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/07/ecjs-judgements-on-gmail-and-skype-out/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/07/ecjs-judgements-on-gmail-and-skype-out/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Treaties, Peremptory Norms and International Courts: Is the Hierarchy Theory Treading Water?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction:&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/02/treaties-norms-international-courts-hierarchy-theory-treading-water/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/02/treaties-norms-international-courts-hierarchy-theory-treading-water/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Preliminary Analysis of Article XXI: Why the National Security Exception is an Implausible Justification for US Steel and Aluminium Tariffs on China</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/02/preliminary-analysis-art-xxi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/02/preliminary-analysis-art-xxi/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Protecting Rights under the Common Law: R(UNISON) v Lord Chancellor</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction:&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/02/protecting-rights-common-law-r-unison/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/02/protecting-rights-common-law-r-unison/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A Bank’s Liability for a Director’s Misappropriation of Funds: Singularis Holdings Limited (in liq) v Daiwa Capital Markets Europe Ltd</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2020/01/bank-liability-director-misappropriation-funds-singularis-holdings-limited/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/01/bank-liability-director-misappropriation-funds-singularis-holdings-limited/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Grossly Undefined Threshold for Establishing Medical Manslaughter</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;abstract1&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/12/grossly-undefined-threshold-establishing-medical-manslaughter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/12/grossly-undefined-threshold-establishing-medical-manslaughter/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>R v. Evans: An Uneasy Precedent?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R v. Evans: An Uneasy Precedent?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/11/r-evans-uneasy-precedent/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/11/r-evans-uneasy-precedent/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Would becoming a republic be so simple?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Would becoming a republic be so simple?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/10/becoming-republic-so-simple/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/10/becoming-republic-so-simple/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Private law protection of human rights from corporate abuses: deep and meaningful?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commentary on &lt;em&gt;Lungowe and others v Vedanta Resources plc and Kokola Copper Mines plc&lt;/em&gt; [2019] UKSC 20&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/10/private-law-protection-human-rights-corporate-abuses/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/10/private-law-protection-human-rights-corporate-abuses/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Privilege against Self-Incrimination in Civil Injunctions: the Double-Edged Sword of Themis?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In general, the privilege against self-incrimination (“&lt;strong&gt;PSI&lt;/strong&gt;”) protects a defendant from being compelled to provide (potentially) incriminating statement or information. PSI may be asserted by a defendant in a civil proceeding in opposition to a disclosure order. Like the double-edged sword of Themis, PSI cuts both ways. Upholding a defendant’s assertion of PSI may damage the interest of a claimant. Abrogating PSI may benefit the claimant at the cost of a defendant’s right to trial.  This article argues that the respective approaches of courts in Australia and England &amp;amp; Wales are both unsatisfactory. The main aim of this article is to persuade readers that this area of common law must be replaced by a statutory abrogation of PSI and corresponding prohibition against the use of information obtained in such disclosure order against the defendant in a subsequent criminal prosecution.  &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/10/privilege-against-self-incrimination-civil-injunctions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/10/privilege-against-self-incrimination-civil-injunctions/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The delicate balance between Carl Schmitt’s constituent power and liberal constitutionalism: a misunderstood and over-complicated dichotomy?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The tension between constituent power and a liberal theory of constitutionalism is important in constitutional theory as they paint very different perceptions of the nature of authority in a constitution. Constituent power is “the power through which the prince’s power to rule was authorised,”&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; and its primary function is to “specify in constitutional language the ultimate source of authority of the state.”&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline2&quot; href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; This article focuses on the work of Carl Schmitt, as it is suggested as a “powerful corrective to the distortions of normativism.”&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline3&quot; href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt; It is clearly anti-liberal and decisionist, providing a direct ground for critical evaluation of the alleged tension. In a similar vein, calls for executive action and/or dominance in times of emergency or crisis renders it necessary to understand whether the assumption of (near) absolute power by the executive in such times entails the death of liberal constitutionalism.&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline4&quot; href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt; This article argues that the concept of constituent power is only anathema to liberal constitutionalism if their relationship is conceived as dichotomous without any mutually inclusive aspects. Three arguments will be made. Firstly, by analysing Schmitt’s conception of constituent power and its perceived contradistinctions against liberal constitutionalism, it will be shown that the relationship between constituent power and liberal constitutionalism is dichotomous only if constituent power is conceived as external to the legal order. It will then narrow down the focus to the issue of emergency, contending that it does not require the law to recede and be totally suspended, and the concept of constituent power can be reconciled with liberal constitutionalism. Last but not the least, using the recent rumors of the use of the Emergency Regulations Ordinance (Cap. 241) (“&lt;strong&gt;ERO&lt;/strong&gt;”) by the Hong Kong Government to deal with various protests and clashes since early June 2019, it will be shown that limitations on the Executive’s power is crucial in order for Schmitt’s concept of constituent power and a liberal theory of constitutionalism to be reconciled. This article will come to the conclusion that Schmitt’s refusal to recognise the broader political and legal contexts underpinning the concept of constituent power is the main reason why it may be anathema to liberal constitutionalism.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/09/delicate-balance-carl-schmitt-constituent-power-liberal-constitutionalism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/09/delicate-balance-carl-schmitt-constituent-power-liberal-constitutionalism/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Material contribution: bridging the evidentiary gap</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;To right a private wrong, causation is generally established between the tortfeasor’s negligent act and claimant’s injury. However, on occasion, the evidence will be such that a causal link is difficult or even impossible to prove by the traditional approach. Material contribution has emerged in tort law to attempt to impose liability where causation is hard to prove in the usual manner, or where applying traditional causation would lead to an undesirable outcome. It is needed to protect vulnerable claimants who should not be barred from seeking remedy merely because their particular circumstances make it harder for them to obtain damages. A comparison of traditional factual causation with material contribution shows how the underlying principles of protecting the claimant are compatible without direct causation. Despite not being a traditional test of causation, material contribution in the law of tort is still needed to solve the problem of an evidentiary gap when the but-for test is insufficient to impose liability where it is desirable. Moreover, it may still be possible to show some level of causal link between the defendant’s negligence and the claimant’s injury.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/09/material-contribution-bridging-evidentiary-gap/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/09/material-contribution-bridging-evidentiary-gap/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Afghanistan: Towards wider interests of justice?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The Pre-Trial Chamber (“PTC”) II of the International Criminal Court (“ICC”) handed down its much-awaited decision on the request for authorisation of an investigation into the situation in Afghanistan&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; earlier this year. The escalating conflict in Afghanistan has generated thousands of civilian casualties, many of whom were also victims of acts potentially constituting war crimes within the ICC’s jurisdiction.&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline2&quot; href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; The decision that the investigation would not be in the interests of justice to pursue thus came as a surprise to the legal community, given the presumed dormancy of the provision – many had thought that any admissible case would &lt;em&gt;ipso facto&lt;/em&gt; be in the interests of justice to pursue. Indeed, it was widely assumed that the decision would only be subject to review by the PTC where the Office of the Prosecutor (“OTP”) had decided &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to pursue an investigation solely in the interests of justice.&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline3&quot; href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt; This case note will analyse the role of state cooperation in the PTC’s interests of justice determination in light of the principle of complementarity, which holds that the ICC should only intervene where a State Party was “unwilling or unable”&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline4&quot; href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt; to investigate a crime falling under the ICC’s jurisdiction. The objectives of domestic institution-building that the principle was conceived of to foster will be considered, before concluding that the PTC’s overt focus on prosecutorial success is misguided.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/09/afghanistan-towards-wider-interests-justice/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/09/afghanistan-towards-wider-interests-justice/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Privacy International: a constitutional barometer</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In the 1960s, there was talk of a ‘Fairness Revolution’ in English judicial review.&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; One of the most pertinent cases exemplifying such a movement is  Anisminic.&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline2&quot; href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; In that case, an administrative statutory body, the Foreign Compensation Commission, was given the job of deciding whether compensation should be awarded for property sequestrated as a result of the 1956 Suez crisis. This was empowered by section 4(4) of  the Foreign Compensation Act 1950,&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline3&quot; href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt; which provided that:&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/08/privacy-international-constitutional-barometer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/08/privacy-international-constitutional-barometer/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Public sneaking into private horizontally: the development of private law as supported by the Human Rights Act 1998</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case note: &lt;em&gt;Fearn and others v The Board of Trustees of the Tate Gallery&lt;/em&gt; [2019] EWHC 246 (Ch)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/08/public-sneaking-private-horizontally/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/08/public-sneaking-private-horizontally/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Extraditing suspects and safeguarding human rights - a tangled tale</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commentary on &lt;em&gt;Kyung Yip Kim v Ministry of Justice of New Zealand and another [2019] NZCA 209 &lt;/em&gt;and insights on the &lt;em&gt;Fugitive Offenders and Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Legislation (Amendment) Bill 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/06/extraditing-subjects-safeguarding-human-rights/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/06/extraditing-subjects-safeguarding-human-rights/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Coherence and consistency: the need to avoid judicial confusion and its consequences under the Human Rights Act 1998</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case Note: &lt;em&gt;In re Siobhan McLaughlin &lt;/em&gt;[2018] UKSC 48&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/03/coherence-consistency-need-avoid-judicial-confusion/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/03/coherence-consistency-need-avoid-judicial-confusion/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Darnley v Croydon Health Service NHS Trust: delineating duty and breach</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case Note: &lt;em&gt;Darnley v Croydon Health Service NHS Trust [2018] UKSC 50, [2018] 3 WLR 1153&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/03/darnley-croydon-health-service/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/03/darnley-croydon-health-service/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A tale of two systems: separation or separability of Hong Kong common law and Chinese socialist legal system?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case note: &lt;em&gt;Sixtus Leung v President of the Legislative Council  &lt;/em&gt;HCAL 1160, 1164, 1165, 1171 &amp;amp; 1178/2018&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/03/tale-two-systems-separation-separability-hong-kong/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/03/tale-two-systems-separation-separability-hong-kong/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Hoffmann vs Sumption – Reconciling the battle on contractual interpretation?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/02/hoffmann-sumption-reconciling-battle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/02/hoffmann-sumption-reconciling-battle/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>“I felt cheated”[1]: a lost opportunity for upholding a right to terminate life with dignity</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case note: &lt;em&gt;R (on the application of Conway) v Secretary of State for Justice&lt;/em&gt; (27 November 2018)&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline2&quot; href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/02/felt-cheated-lost-opportunity-upholding-right-terminate-life/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/02/felt-cheated-lost-opportunity-upholding-right-terminate-life/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The illegality of Russian intervention in Syria</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h5&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/02/illegality-russian-intervention-syria/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/02/illegality-russian-intervention-syria/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Creating easements with ease: *Re Ellenborough Park* test revisited</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case note: &lt;em&gt;Regency Villas Title Ltd v Diamond Resorts (Europe) Ltd&lt;/em&gt; [2018] UKSC 57&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/01/creating-easements-ease-ellenborough-park/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/01/creating-easements-ease-ellenborough-park/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A symphony of parliamentary sovereignty</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;– Case note: &lt;em&gt;Case C-621/18 Wightman v Secretary of State for Exiting the European Union&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2019/01/symphony-parliamentary-sovereignty/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/01/symphony-parliamentary-sovereignty/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Medical exceptionalism: Best Interests From a Human Rights Perspective</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case note: &lt;em&gt;Y v An NHS Trust and others [2018] UKSC 46&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2018/12/medical-exceptionalism-best-interests-human-rights/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/12/medical-exceptionalism-best-interests-human-rights/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>English Choice of Law in Contract Under the Rome I Regime: Is Flexibility Giving Way to Predictability?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The Rome I Regulation (593/2008/EC) is the EU regulation which governs the choice of law applicable to contractual obligations in civil and commercial matters. It replaces the 1980 Rome Convention and effects important structural changes to the rules for determining the applicable law, as well as the exceptions to those rules (the ‘choice of law gateways’). The English courts’ application of the gateways in the Rome Convention has been criticised as excessively flexible. While this view may be justified in relation to earlier cases decided on the Convention, there has been a gradual movement towards a more cautious judicial approach to both implied choice (Article 3) and the escape clause (Article 4), which was partly crystallised and partly precipitated by the changed architecture of these two provisions in the Rome I Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2018/10/english-choice-law-contract-rome-i-regime/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/10/english-choice-law-contract-rome-i-regime/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Undisclosed Principal: Limiting Liability for Negligent Misrepresentations</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Banca Nazionale del Lavoro SPA v Playboy Club London Limited and others&lt;/em&gt; [2018] UKSC 43 concerns a claim for pure economic loss due to a negligent misrepresentation. It sets a precedent for cases that concern a duty of care between a statement-maker and third party undisclosed principal. At first glance, the instant case appears consistent to &lt;em&gt;Hedley Byrne &amp;amp; Co Ltd v Heller &amp;amp; Partners Ltd&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;inline-reference&quot; id=&quot;inline1&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;. Yet, on closer examination, it contains several distinctive material facts.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2018/09/undisclosed-principal-limiting-liability-negligent-misrepresentations/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/09/undisclosed-principal-limiting-liability-negligent-misrepresentations/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The 'Live-in Requirement' for Foreign Domestic Helpers in Hong Kong: Fundamental Rights at Risk?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case note: &lt;em&gt;Lubiano v The Director of Immigration&lt;/em&gt; HCAL 210/2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2018/09/live-in-requirement-foreign-domestic-helpers-hong-kong/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/09/live-in-requirement-foreign-domestic-helpers-hong-kong/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>No Cake for You: The Legal Battle for Equal Treatment in Lee v McArthur &amp; Ors</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lee v McArthur &amp;amp; Ors&lt;/em&gt; [2016] NICA 39, commonly known as the ‘Gay Wedding Cake’ case, is currently awaiting judgment from the UK Supreme Court (‘UKSC’). &lt;em&gt;Lee&lt;/em&gt; promises to provide vital guidance on how conflicts between the LGBT and faith community should be resolved commercially. This article analyses the judgment handed down by the Northern Ireland Court of Appeal (‘NICA’) and concludes that, despite the controversy, an outcome against the bakery is legally unsurprising and desirable within a commercial context.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2018/09/no-cake-for-you-legal-battle-equal-treatment-lee-mcarthur/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/09/no-cake-for-you-legal-battle-equal-treatment-lee-mcarthur/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>European Integration, Brexit and Democracy: What do we do now?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past two decades, the European Union has experienced an increased disjuncture between its political vision for peace, prosperity and security and the democratic mandate of the people. This disconnect has been vociferously animated by sundry arguments of principle during the United Kingdom’s EU referendum in June 2016, the seismic decision by the UK to leave the EU as well as the continuing negotiations over exit terms between the UK government and the EU. When the European Union (Withdrawal) Act 2018 received Royal Assent two months ago,  it marked a weighty moment in Britain’s troubled history with Europe. It represented democratic resistance to the EU’s politically hegemonic tunnel vision. In this article, I want to make three arguments about an overly-scrutinised and perhaps fatigued project of the EU: European integration. First, I want to offer a theoretical explanation for faltering European integration. Second, I want to advance some reasons why we should be cautious about European integration post-Brexit. Finally, I will tentatively grapple with how European integration ought to be structured.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2018/08/european-integration-brexit-democracy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/08/european-integration-brexit-democracy/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Employees or Independent Contractors: What Defines a “Worker”?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pimlico Plumbers Limited v Smith&lt;/em&gt; [2018] UKSC 29 deals with several important issues concerning an intermediate category of working people falling between an “employee” under a contract of service and those who work for others as independent contractors. The final appeal decision clarifies the meaning of “worker” under section 230(3)(b) of the Employment Rights Act 1996 (‘ERA’), Regulation 2(1) of the Working Time Regulations 1998 (‘the Regulations’) and section 83(2) of the Equality Act 2010 (‘the Equality Act’).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2018/08/employees-independent-contractors-defines-worker/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/08/employees-independent-contractors-defines-worker/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Standard Bank Plc Deferred Prosecution Agreement</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h6 id=&quot;dear-editor&quot;&gt;Dear Editor,&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2016/03/standard-bank-plc-deferred-prosecution-agreement/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/03/standard-bank-plc-deferred-prosecution-agreement/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>What can legal academics add to the debate about private equity?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h6 id=&quot;dear-editor&quot;&gt;Dear Editor, &lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2016/03/legal-academics-add-debate-private-equity/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/03/legal-academics-add-debate-private-equity/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A Right to 'Truth' on the War on Terror</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h6 id=&quot;dear-editor&quot;&gt;Dear Editor,&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2016/02/right-truth-war-terror/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/02/right-truth-war-terror/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>UK/EU Referendum: Are there alternatives to Membership?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h6 id=&quot;dear-editor&quot;&gt;Dear Editor,&lt;/h6&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2016/01/eu-uk-referendum-alternatives-membership/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/01/eu-uk-referendum-alternatives-membership/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
