<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title></title>
   
   <link></link>
   <description>A student-run law journal seeking to provide a platform for high quality legal scholarship.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> </managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Private law protection of human rights from corporate abuses: deep and meaningful?</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/10/private-law-protection-human-rights-corporate-abuses/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/10/private-law-protection-human-rights-corporate-abuses/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Commentary on <em>Lungowe and others v Vedanta Resources plc and Kokola Copper Mines plc</em> [2019] UKSC 20<a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a></strong></p>

<p>The need to secure individual human rights from corporate malpractice is of increasing importance in recent years in light of industrial incidents causing considerable injury to individuals and damage to properties and the environment.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> The UK Supreme Court’s recent decision in <em>Lungowe v Vedanta Resources plc and Kokola Copper Mines plc</em>,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> commented as “the most important judicial decision in the field of business and human rights since the jurisdictional ruling of the United States Supreme Court in <em>Kiobel v Royal Dutch Petroleum</em> in 2013,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> is the latest entry on the English jurisprudence on the protection of human rights against corporate abuses and malpractices. Although formally a jurisdictional ruling, it has provided important insights on how English courts will assess whether a defendant corporation(s) has breached its duty of care to the relevant claimants. A duty of care owed by a private company, despite being a private law matter, has considerable implications for the necessary human rights protection that the law should offer in favour of stakeholders affected by corporate malpractices. An example of this would be a fundamental human right to health.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a> This article will focus on two issues: (i) the Supreme Court’s (“<strong>the Court</strong>”) approach to determining the existence of a duty of care owed by a corporation to others and breaches of such duty, and (ii) the approach to determining the proper forum for suing an anchor defendant.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> It argues that the Court’s approach to finding the existence of a duty of care is commendable but potentially analytically confusing. Similarly, concerning the Court’s approach to the determination of the proper forum in the present context, it argues that the Court’s approach improves the ability of the assessment to be tailored closer to the facts, but the cost of less predictable application of the law.</p>

<h5 id="facts-and-appellate-history">Facts and appellate history</h5>

<p>From Chingola in Zambia, 1,826 people claimed that Vedanta Resources plc (“<strong>Vedanta plc</strong>”) (an English holding company with a small office in London but controlled a huge amount of assets) breached its duty of care to ensure that its Zambian subsidiary (Konkola Copper Mines plc (“<strong>KCM plc</strong>”); biggest private employer in Zambia but had few assets of its own) would not harm the environment surrounding its mining sites and local communities. The claimants claimed compensation for personal injury, property damage, loss of income, amenity and enjoyment of land because of discharges from copper mines. In response, Vedanta plc and KCM plc argued that the English courts did not have jurisdiction to hear the claim and the proceedings should be stayed on <em>forum non conveniens</em> grounds. At the first instance,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> Coulson J granted jurisdiction over the claims and held that the case could not be fairly pursued in Zambia.</p>

<p>At the Court of Appeal,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> Simon LJ (with whom Jackson LJ and Asplin LJ agreed with) confirmed that the foreign citizens may pursue legal claims in England against English-based multinational companies for their overseas activities. On the claims, Simon LJ summarised the following principles at [83] about the determination of the existence of a duty of care owed by a parent company of a multinational corporation:-</p>

<p>● The starting point is the three-part test of foreseeability, proximity, and reasonableness from the seminal tort case of <em>Caparo Industries plc v Dickman</em>.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a></p>

<p>● A duty of care may be owed by a parent company to an employee of a subsidiary, or a party directly affected by the operations of that subsidiary. Such duty of care may arise where the company (a) has taken direct responsibility for devising a material health and safety policy the adequacy of which is the subject of the claim, or (b) controls the operations which give rise to the claim.</p>

<p>Simon LJ also held that England and Wales was the proper place to bring trial, and defended Coulson J’s decision as he was “entitled to view that it was inappropriate for the litigation to be conducted in parallel proceedings involving identical or virtually identical facts, witnesses and documents, in circumstances where the claim against Vedanta would in any event continue in England.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> Considerable emphasis was laid on a need to avoid similar proceedings in two jurisdictions. He further noted that if the claimants litigated against KCM plc in Zambia, they would not obtain justice for a number of reasons: (i) they would not be able to afford the cost of any legal representation even with their low levels of earnings in the first place,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a> (ii) Condition Fee Agreements are unlawful in Zambia and thus the claimants could not avail of it,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a> (iii) there was no prospect for the claimants to obtain legal aid,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a> (iv) prospect of <em>ad hoc</em> funding was unrealistic,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a> (v) no private lawyers with relevant experience were willing and capable of taking on such claims in Zambia,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> (vi) previous environmental litigations in Zambia had failed for various reasons,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a> and (vii) KCM plc was likely to adopt an obdurate approach to litigation in Zambia thus resulting in an enormous increase of time and cost.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a></p>

<p>The appeal to the Supreme Court raised three questions on jurisdiction, two of which are relevant to the discussion on the Court’s approach to jurisdiction and <em>forum non conveniens</em>: (i) whether England and Wales was the proper place to bring the claims, and (ii) even if Zambia would otherwise be the proper place, whether there was a real risk that the claimants would not obtain access to substantial justice in Zambia.</p>

<h5 id="lord-briggss-contextualised-approaches">Lord Briggs’s contextualised approaches</h5>

<h6 id="parent-companys-duty-of-care"><u>Parent company's duty of care</u></h6>

<p>Holding that ownership of a subsidiary company by a parent company does not impose a duty to take control of the management of the operations or business owned by the subsidiary, Lord Briggs noted that “everything depends on the extent to which, and the way in which, the parent availed himself of the opportunity to take over, intervene in, control, supervise or advise the management of the relevant operations … of the subsidiary.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> The intervention of the English-domiciled parent companies in the management of subsidiaries’ operations and their human rights and environmental performance may give rise to a duty of care to third parties, for example local communities. The human rights of such third parties is thus indirectly protected by prudent, or at least well-planned, corporate practices. Instead of focusing only on the subsidiary company itself, both the parent and subsidiary companies will be required to contribute to prudent corporate practices and mitigate the detrimental impacts of corporate practices on e.g. local communities. The duty is, moreover, not merely limited to health and safety issues. Moving on, Lord Briggs also refused to compartmentalise and categorise the cases and scenarios under which a parent company would be liable. In light of the lack of any limitations to models of management, Lord Briggs was “reluctant to seek to shoehorn all cases of the parent’s liability into specific categories of that kind, helpful though they will no doubt be for the purposes of analysis.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a></p>

<p>Lord Briggs argued that the existence of group-wide policies and guidelines <em>per se</em> and the parent’s expectation on the subsidiary to comply with them is not sufficient for finding a duty of care. It is necessary for the parent company, instead of merely proclaiming such policies, to “take active steps, by training, supervision and enforcement, to see that they are implemented by relevant subsidiaries.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> Alternatively, a parent company may incur a duty of care to a third party if, in its published materials, “[the company] holds itself out as exercising that degree of supervision and control of its subsidiaries, even if it does not in fact do so.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> In such circumstances, the parent company’s omission from acting may constitute an abdication of the responsibility which it has publicly undertaken. The published materials of Vedanta plc was held to show that the company had “asserted its own assumption of responsibility for the maintenance of proper standards of environmental control over the activities of the subsidiaries, and in particular the operations of the Mine … to show that it is well arguable that a sufficient level of intervention by Vedanta in the conduct of operations at the Mine may be demonstrable at trial…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a></p>

<h6 id="forum-non-conveniens-and-proper-place-for-trial"><u>*Forum non conveniens* and proper place for trial</u></h6>

<p>For the Respondents to persuade the Court to decline jurisdiction on the basis of <em>forum non conveniens</em>, two requirements must be satisfied:<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a> (i) they need to show that the foreign forum is “clearly more appropriate,” and (ii) “substantial justice” will be done at the foreign form – stay of proceedings will not be granted in favour of the defendant if “substantial justice” will not be done at the foreign forum. Firstly, under (i), in contrast to Coulson J’s and Simon LJ’s analysis based on the need to avoid parallel proceedings and judgements, Lord Briggs argued that the purpose of avoiding irreconcilable judgements should be balanced against other connecting factors which link the case with the foreign forum. As Vedanta plc had consented to submit to the jurisdiction of Zambian courts, the choice of the forum of litigation now enjoyed by the claimants renders the possibility of irreconcilable judgements no longer a decisive or conclusive answer to the question of the appropriateness of forum.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a> This is because it becomes possible for both parties to agree to litigate in Zambian courts. Coulson J’s determination on this point is thus an error of principle.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline25" href="#25">25</a> Lord Briggs then moved on to note that, while the risk of irreconcilable judgements was a relevant factor and contoured against holding Zambia as the proper forum, the other connecting factors in the present case showed that Zambia was “the overwhelmingly the proper place for the claim to be tried.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline26" href="#26">26</a> In such an assessment, “it is sensible to stand back and look at the matter in the round.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline27" href="#27">27</a></p>

<p>Moving on to the second limb of the <em>forum non conveniens</em> test, for the court to exercise discretion and permit English proceedings, it is necessary to satisfy the court “…by cogent evidence … there is a real risk that substantial justice will not be obtainable in that foreign jurisdiction.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline28" href="#28">28</a> Lord Briggs found in favour of the claimant that substantial justice will not be done if the claim was pursued in Zambia, the key issue being the lack of funding. While there existed various forms of funding, it was found that “most were unavailable but that the one which was in principle available would not attract a legal team which was both prepared to act, and able to do so with the requisite resources and experience.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline29" href="#29">29</a> The need for expert evidence and work in the present case, from the legal team representing the claimants, be “paid for as disbursements, but it will still need to be supervised by competent and experienced lawyers.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline30" href="#30">30</a> The “unavoidable scale and complexity of this case (wherever litigated)”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline31" href="#31">31</a> has led the judge to conclude, correctly in Lord Briggs’s opinion, that in light of the limited funding and legal resources available within Zambia, substantial justice could not be achieved in Zambian courts.</p>

<h5 id="implications-of-lungowe-and-future-developments">Implications of <em>Lungowe</em> and future developments</h5>

<h6 id="parent-company-liabilities"><u>Parent company liabilities</u></h6>

<p>To begin with, Lord Briggs’s judgement of the existence of a duty of care owed by parent companies is an important step towards enhancing corporate accountability for human rights violations. The contextualised approach at [49] focusing on the extent of intervention by the parent company into the subsidiary’s operations allow for a more accurate assessment of the actual scope of liability that should be borne by the parent. This is because the “human rights” under consideration in the present case are likely to be, in contrast to the fundamental rights found in the e.g. the European Convention on Human Rights,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline32" href="#32">32</a> of a socio-economic character. An example mentioned at the start of this article is a right to health under Article 12 of the International Convention on Economics, Social and Cultural Rights. This would be particularly important for countries like Zambia, a third-world country in a developing status and the nation’s social-economic infrastructure and rights protection are not as robust as first-world countries. Instead of imposing any direct judicial standards on the requisite standard of duty of care to be satisfied, Lord Briggs’s judgement has struck a delicate balance between the need to maintain (i) the need for autonomy and flexibility in corporate practices and (ii) the need for judicial oversight in monitoring multinational companies and their practices, in particular the subsidiaries, in less-developed countries across the globe.</p>

<p>Another point to note is the open-ended nature of the scope of liability borne by parent companies. It should be seen as an improvement from the seminal Court of Appeal case of <em>Chandler v Cape plc</em> in 2012.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline33" href="#33">33</a> In <em>Chandler</em>, Arden LJ laid down four requirements to be satisfied in order for the court to impose on a parent company responsibility for the health and safety of its subsidiary’s employees.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline34" href="#34">34</a> Arden LJ’s approach was more restrictive than Lord Briggs’s formulation for two reasons. Firstly, the <em>Chandler</em> duty of care only focused on the health and safety policies of the subsidiary company, instead of the general management of the “relevant operations” of the subsidiary. Lord Briggs’s formulation allows for a more expansive range of policies and practices to be covered in assessing whether the parent company should be adjudged to owe a duty of care to the relevant parties. The court enjoys a “broad supervisory spectrum”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline35" href="#35">35</a> in monitoring the policies and practices of the multinational corporation, based on the instructions of the parent company, as a whole. Secondly, and more importantly, Lord Briggs’s approach is not limited to the employees of the subsidiary company, but may include third parties affected by the corporation’s operation, for example local communities. This expands the scope of accountability of the parent company, thus encouraging them to be more mindful of the possible consequences and implications of their practices on potential stakeholders related or relevant to its business operations.</p>

<p>As a matter of legal analysis, Lord Briggs’s judgement can be seen as a scale for determining whether a parent company should be held to have owed a duty of care to the relevant stakeholders, and thus whether it has breached its duty of care (as adjudged to have existed). This scale is based on the extent of participation and intervention into the subsidiary’s operations. This, however, gives rise to the possible scenario and incentive of a hands-off parent company permitting its subsidiary to commit human rights abuses for business purposes,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline36" href="#36">36</a> yet to be adjudged to have not intervened sufficiently into the subsidiary’s operations and thus cannot be said to have owed any duty of care. Robert McCorquodale observes that this would undermine developments in human rights due diligence on the part of multinational corporations.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline37" href="#37">37</a> Omission on the part of the parent company may, therefore, not be seen as a breach of duty of care (since there could not be any duty of care in the first place). This is particularly problematic for vulnerable third parties, for example local communities, that do not have adequate resources to protect their neighbourhood and natural resources from being damaged by the business operations of subsidiaries of multinational corporations.</p>

<p>A possible remedy for this loophole may be found in the requirements offered by Arden LJ in <em>Chandler</em>. It is worthy to note that Arden LJ formulated the parent company’s involvement in the subsidiary’s business operations as “has or ought to have.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline38" href="#38">38</a> The “ought” part of the formulation is illuminating, as it allows the court to escape the analytical loophole mentioned in the foregoing paragraph and hold that the parent should have intervened in the first place. Instead of focusing on what the parent company has done or offered to do, the incorporation of Arden LJ’s analysis in Lord Briggs’s formulation could allow a court to find what the parent company should have done. This would also fit in nicely with Lord Briggs’s refusal to compartmentalise cases of parent’s liability at [50], as a type of case in which the parent should have asserted responsibility but nevertheless failed to. Alternatively, considerations over what the parent company should have done may be seen as an example of being “reasonable” to hold the company to have owed a duty of care under the <em>Caparo</em> test. Under Lords Brigg’s emphasis on the general management and operations of the subsidiary company, this may suggest that liability for omissions may encompass the parent company’s inaction in terms of ensuring that the subsidiary’s relevant management and operations would not be contrary to the human rights interests of stakeholders, in particular local communities and vulnerable individuals.</p>

<h6 id="forum-non-conveniens-and-proper-place-for-trial-1"><em><u>Forum non conveniens</u></em><u> and proper place for trial</u></h6>

<p>The continued application of the two-part test of <em>forum non conveniens</em> protects the legal and analytical certainty needed for such analysis. Such certainty is particularly crucial in the present context as it carries considerable implications on the proper role of a domestic court in deciding whether to intervene into a case which may be more appropriately held in a foreign court. The most important change brought by Lord Briggs’s judgement, it is submitted, is the diminished importance of the policy of avoiding parallel proceedings as a factor in determining the appropriate place for a trial involving an anchor defendant. On this point, Ekaterina Aristova argues that the policy of avoiding parallel proceedings had more force in the jurisdictional analysis of the judgement than the existence of any territorial connections between England and claims against the foreign subsidiary.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline39" href="#39">39</a> What was not resolved in Lord Briggs’s judgement is, however, the actual importance and position of the factor of (risk of) irreconcilable judgements in the first limb of the <em>forum non conveniens</em> test (the “clearly more appropriate” component). This is because, despite connecting factors now being given primary (or at least increased) importance in the first limb of the test, it is unclear the extent to which the need to avoid parallel proceedings should be given weight. Given such an important change in the method of determining proper forum, Lord Briggs could have clarified the analytical flow in determining whether an English court is the proper forum for hearing cases like <em>Lungowe</em>.</p>

<p>The identification of proper forum also raises concerns about the future of litigating negligence claims against English-domiciled parent companies in English courts. Following <em>Lungowe</em>, English courts will not treat jurisdictional rules as decisive of the question of proper forum, but will focus more on the balance of connecting factors to determine where the proper forum for litigating claims against the foreign subsidiary is. This takes place in the final step of the <em>forum non conveniens</em> test - only after having determined that the impugned foreign court is the appropriate forum for the trial. The outcome of the <em>forum non conveniens</em> inquiry will now be dependent on the achievement of substantial justice in the foreign court.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline40" href="#40">40</a> It must not be ignored, however, that “substantial justice” was not given a comprehensive elaboration in terms of the possible scope of considerations that can arise under it. Putting such criticism to its strongest, “substantial justice” may be interpreted as a wild card for the court to grant English proceedings in order to allow claimants to avail themselves of the comprehensive English tort rules in pursuing claims against multinational corporations. That being said, it is submitted that Lord Briggs’s analysis is unlikely to be interpreted as such. This is because his analysis is, appropriately, focused on the need to ensure access to justice for the disadvantaged claimants. Given access to justice (in particular, right of access to courts) has always been one of the rights most cherished by English courts in common law,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline41" href="#41">41</a> Lord Briggs’s focus on access to justice is a prudent formulation of what “substantial justice” should entail. The key should always be on the possibility of access to justice and allowing claimants to have their claims properly heard and assessed.</p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p>The need to protect the human rights of stakeholders in the context of the business operations of multinational corporations presents a delicate challenge for the courts. Tasked with balancing the need for robust human rights protection and restraint from excessive judicial intervention in corporate practices and possible hearings in foreign forums, <em>Lungowe</em> has struck a commendable balance between the two. It has also presented a breath of fresh air on important questions of corporate accountability in private law, which has considerable implications on human rights protection indirectly offered by the court. Although a full assessment of Lord Briggs’s judgement cannot be conducted in the limited space of this commentary, it is clear that it represents an important step in enhancing human rights protection for stakeholders in business operations of multinational corporations across an increasingly globalised business environment.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
Many thanks to Steve Lee (LLB ‘19, PCLL ‘20 HKU)  for his comments on an earlier draft. All errors remain on the author’s own.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
For example, see <em>ONCA Das v George Weston Limited and others</em> (2018) ONCA 1053 (Ontario Court of Appeal) and <em>Okpabi and others v Royal Dutch Shell</em> [2018] EWCA Civ 191 (English Court of Appeal).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
[2019] UKSC 20.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
Doug Cassel, “<em>Vedanta v Lungowe</em> Symposium: Beyond <em>Vedanta</em> - Reconciling Tort Law with International Human Rights Norms” (OpinioJuris, 19th April 2019) (<a href="http://opiniojuris.org/2019/04/19/vedanta-v-lungowe-symposium-beyond-vedanta-reconciling-tort-law-with-international-human-rights-norms%EF%BB%BF/">http://opiniojuris.org/2019/04/19/vedanta-v-lungowe-symposium-beyond-vedanta-reconciling-tort-law-with-international-human-rights-norms%EF%BB%BF/</a>) (Accessed 26th August 2019).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
Article 12, International Covenant on Social, Economics and Cultural Rights.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
An anchor defendant in a litigation against a multinational corporation with subsidiaries in foreign countries refers to the defendant, usually the foreign subsidiary, that in order to sue the subsidiary, the parent company must be sued first. The key is whether the foreign company is a  “necessary and proper party” (Civil Procedure Rules Practice Direction 6B Rule 3.1(3)) to the litigation in a suit against a domestic defendant.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
[2016] EWHC 975.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
[2017] EWCA Civ 1528.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
[1990] UKHL 2.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
(n 8) [117].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
ibid [124].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
ibid [125].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
ibid [126].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
ibid [127].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
ibid [128].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
ibid [129].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
ibid [130].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
(n 3) [49].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
ibid [51].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
ibid [53].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
ibid.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
ibid [61].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="23" href="#inline23">[23]</a>
This follows from the European Court of Justice’s (“<strong>ECJ</strong>”) decision in C-281/02 <em>Owusu v Jackson</em> [2005]. In <em>Owusu</em>, the ECJ held that contrary to earlier English jurisprudence, Article 4.1 of the Recast Brussels Regulation conferred a right on any claimant (regardless of domicile) to sue an English domiciled defendant in England, free from jurisdictional challenge on <em>forum non conveniens</em> grounds, even where the competing candidates for jurisdiction were England (part of a member state) and some other non-member state.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="24" href="#inline24">[24]</a>
(n 3) [75].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="25" href="#inline25">[25]</a>
ibid [84].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="26" href="#inline26">[26]</a>
ibid [85].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="27" href="#inline27">[27]</a>
ibid [87].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="28" href="#inline28">[28]</a>
ibid [88].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="29" href="#inline29">[29]</a>
ibid [93].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="30" href="#inline30">[30]</a>
ibid [94].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="31" href="#inline31">[31]</a>
ibid [95].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="32" href="#inline32">[32]</a>
This refers to the rights under Articles 2-14 of the Convention.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="33" href="#inline33">[33]</a>
[2012] EWCA Civ 525.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="34" href="#inline34">[34]</a>
ibid [80].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="35" href="#inline35">[35]</a>
(n 4).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="36" href="#inline36">[36]</a>
(n 4).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="37" href="#inline37">[37]</a>
Robert McCorquodale, “<em>Vedanta v Lungowe</em> Symposium: Duty of Care of Parent Companies” (OpinioJuris, 18th April 2019) (<a href="http://opiniojuris.org/2019/04/18/symposium-duty-of-care-of-parent-companies/">http://opiniojuris.org/2019/04/18/symposium-duty-of-care-of-parent-companies/</a>) (Accessed 1st September 2019).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="38" href="#inline38">[38]</a>
For example, the second requirement of <em>Chandler</em> is that “The parent either has or ought to have some knowledge about health and safety issues in respect of the subsidiary’s business” (at [80]).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="39" href="#inline39">[39]</a>
Ekaterina Aristova, “UK Supreme Court decision in Vedanta: Finding a proper balance between Brussels I and the English common law rules of jurisdiction” (Conflictoflaws.net, 24th April 2019) (<a href="http://conflictoflaws.net/2019/uk-supreme-court-decision-in-vedanta-finding-a-proper-balance-between-brussels-i-and-the-english-common-law-rules-of-jurisdiction/">http://conflictoflaws.net/2019/uk-supreme-court-decision-in-vedanta-finding-a-proper-balance-between-brussels-i-and-the-english-common-law-rules-of-jurisdiction/</a>) (Accessed 1st September 2019).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="40" href="#inline40">[40]</a>
In <em>Lungowe</em>, the “substantial justice” issue is phrased by Coulson J (approved by Lord Briggs) as a matter of “access to justice” ([2019] UKSC 20, at [89]).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="41" href="#inline41">[41]</a>
On the importance of justice concerns for courts, see Richard Clayton, “The Empire Strikes Back: Common Law Rights and the Human Rights Act” [2015] (1) <em>Public Law</em> 3-12.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>The delicate balance between Carl Schmitt’s constituent power and liberal constitutionalism: a misunderstood and over-complicated dichotomy?</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/09/delicate-balance-carl-schmitt-constituent-power-liberal-constitutionalism/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/09/delicate-balance-carl-schmitt-constituent-power-liberal-constitutionalism/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>The tension between constituent power and a liberal theory of constitutionalism is important in constitutional theory as they paint very different perceptions of the nature of authority in a constitution. Constituent power is “the power through which the prince’s power to rule was authorised,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a> and its primary function is to “specify in constitutional language the ultimate source of authority of the state.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> This article focuses on the work of Carl Schmitt, as it is suggested as a “powerful corrective to the distortions of normativism.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> It is clearly anti-liberal and decisionist, providing a direct ground for critical evaluation of the alleged tension. In a similar vein, calls for executive action and/or dominance in times of emergency or crisis renders it necessary to understand whether the assumption of (near) absolute power by the executive in such times entails the death of liberal constitutionalism.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> This article argues that the concept of constituent power is only anathema to liberal constitutionalism if their relationship is conceived as dichotomous without any mutually inclusive aspects. Three arguments will be made. Firstly, by analysing Schmitt’s conception of constituent power and its perceived contradistinctions against liberal constitutionalism, it will be shown that the relationship between constituent power and liberal constitutionalism is dichotomous only if constituent power is conceived as external to the legal order. It will then narrow down the focus to the issue of emergency, contending that it does not require the law to recede and be totally suspended, and the concept of constituent power can be reconciled with liberal constitutionalism. Last but not the least, using the recent rumors of the use of the Emergency Regulations Ordinance (Cap. 241) (“<strong>ERO</strong>”) by the Hong Kong Government to deal with various protests and clashes since early June 2019, it will be shown that limitations on the Executive’s power is crucial in order for Schmitt’s concept of constituent power and a liberal theory of constitutionalism to be reconciled. This article will come to the conclusion that Schmitt’s refusal to recognise the broader political and legal contexts underpinning the concept of constituent power is the main reason why it may be anathema to liberal constitutionalism.</p>

<p><strong>Schmitt’s unnecessarily dichotomous conception of the relationship between constituent power and a liberal theory of constitutionalism</strong></p>

<p>For Schmitt, the sovereign bears constituent power: “sovereign is he who decides on the exception,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a> which cannot be derived solely from a general norm. It is a power which has the ultimate say in a political regime, unconstrained by any norms. His insistence on constituent power as the subject of a constitution denies the possibility of a closed, purely normative constitutional system.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> From this stance, it is unmistakable that Schmitt is antagonistic against a liberal theory of constitutionalism. The sovereign decision is the absolute beginning. His conception of constituent power is clearly anathema to liberal constitutionalism. Taken to its logical extreme, Schmitt’s conception of constituent power in <em>Political Theology</em> forms the basis for an “authoritarian exceptionless exception.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> Based on the omnipotence of the sovereign, it has the absolute discretion to determine what “constitutes” an exception, without any constraints from any other parties, rules, or norms whatsoever. The untrammeled absolute power the sovereign enjoys here in determining what constitutes an exception and what to do with such “exception” illustrates the possibly endless power the sovereign may be said to possess.  This is an accurate observation as the exception which the sovereign decides on may be easily normalised as a daily occurrence. The power to authorise so is unchecked. The utilisation of extraordinary powers in cases of the now-normalised “exceptional” circumstances is antagonistic against a liberal constitutionalist’s propositions for checks and balances and rooting the foundation of extraordinary powers in a <em>legal</em> source.</p>

<p>Before proceeding to scrutinise Schmitt’s propositions, a liberal theory of constitutionalism should first be introduced. In contradistinction to Schmitt’s absolutist picture, Friedrich Hayek offers a remarkably liberal and norm-based theory of constitutionalism. For Hayek, the authority of a legislator should rest on something distinguished from “an act of will on a particular matter in hand.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> Such authority cannot rest solely upon the discretion of the legislator himself. Instead, such power “rests on a common opinion about certain attributes which the laws he produces ought to possess.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a> The power must be shaped and/or contributed by such attributes, instead of stemming from any unpredictable and variable absolute discretion of a legislator. Moreover, there is no logical necessity that the ultimate power must be omnipotent. Such ultimate power is “a negative power, but as a power of withholding allegiance it limits all positive power.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> The ultimate authority authorising all actions of the government constraints the government’s actions. The only true side of law is <em>nomos</em>, and it should neither dictate nor direct the actions of the people. For Schmitt, the true side of law is <em>thesis</em> — the law of will: imposed organisation. Schmitt’s main attack on liberalism is based on the inevitable existence of the exception. There is no normative basis which it may be seen to rest or be constrained on.</p>

<p>What Schmitt fails to realise, however, is that his dichotomous conception of the relationship between constituent power and liberal constitutionalism has blinded him from the position the former has within the latter. Loughlin recognised<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a>  that for Schmitt, the significance of constituent power lies in the fact that the state continues to evolve, expressing “the principle of dynamic emergence of political unity, of the process of constantly renewed formation and emergence of this unity from a fundamental or ultimately effective power …”.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a> Constituent power also expresses the formative process by which that sovereign will exhibits itself through time.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a>  Here is where Schmitt misses the point: the formative process of exhibition and decision-making can and necessarily have recourse to legal norms; there can be fundamental norms which the sovereign is subjected to. The <em>authorisation</em> from constituent power in terms of the decisions that can be adopted can nevertheless be subjected to liberal norms, such as the rule of law. For example, the collective autonomy of the people to uphold the rule of law can control the exercise of ultimate authority <em>for the purpose of</em> upholding the desired norms. Schmitt, however, only focused on the formation of the unity <em>itself</em>, but not the role of this unity in conferring power to the government. The formation of the unity and its authorisation of the ruler’s power are separate questions, but Schmitt’s conflation of them has blinded him from the possibility of liberal norms underpinning the authorisation of power. The collective autonomy of the people as vested in the ruler to make decisions does not have to be dichotomised with the norms that the community of people decides to uphold. From this lens, the exercise of constituent power is part of the liberal constitutional order. This gives crucial insight into the second inquiry of this article: the conception of constituent power in the context of emergency.</p>

<p><strong>The peaceful co-existence of constituent power and liberal constitutionalism in times of emergency</strong></p>

<p>The recent expanded uses of emergency power that suspend normal constitutional protections have rejuvenated interest on Schmitt’s distinction between the norm and exception as the analytical framework for relevant constitutional measures.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a> For Schmitt, the exception can be “best characterised as a case of extreme peril…It cannot be circumscribed factually and made to conform to a preformed law.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> If actions in an emergency are not subject to controls, which a liberal theory of constitutionalism would require, it should become clear who the sovereign is.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a> In order for the executive to respond to emergencies effectively, constituent power must be unlimited in authorising the range of responses it can offer, regardless of extremity. The exception is characterised by principally unlimited authority, entailing the suspension of the entire existing legal order: “the state remains, whereas the law recedes.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> Constituent power gives unlimited authority for the ruler to do whatever he deems necessary: it is not subjected to controls of any sort. This contrasts with a liberal constitutionalist’s, for example Hayek, claim that such exercise of power should still be constrained. The key is to limit the power that <em>authorises</em> the government’s powers and actions.</p>

<p>The need to decide on the exception emphasises the central role of political decision-makers who decide on how to deal with it on a case-by-case basis. Schmitt’s conception of constituent power “denies that law’s authority can be found on the intrinsic qualities of legal order.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> His account, however, is flawed; by correcting this logical fallacy, the tension between constituent power and liberal constitutionalism can be resolved. To begin with, Dyzenhaus noted that Schmitt was unable to locate authority in something external because it is “drawn to claim that the basis is quasi-legal.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a> This is reflected in Schmitt’s insistence for a normal situation to exist in order to determine whether the nation is still in a normal situation or it has entered into a state of emergency. In deciding so, the executive has to start from the norm, which delineates the normal situations of a constitutional order. This is because the power authorising the government’s power to make emergency measures has, at the very minimum, part of its basis in the norm <em>itself</em>. Without recourse to or starting from the general norm, the exception may become the norm itself, as it has nothing to be “exceptional” from. Given the necessary involvement of a “norm,” the concept of constituent power can therefore be reconciled with liberal constitutionalism. The power which authorises the executive to adopt emergency measures does not spring out from nowhere, but from the norm underpinning the normal situation as recognised by the liberal constitution. For example, for a liberal state to declare martial law, it is necessary for the power making the decision to enter into a state of emergency to find in the general norm situations or conditions which <em>allow</em> such state of emergency to be declared. The move from a state of normal law to martial law has to start with an examination of the normal law itself, and whether its inability to tackle the alleged emergency warrants exceptions to be made <em>to</em> the normal law.</p>

<p>However, to further rescue the concept of constituent power from Schmitt’s extreme stance, it is necessary to briefly examine his views on the influence of politics on law. Schmitt’s systematic thinking, in reducing the concept of the “political” to “friend” and “enemy,” has led him to conceive emergency, based on constituent power, as a “battering ram”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> against liberal democracy. His conception of law, that “all law is ‘situational law,’“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> is “intrinsically bound up with a political struggle.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a> Once the “struggle” of the exception triumphs over the normal situation, the latter is seen as “defeated;” the exception’s “victory” awards the executive an unlimited authorisation to enact emergency measures. It is questionable, however, whether the concept of “political” has to be reduced to “friend” and “enemy” in order to justify the application of emergency measures. As Scheuerman observes, Schmitt’s analysis of emergency government “neglects its complex political origins.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a> It focuses excessively on the formation and constant renewal of the power <em>itself</em>, neglecting any common interests which competing concerns in politics may have or compromise on.  Here is where liberal constitutionalism can provide an answer: to safeguard the sustainability of the norms the liberal constitutional order is found on. Once the focus of constituent power is broadened to encapsulate the objectives of the authorising the use of emergency powers and “malleable recent social trends,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a> instead of only pestering on the formation and history of constituent power itself, it may be re-conceptualised as the starting point for ending the exceptional situation and return to the normal order. Historical givens, despite providing a solid ground for a framework of exception, is inadequate. It tends to neglect the reasons for emergency and the objectives of emergency measures. The stakeholders within the “political” do not have to be dichotomised into an opposing relationship of friend and enemy.</p>

<p>Once the competing interests underlying norms and exceptions are no longer contradistinguished from one another in the Schmittian sense, constituent power can be reconciled with a liberal theory of constitutionalism in acknowledging the existence of mutually competing interests. No particular stance and interests would enjoy an absolute status over another. In order to reconcile with the concept of constituent power, liberal constitutionalists should view the state of emergency as “a crucial tool enabling public reassurance in the short run without creating long-run damage to foundational commitments to freedom and the rule of law.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline25" href="#25">25</a> Constituent power, as the ultimate authority for the executive to act for the purpose of safeguarding commitments to liberal ideals, works alongside liberal constitutionalism to correct the state the exceptional situation and return it to normal.</p>

<p><strong>The Emergency Regulations Ordinance (Cap. 241)</strong></p>

<p>The ERO empowers the Chief Executive of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region to enact a wide but exhaustive range of regulations<a class="inline-reference" id="inline26" href="#26">26</a> “whatsoever which he may consider desirable in the public interest.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline27" href="#27">27</a> Any regulations made under section 2(2) would, moreover, be “continue in force until repealed by order of the Chief Executive in Council.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline28" href="#28">28</a> Moreover, any regulations enacted under section 2(2) would “have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline29" href="#29">29</a> When read together, sections 2(2) and 2(3) or 2(4) would suggest that unlimited power is bestowed upon the Chief Executive in the selected area(s) (s)he chooses to legislate on. Instead of being limited by any external restraints (say, for example, a judicial review action which, given the generality of the language under the ERO, is unlikely to succeed), the Chief Executive has unlimited power to legislate in any terms (s)he desires to be in the public interest. Moreover, the language of section 2(1) epitomises Schmitt’s conception of the exception. Instead of requiring any approval by any other institutional bodies, for example the Executive Council or the Legislative Council, the power to make regulations under section 2(1) only refers to the Chief Executive himself and himself only. This opens the possibility of a significant threat being posed to the liberties which citizens would ordinarily enjoy – in times of alleged emergency or public danger, civil liberties may be disregarded significantly (if not completely) and there are no executive or legislative checks against it.</p>

<p>Section 2(3) provides the only statutory method for terminating a regulation enacted under section 2(1) and 2(2) of the ERO. This means that the termination of any emergency regulation would, on a literal interpretation of the Ordinance, be at the absolute discretion of the Chief Executive in Council. Whilst any predictions to the Chief Executive’s use of the Ordinance is beyond the scope of this article, it is sufficient to note that the civil liberties of over seven million Hong Kong citizens would lie in her sole discretion. The lack of any principles or rules guiding the return to normalcy under the Ordinance further exposes the potential dangers to liberal constitutionalism posed by the Ordinance. Instead of being required to repeal any emergency regulations over a particular period of time, or inserting mandatorily such regulations with sunset clauses, the Ordinance provides no hints as to normalcy can and should be achieved (or returned to) once the emergency regulations are enacted. Any approaches to the Ordinance and the enactment of regulations must, for at least the purpose of restoring the stability and orderliness of the Hong Kong society, bear in mind the protection of a liberal constitutional order and the integrity of the legal system.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>Constituent power is a powerful concept in illustrating the ultimate authority of the state and justifying the ruler’s authority to act. Schmitt’s wickedly ingenious illustration of the unlimitedness of the exception and its authority to respond to emergencies, whilst compelling, risks unnecessarily dichotomising the relationship between constituent power and liberal constitutionalism. Although a thorough examination of Schmitt’s conception and critique against it cannot be examined in the limited space of this article, it is clear that the concept of constituent power is not anathema to a theory of liberal constitutionalism: they can work together to uphold the liberal constitutional order, and safeguard it from falling into a permanent state of emergency.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
Martin Loughlin, “The Concept of Constituent Power” (2014) 13 <em>European Journal of Political Theory</em> 218, 219.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
ibid 220.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
Martin Loughlin, “Why Read Carl Schmitt?” in Christoph Bezemek, Michael Potacs and Alexander Somek (eds), <em>Vienna Lectures on Legal Philosophy</em>, <em>volume 1</em> (Oxford; Hart, 2018) 63.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
A recent example is rumors of use of the Emergency Regulations Ordinance (Cap. 241) by the Hong Kong Government to deal with the ongoing protests in the city against, <em>inter alia</em>, (i) the attempted (now failed) legislation Fugitive Offenders and Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Legislation (Amendment) Bill 2019 and (ii) alleged incidents of police violence since early June 2019. “Hong Kong leader Carrie Lam says protests will be addressed with local laws, amid rumors of emergency legislation” (Hong Kong Free Press, 27th August 2019) (<a href="https://www.hongkongfp.com/2019/08/27/hong-kong-leader-carrie-lam-says-protests-will-addressed-local-laws-amid-rumours-emergency-legislation/">https://www.hongkongfp.com/2019/08/27/hong-kong-leader-carrie-lam-says-protests-will-addressed-local-laws-amid-rumours-emergency-legislation/</a>) (Accessed 27th August 2019). For an article discussing the controversial 2019 extradition bill and its perceived defects (as a result of, <em>inter alia</em>, excessive executive discretion in the extradition process and ineffective judicial control), see Thomas Yeon and Claudia Tam, “Extraditing suspects and safeguarding human rights – a tangled tale” <em>LSE Law Review Blog</em> (25th June 2019).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
Carl Schmitt, <em>Political Theology</em> (G Schwab tr, Chicago: Chicago University Press, 2005) 5.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
Hans Lindahl (2007), “Constituent Power and Reflexive Identity: Towards an Ontology of Collective Selfhood” in Martin Loughlin and Neil Walker (eds), <em>The Paradox of Constitutionalism: Constituent Power and Constitutional Law</em> (Oxford University Press 2007) 12.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
Owen Gross, “The Normless and Exceptionless Exception: Carl Schmitt’s Theory of Emergency Powers and the Norm Exception Dichotomy” (2000) 21 <em>Cardozo Law Review</em> 1825, 1829.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
Frederick Hayek (1973), <em>Law, Legislation and Liberty, Volume 1</em> (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1973) 92.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
ibid.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
ibid 93.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
(n 1) 225.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
Carl Schmitt, <em>Constitutional Theory</em> (1928; Duke University Press 2008) 61.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
ibid 62.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
(n 3) 51.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
(n 5) 6.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
ibid 6.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
ibid 11.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
David Dyzenhaus, “Constitutionalism in an Old Key: Legality and Constituent Power” (2012) 1 <em>Global Constitutionalism</em> 229, 233.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
ibid.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
Bruce Ackerman, “The Emergency Constitution” (2004) 113 <em>Yale Law Journal</em> 1029, 1044.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
(n 4) 13.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
(n 3) 64.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="23" href="#inline23">[23]</a>
William Scheuerman, “Emergency Powers and the Rule of Law after 9/11” (2006) 14 <em>Journal of Political Philosophy</em> 61, 64.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="24" href="#inline24">[24]</a>
ibid.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="25" href="#inline25">[25]</a>
(n 20).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="26" href="#inline26">[26]</a>
Section 2(2) ERO.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="27" href="#inline27">[27]</a>
ibid section 2(1).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="28" href="#inline28">[28]</a>
(n 26) section 2(3).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="29" href="#inline29">[29]</a>
(n 26) section 2(4).</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Public sneaking into private horizontally: the development of private law as supported by the Human Rights Act 1998</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/08/public-sneaking-private-horizontally/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/08/public-sneaking-private-horizontally/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Case note: <em>Fearn and others v The Board of Trustees of the Tate Gallery</em> [2019] EWHC 246 (Ch)</strong></p>

<p>The incorporation of the European Convention on Human Rights (“<strong>ECHR</strong>”) into domestic law under the Human Rights Act 1998 (“<strong>HRA</strong>”) is not solely concerned with actions against the institutions of the State, otherwise categorised as “core” public authorities.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a> It also concerns what is come to known as “horizontal effect” - that private litigants may have recourse to Convention rights during their dispute by virtue of requiring the court, based on the cause of action of a claimant, to act compatibly with the Convention.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> The content of the cause of action(s) relied on the Claimant are supported by Convention norms, instead of substituting the common law or statutory cause of action in question. <em>Fearn and others v The Board of Trustees of the Tate Gallery</em><a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> provides an example of the role of courts in the context of horizontal effect of the Human Rights Act, in this case attempting to fill the gap in the common law action of tort of nuisance. This case note focuses primarily on the approach of Mann J in determining whether a claimed privacy from overlooking can be protected by the tort of nuisance. It argues that a principled and restrained judicial approach is the best in delineating the court’s role of infusing Convention norms into disputes between private parties under s.6(3)(a) HRA 1998.</p>

<h5 id="facts-and-summary-of-judgement">Facts and summary of judgement</h5>

<p>The flats in question were in a development adjacent to the Tate Modern art gallery. Their living areas looked directly onto a viewing gallery which was open to the visitors of the museum. The flats had winter gardens which had wall-to-ceiling windows. The gardens were used by the claimants as part of their living accommodation. Visitors using the gallery had an uninterrupted view of the living areas of the flats.</p>

<p>The claimants alleged that they were the subject of scrutiny by many visitors of the gallery. They submitted that they had a cause of action in nuisance, and argued that they could rely on their right to privacy under Article 8 on the basis that the Defendant is a “hybrid public authority” under s.6(3)(b) HRA 1998.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> In arguing that the Defendants are liable in nuisance, it seeks to bridge the gap between the tort of nuisance and the acts of overlooking in question, relying on the Human Rights Act, and in particular Article 8 of the Convention. The Claimant’s submissions on the role of Article 8 in developing the tort of nuisance are twofold:<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a></p>

<p>● Privacy is an aspect of amenity of land. Article 8 reinforces claims to privacy, and courts are now obliged to develop the law so as to give effect to that right of privacy by extending (if necessary) the law of nuisance to protect it. This is mirrored by the extension of the law of confidence to protect private information.</p>

<p>● The nuisance is the operation of the gallery as a viewing gallery, from which there is afforded a view into their flats which is inevitable and which visitors take advantage of, to an extent which affects the use and enjoyment of the flats because it encroaches on and invades their privacy.</p>

<p>Having found that the Defendant is not a “hybrid public authority” under s.6(3)(b),<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> Mann J proceeded to dealt with the core issue of the case and the focus of this case note: the tort of nuisance claim as based on the right to private and family life under Article  8 ECHR.</p>

<h5 id="the-role-of-the-human-rights-act-in-supplying-convention-norms-to-private-actions-the-tort-of-nuisance">The role of the Human Rights Act in supplying Convention norms to private actions: the tort of nuisance</h5>

<h6 id="the-common-law-reaching-out-to-the-human-rights-act-and-convention-norm"><u>The common law reaching out to the Human Rights Act and Convention norm</u></h6>

<p>Mann J began by noting that the tort of nuisance, absent statute, would probably have been capable, as a matter of principle, of protecting privacy rights, at least in a domestic home.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> The Defendant’s concession that deliberate overlooking could give rise to nuisance accompanied by malice suggests that, given the right circumstances, a deliberate act of overlooking could amount to actionable nuisance. Having set out the contours of the common law action, Mann J then moved on to observe that, in the case if there are any doubts as to the ability of nuisance to form a cause of action in the present case, the doubt “has been removed by the Human Rights Act and Article 8,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> which contains a right to respect for an individual’s private and family life and his come. This reinforces the relatively limited and restrained role of Convention norms when the court is adjudicating private disputes: the primary emphasis of protection of privacy horizontally remains in tort law. Convention norms articulating a right to private and family life, while accurately reflecting the position which the individual should be restored in the case of a successful nuisance action, nevertheless should only be consulted in the case of any doubts as to the nature and contours of the common law nuisance action.</p>

<p>Mann J then moved on to note that the notion of “home” is expressly referred to in the present case, stating that “a person has a reasonable expectation of privacy in relation to much of what occurs in the home and in relation to the home itself.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a> The notion of “home” here as employed, it is submitted, is sufficiently expansive to incorporate issues which are not covered by the common law of nuisance itself. It opens up considerations relevant to an individual’s privacy in a private place (in this place his home), and thus considerations under Article 8, which were originally excluded from consideration due to the court’s conclusion on the s.6(3)(b) issue. At this point, Mann J relied on <em>McKennitt v Ash</em> [2008] to extend the tort of nuisance to cover the alleged tortious actions: that “external prying into a home would contravene the privacy protected by Article 8. It could be done by e.g. particular acts of directed and intentional overlooking, if the circumstances justified it.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> The cause of action resulting from an alleged act of prying does not arise under Article 8 ECHR, but by developing existing causes of action.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a> This is the correct and an appropriately restrained judicial approach to the court’s development of the common law in the HRA era. Although the courts cannot a new cause of action based on Convention rights, it is possible for it to fulfil its role of acting compatibly with the Convention by developing existing cause of actions.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a></p>

<p>Given the bridge between common law and HRA is bridged by <em>McKennitt</em>, it is worthy to examine it and its relationship with the present case. Focusing on the notion of home, Buxton LJ noted that Article 8 imposes “not merely negative but positive obligations” on the State.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a> Following so, the effect of s.6 HRA 1998 is that in order to find a breach of confidence, it would be necessary to look into Convention jurisprudence.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a> Buxton LJ also observed that it is possible to draw an analogy between security or stability of the residence with the issue of privacy within the home; it is “intrusive and distressing for Ms McKennitt’s household minutiate to be exposed to curious eyes.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> The basis of a positive obligation to develop a common law cause of action based on the Convention requirements thus lies at the root of section 6. Without such connection, courts cannot simply resort to Convention rights by drawing analogies or comparisons between notions which appear to concern similar issues (e.g. “home”, “privacy” etc.). The court’s duty to act compatibly with the Convention and subsequent inclusion of Convention norms and principles in private law tort claims, otherwise known as “indirect horizontal effect,” is reflected in its modification of common law principles to reflect the relevant fundamental right(s) an individual enjoys under the Convention.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a></p>

<h6 id="support-from-the-human-rights-act-enriching-common-law-jurisprudence"><u>Support from the Human Rights Act: enriching common law jurisprudence</u></h6>

<p>Mann J noted that since the enactment of the HRA 1998, the law of nuisance “ought to be and is capable of protecting privacy rights from overlooking in an appropriate case.” If such development is not made by the courts, there would be “a gap in the protection of privacy in the home where e.g. a landowner used his/her land to spy on a neighbour unreasonably.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> Together with his reliance on <em>McKennitt v Ash</em>, it appears that the “bridge” in question that brings norms underlying the Convention and the concerns of the common law tort of nuisance is supported by two issues: (i) the notion of the “home” as expressly stated and referred to by the litigating parties in the present case, and (ii) the values and expectations associated with privacy and the concept of a “home.” Commenting on the court’s approach to the horizontal effect of Convention rights, Phillipson observed that the courts’ approach in finding values applicable to the situation before them is an instance of identifying some broad principles that should be taken into account. This differs sharply from saying that the individual “has” rights.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> None of the cases concerning the protection of individual privacy under tort law post-HRA 1998, from <em>Campbell v Mirror Group Newspapers</em> to <em>Fearn</em>, has accepted full or direct horizontal effect of Convention rights. A private litigant is not allowed to invoke a Convention right directly against another private individual, and then asking courts to adjudicate on the merits of the Convention rights claim directly.</p>

<p>The ultimate concern in question, as the courts’ approach demonstrates, is the substance of the common law on which, in light of the incorporation of Convention rights into domestic law under HRA 1998, the parties will be entitled to protection on. This is generally consistent with domestic courts’ previous approaches to the issue of indirect horizontal effect of Convention rights in, <em>inter alia</em>, <em>Campbell</em> and <em>Douglas v Hello! Ltd</em>.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a> In <em>Douglas</em>, it was stated that it was “no longer the case” that “Strasbourg provides no definite answer to the question of whether the Convention requires states to provide a privacy remedy against private actors.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> The seminal ECHR case of <em>Von Hannover v Germany</em>, in which the ECtHR recognised the possibility of a positive obligation on the part of the State to protect an individual’s Article 8 right,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> was cited by the Court of Appeal as a direct authority for finding a positive obligation on the part of the State to ensure that a private remedy is available for the claimants in the case of a successful action.</p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p><em>Tate Modern</em> is an interesting decision illustrating how the HRA shapes the development of domestic law. It shows that the Act, despite having no direct bearing on private actions, can nevertheless enter into the realm of private law via the doctrine of horizontal effect. While the full implications of the case cannot be examined in the limited space of this essay, it is nevertheless clear that the HRA does not only shape our rights as individuals against public authorities,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a> but also disputes in private law.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
For a definition of “core” public authorities, see <em>Parochial Church Council of the Parish of Aston Cantlow and Wilcote with Billesley, Warwickshire v Wallbank</em> [2003] UKHL 17.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
The Court’s duty here is stated by s.6(3)(a) HRA 1998, when read in conjunction with s.6(1) HRA 1998.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
[2019] EWHC 246 (Ch).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
The legal issues and principles surrounding s.6(3)(b) is complicated and would not be elaborated in this case note. An overview of the law and recent developments on s.6(3)(b) can be found in A Williams, “Public Authorities and the HRA 1998: Recent Trends” [2017] <em>Judicial Review</em> 247.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
(n 3) [128].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
<em>ibid</em> [123]-[125].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
<em>ibid</em> [169].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
<em>ibid</em> [170].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
(n 8).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
(n 3) [170]-[171].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
Ibid [172].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
This approach is authoritatively stated by Lady Hale in the seminal case of <em>Campbell v Mirror Group Newspapers Ltd</em> [2004] UKHL 22, [132].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
[2008] QB 73, [9].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
<em>Ibid</em> [11]. Being a breach of confidence case, the Convention jurisprudence being taken into account in <em>McKennitt</em> were those arising under Articles 8 and 10 ECHR.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
(n 13) [22].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
A Young, “Mapping Horizontal Effect” in D Hoffmann (ed), <em>The Impact of the Human Rights Act on Private Law</em> (CUP 2011).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
(n 3) [174].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
G Phillipson,”Clarity Postponed: Horizontal Effect After <em>Campbell</em>” in H Fenwick, G Phillipson and R Masterman (eds) <em>Judicial reasoning under the UK Human Rights Act</em> (2007), Chapter 6.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
[2005] EWCA Civ 595.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [47].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
ECtHR 24 June 2004, app. no. 59320/00, [57]-[58].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
As found under s.6(1) of the Act.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Extraditing suspects and safeguarding human rights - a tangled tale</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/06/extraditing-subjects-safeguarding-human-rights/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/06/extraditing-subjects-safeguarding-human-rights/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Commentary on <em>Kyung Yip Kim v Ministry of Justice of New Zealand and another [2019] NZCA 209 </em>and insights on the <em>Fugitive Offenders and Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Legislation (Amendment) Bill 2019</em></strong><a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a></p>

<p>As a special administrative region of the People’s Republic of China (“<strong>PRC</strong>”), the relationship between Hong Kong and the PRC in terms of legal systems can be reflected in the “one-country, two systems” arrangement: the PRC legal system is a civil law system, while the Hong Kong legal system is a common law system. The recent proposal by the Hong Kong Government regarding the Fugitive Offenders and Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Legislation (Amendment) Bill 2019 (“<strong>the Bill</strong>”) has generated extensive controversy over the Bill both in terms of principle and practice.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> The issue of extradition to the PRC for a criminal trial is further elaborated by the recent New Zealand Court of Appeal judgement in Kyung Yip Kim v Ministry of Justice of New Zealand and another [2019]. This case note analyses the New Zealand judgement in light of concerns over extradition to the PRC under the Bill, and argues that there exist legitimate and serious concerns over extradition under the Bill. It will also engage in depth with the observations and recommendations made by the Hong Kong Bar Association (“<strong>HKBA</strong>”) and the Law Society of Hong Kong (“<strong>LSHK</strong>”), and discuss two possible legal solutions to the dilemma underlying and generated by the Bill in its current form. In order to offer a sharp and defined focus on the relevant legal issues and principles, the political issues and controversies surrounding the Bill will not be discussed.</p>

<h5 id="facts-and-appellate-history">Facts and Appellate History</h5>

<p>Mr Kim, a citizen of the Republic of Korea, is a permanent resident of New Zealand. In the present case, Chinese authorities state that in 2009, Mr Kim killed a 20-year-old woman in Shanghai; the police is said to have both forensic and circumstantial evidence linking Mr Kim to the homicide. On 25 May 2011, New Zealand received a request from the PRC seeking the extradition of Mr Kim on one count of intentional homicide; that request included an assurance that if convicted, Mr Kim would not be sentenced to death. In the ensuing years since the initial arrest in 2011, Kim has resisted surrender on, inter alia, the grounds that he will be at significant risk in the PRC for torture, extra-judicial killing or the imposition of the death penalty. He claims to have a defence to the homicide charge, but that he will not receive a fair trial if extradited because of systemic and fundamental flaws in the Chinese criminal justice system. He also argues that if convicted, he will be expected to serve a disproportionately severe sentence.</p>

<p>A judicial review action brought by Mr Kim against the Ministry of Justice’s decision to surrender him to PRC authorities in 2015 (“<strong>the First MoJ Decision</strong>”) was successful before Mallon J,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> and the Minister was redirected to reconsider the extradition request. In particular, it was noted that the fact of Shanghai being the place of the trial should not be given much weight in determining whether to surrender Mr Kim, in light of the limited information upon which that was based.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> Upon reconsidering the case, the Minister decided to agree to the extradition request (“<strong>the Second MoJ Decision</strong>”). Kim brought a judicial review action against the Second Decision but failed before Mallon J (“<strong>the JR Judgement</strong>”).<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a></p>

<p>The present case note concerns the JR Judgement regarding the Second Decision. In particular, it focuses on the third and seventh grounds of appeal, which concern, respectively, the acceptance of assurances in relation to the adequacy of protection for Kim in the PRC and considerations over possible risk of departure from fair trial standards. It is because the two grounds of appeal shed light directly on the issues faced by the Bill in principle and practice. In unpacking judgement, it will also briefly discuss the fourth to sixth grounds of appeal.</p>

<h5 id="the-judgement">The Judgement</h5>

<h6 id="a-summary-on-material-issues-related-to-concerns-over-extradition-to-china-from-the-new-zealand-perspective"><u>A summary on material issues related to concerns over extradition to China from the New Zealand perspective</u></h6>

<p>This section broadly thematises the JR Judgement into two issues: (i) assurance from PRC authorities in relation to torture as adequate to protect Mr Kim on return to the PRC, and (ii) possible risk of departure from fair trial standards justifying refusal of surrender. This allows the case note to shed light directly on the issues and controversies generated by the Bill (to be elaborated in the subsequent sections).</p>

<h6 id="whether-the-minister-erred-in-accepting-assurances-in-relation-to-torture-as-adequate-to-protectmr-kim-on-return-to-the-prc"><u>Whether the Minister erred in accepting assurances in relation to torture as adequate to protect Mr Kim on return to the PRC</u></h6>

<p>This mainly concerns the third ground of appeal. To begin with, the Court noted that the risk of torture is a material consideration in reflecting on the adequacy of diplomatic assurances regarding Kim’s trial in China;<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> the risk of torture is a significant issue, given that “those who torture, do so outside the law…they take steps to ensure that what they do is not recorded or detected.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> The Minister did not receive fresh evidence in the period between the First MoJ Decision and the Second MoJ Decision to provide any firmer foundation for the Minister’s conclusion that the location of the trial reduced the risk of torture.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> The Minister has also failed to address adequately the extent as to which the PRC criminal justice system is reliant upon confession in prosecution and conviction.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a> The fact that confession is made under formal recording and interrogation is not necessarily reliable and/or legitimate as evidence for trial, since it “does not address the risk of torture occurring when the cameras are not turned on…interrogations in the PRC are selectively recorded, and that notwithstanding rules in connection with recording interrogations, torture does take place outside video surveillance.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> The evidence reflects that the rule in the PRC criminal justice system that statements obtained by torture will not be admitted in evidence “is not being consistently or successfully implemented.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a> In concluding that the Minister erred in accepting assurances in relation to torture as adequate to protect Mr Kim on return to PRC, the Court held that the Minister has failed to address adequately how the assurances could protect Mr Kim from torture when: “(a) torture is already against the law, yet persists; (b) the practice of torture in the PRC is concealed and its use can be difficult to detect in particular cases; (c) videotapping of interrogations is selective and torture often occurs outside the recorded session; (d) evidence obtained by torture is regularly admitted in court; and (e) there are substantial disincentives for anyone, especially the detained person, reporting the practice of torture.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a></p>

<p>It should be noted, however, that if practices under the criminal justice system are conducted based on existing legal rules and/or principles, the Minister will be entitled to give them greater weight in determining whether to extradite Mr Kim. Under the fourth ground of appeal, the Court stated that given an imposition of the death penalty will be “monitored through trial and sentence,” the Minister was entitled to take it into account in determining the validity of the assurances offered by PRC authorities.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a> Furthermore, the different types of potential threats Mr Kim alleges himself to face needs to be considered and assessed separately. Death by organ-harvesting, as pleaded by Mr Kim under the fifth ground of appeal, is to be assessed separately from the risk of torture.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a></p>

<h6 id="whether-the-minister-erred-in-considering-that-there-was-no-risk-of-departure-from-fair-trial-standards-justifying-refusal-of-surrender"><u>Whether the Minister erred in considering that there was no risk of departure from fair trial standards justifying refusal of surrender</u></h6>

<p>This mainly concerns the seventh ground of appeal. It would be useful, however, to first note the legal standard adopted by the Court in determining whether Mr Kim’s right to a fair trial would be upheld: “…whether there is a real risk of a departure from the standard such as to deprive the defendant of a key benefit of the right in question.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> “Real risk” refers to a risk that is real and not merely fanciful, so that it may be established by something less than a fifty-one percent probability.</p>

<p>The Court’s consideration over the risk of departure from fair trial standards justifying refusal or surrender is subdivided into four issue: (i) the nature and operation of the PRC criminal justice system, (ii) a right to a hearing before an independent and public tribunal, (iii) a right to legal representation, and (iv) a right not to be compelled to testify or confess guilt. In relation to issue (i), the court noted that the PRC criminal justice system is “essentially inquisitorial but has incorporated an increasing number of adversarial components”;<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a> the Supreme People’s Procuracy<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> (“<strong>SPP</strong>”) is responsible to the National People’s Congress (“<strong>NPC</strong>”) and its Standing Committee (“<strong>NPCSC</strong>”), which is a legislative body. The SPP is “the state organ for legal supervision, charged with investigating crimes committed by state functionaries…, public prosecutions and supervising the application and enforcement of the law by other legal institutions…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> Selection of judges in the PRC criminal justice system is based on both merits and political integrity,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a> and the political influence in the system “prioritises social policy objectives over individual procedural protections. The lack of independence of the judiciary is systemic…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a></p>

<p>As introduced above, the JR Judgement also identified three rights for the purpose of articulating and assessing the risk of departure from fair trial standards. Firstly, in relation to a right to a hearing before an independent and public tribunal, the Court noted that the system operates in a way which “enables a decision to be made by a body other than the body that heard the case. The procedural rights do not alter the fundamental structure of the system…those procedural rights are largely discretionary and…pale in comparison with the objective of maintaining stability through punishing crime.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a>Given the PRC criminal justice system is inherently subject to political control, the assurances provided “cannot reasonably be seen as providing reassurance that Mr Kim’s case will be dealt with in some different way,” and that it was not reasonably open to the Minister to “conclude, on the information before her, that the risk that Mr Kim would not be tried before an independent tribunal was addressed by these assurances.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a> Secondly, in relation to a right to legal representation, after noting that the procedural deficiencies were not adequately addressed in practice,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a> the Court stated that right for the defence to apply for disclosure of evidence held by the prosecution helpful to their case is “difficult to exercise when the defence does not know what evidence the prosecution holds and when the grant of the application for disclosure is discretionary.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a> The position of the PRC defence bar also arguably strengthens the criticism that there is a lack of a right to a fair trial under the PRC criminal justice system, since it is not clear whether the defence bar operates in an environment which can secure defendants with the benefit of legal representation.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline25" href="#25">25</a> It is the norm in the PRC that “witnesses do not appear, and so will not be available for cross-examinations”;<a class="inline-reference" id="inline26" href="#26">26</a> it is crucial to consider “how the procedural right to examine witnesses operates in practice, and whether there is in substance a right for the accused to examine witnesses.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline27" href="#27">27</a> Thirdly, in relation to a right not to be compelled to testify or confess guilt, the Court notes that legal niceties in terms of lack of legal consequences flowing from refusal to answer in interrogation are “very likely to be lost sight of within the human dynamic of an interrogation, especially when they interrogation may extend on and off over a period of months.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline28" href="#28">28</a> In the present case, the Minister should “require an assurance that Mr Kim has the opportunity to have a legal representative during interrogation.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline29" href="#29">29</a></p>

<h5 id="analysis-of-the-judgement-and-a-summary-of-issues-on-the-proposed-bill">Analysis of the judgement and a summary of issues on the proposed Bill</h5>

<p>The JR Judgement reflects a number of important issues to consider in terms of extraditing an individual to another country to face a criminal trial. First and foremost, it is important to ensure that fundamental human rights enjoyed by the extraditees as recognised in international law<a class="inline-reference" id="inline30" href="#30">30</a> would be safeguard once he/she is extradited, or that any legally permissible interference with such rights by the recipient State’s authorities can be justified under the relevant domestic and international legal frameworks. The pertinent issue in the present context, however, is that the PRC has not ratified the ICCPR and implements the provision which it has signed in domestic law. It would therefore be difficult for extraditees in the PRC to claim fundamental human rights protections in relation to rights against, inter alia, torture and extra-legal interrogations under the ICCPR.</p>

<p>The risk of torture in the extradition context is problematic as it implies that once the individual is extradited, the extraditing State would lose all practical means of guaranteeing on its own initiative that the individual would not be subjected to torture of any sorts in the recipient State. The extra-legal practice of using torture to obtain evidence further exacerbates the problem, as it would be very difficult if not virtually impossible for the extraditing State to monitor the treatment of the extraditee in the recipient State. Any distinction between (i) any prohibitions against torture as stated in statutory texts and (ii) the actual practice and extent of use of torture as a means of obtaining evidence generates considerable doubts as to any assurances, regardless of its cogency in terms of use of language. In the PRC context, given that a criminal trial “relies extensively on documents, rendering a trial virtually a trial by affidavits,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline31" href="#31">31</a> the use of torture in obtaining confessions which are subsequently documented and presented in the actual trial poses grave concerns to the integrity of the pre-trial process of obtaining statements from the accused as a whole.</p>

<p>Before moving on to analyse the contents and effects of the Bill in light of the JR Judgement, the nature of denial of justice resulting from improper and human rights-violating procedures should be briefly noted. Under the sixth ground of appeal on the question of the correct legal standard in determining whether Kim’s right to a fair trial will be upheld, the Court stated that the material concept is “flagrant denial of justice” with jurisprudential roots in the European Convention on Human Rights (“<strong>ECHR</strong>”). In Othman v United Kingdom,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline32" href="#32">32</a> the European Court of Human Rights noted that a flagrant denial of justice requires “a breach of the principles of fair trial guaranteed by Article 6 which is so fundamental as to amount to a nullification, or destruction of the very essence, of the right guaranteed by that Article.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline33" href="#33">33</a> While the JR Judgement did not adopt in full the concept as elucidated by the Othman, its suggestion that there needs to be “a real risk of a departure from the standard such as to deprive the defendant of a key benefit of the right in question”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline34" href="#34">34</a> shows that it is crucial to ensure that any relevant right which an accused may enjoy under international law in the extraditing and/or recipient State can be preserved and manifested.</p>

<p>The JR Judgement suggests that in the context of extradition cases, human rights guarantees and actual practices in the recipient State’s criminal justice system are the most important considerations in ensuring the integrity of any extradition regimes. From the perspective and standpoint of the extraditing State, it would thus be crucial any extradition agreements and decisions to, so far is possible, to ensure that the extraditee will be entitled to similar if not the same degrees of human rights and procedural protections as he/she can enjoy in the extraditing State if he/she is to face a criminal trial therein. It is to these twin issues, together with the particular contexts and concerns relevant to extradition to PRC, that this case note now turns to.</p>

<h6 id="the-nature-of-the-agreements-to-be-made-under-the-bill"><u>The nature of the agreements to be made under the Bill</u></h6>

<p>The Fugitive Offenders Ordinance (Cap. 503) (“<strong>FOO</strong>”) currently allows Hong Kong to conclude one-off surrender arrangements for the surrender of fugitive offenders with any place with which it does not already have a reciprocal agreement, to the exclusion of “any other part of the PRC” including Macau, Taiwan, and the Mainland.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline35" href="#35">35</a> The proposed amendment to the FOO would remove these geographical limitations and permit one-off “special surrender arrangements” to be made between Hong Kong and “any other part of the PRC”, the effect of which is that people living in Hong Kong could be removed to stand trial or serve a criminal sentence in Macau, Taiwan, and the Mainland. A further proposed amendment to the Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Ordinance (Cap. 525) would enable Hong Kong authorities to provide assistance in criminal matters to the PRC.</p>

<p>The Hong Kong Government’s justification for the introduction and urgent passing of the Bill was to ensure that Mr Chan Tong-kai, a murder suspect who allegedly killed his pregnant girlfriend Miss Poon Hiu-wing while on holiday in Taiwan in February 2018, could be surrendered to stand trial in Taiwan, despite Hong Kong not having concluded an extradition treaty with Taiwan. The Bill would supposedly plug the “loopholes” in the FOO, with respect to the existing geographical limitations.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline36" href="#36">36</a></p>

<h6 id="the-role-of-the-chief-executive-under-the-bill-and-practical-concerns"><u>The role of the Chief Executive under the Bill and practical concerns</u></h6>

<p>The Chief Executive (“<strong>CE</strong>”) plays a predominant role under the Bill, since (s)he decides whether or not to surrender a fugitive offender at three key junctures of the surrender process. First, upon receiving a request for surrender, the CE may issue an authority to proceed, which permits a magistrate to issue a warrant of arrest and bring the fugitive before the court of committal.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline37" href="#37">37</a> Second, the CE may issue a certificate to initiate a special surrender arrangement.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline38" href="#38">38</a> Then, assuming the fugitive is committed pursuant to an order of committal and is not discharged, the final decision to make an order for surrender lies solely with the CE, subject to the fugitive bringing a judicial review challenge.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline39" href="#39">39</a> The CE may refuse surrender based on the general statutory restrictions on surrender<a class="inline-reference" id="inline40" href="#40">40</a>, for instance where the offence is of a political character, or raise other discretionary grounds that are not included in the FOO, such as the fugitive’s mental or physical health.</p>

<p>The Bill raises immediate practical concerns. It is because unlike the twenty agreements for the reciprocal surrender of fugitives to which the FOO applies which were presumably based on sovereign states negotiating agreements on equal terms, there is an asymmetrical relationship between Hong Kong and the PRC. Under the Hong Kong Basic Law, the CE is politically appointed by the Central People’s Government<a class="inline-reference" id="inline41" href="#41">41</a> and is dually accountable to it and Hong Kong.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline42" href="#42">42</a> In concluding the proposed one-off agreements with the PRC, it is likely that the CE will not refuse a request for surrender from the Mainland requesting authority, that is the Supreme People’s Procuratorate. This means that the CE is unlikely to exercise his/her discretion in the surrender process, and thus, requiring the CE to issue a certificate is not an adequate safeguard against surrender to the Mainland. If the proposed one-off agreement creates a conflicting interest between the mainland and Hong Kong, it would be up to the CE’s discretion to determine which jurisdiction’s interest(s) should prevail.</p>

<h6 id="the-role-of-courts-under-the-bill"><u>The role of courts under the Bill</u></h6>

<p>Conversely, Hong Kong courts play a fairly limited role in reviewing and rejecting a request for surrender: it must only consider whether the evidence produced before it would prima facie constitute a scheduled offence under the FOO, and must not examine the substantive law of the requesting jurisdiction.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline43" href="#43">43</a> In the proceedings for committal,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline44" href="#44">44</a> the magistrate cannot inquire into whether the fugitive is in fact guilty of the offence. Rather, the magistrate must issue an order of committal, subject to the fugitive’s right of appeal by way of writ of habeas corpus,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline45" href="#45">45</a> as long as all due formalities are observed by the requesting jurisdiction and the aforementioned general statutory restrictions on surrender do not apply. Pursuant to the non-inquiry principle, the magistrate also cannot consider the quality of justice that the fugitive may face in the requesting jurisdiction and whether the fugitive’s surrender would be compatible with the Hong Kong Bill of Rights Ordinance (“<strong>HKBORO</strong>”).</p>

<h5 id="flags-to-highlight">Flags to highlight</h5>

<p>The Bill raises several red flags, regarding (i) the lack of justification for its necessity, (ii) the problematic nature of the proposed one-off special surrender agreements and (iii) the ensuing human rights concerns particularly in the context of surrender to the PRC in light of Kim v Ministry of Justice.</p>

<p>First, the need for the Bill has not been satisfactorily addressed by the Hong Kong Government. The rationale underlying the Bill is unclear, since Hong Kong has not faced any major problems with the surrender of fugitives in the last twenty years, despite not having any such arrangements with Macau, Taiwan, and the Mainland. The Hong Kong Government’s reliance on the Taiwan murder case is not at all persuasive, given that not only has Taiwan since indicated that they would not extradite Mr Chan under the one-off arrangements in the proposed Bill, but Taiwan’s Presidential Office subsequently released a statement that “[t]he Hong Kong Government’s use of a [criminal] case involving Taiwan as a pretext to legislate a bill that may violate human rights is irresponsible and lacks a sense of morality”.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline46" href="#46">46</a> Furthermore, as the HKBA argued in its rebuttal against the Government’s claim of the need to close the “loophole” generated by the lack of extradition agreement between Hong Kong and China, the lack of such arrangement was deliberate. The Government could not put forward any satisfactory change of circumstances in the PRC to explain the necessity of the Bill in the present moment. In light of these developments, even assuming that there is a need for the Bill, there is no convincing reason why the amendment has to be urgent and cannot instead be part of a proper consultation process. There are other alternatives that could effectively remedy the “loophole” problem presented by the Hong Kong Government regarding the Taiwan murder case: for example, s 153P of the Crimes Ordinance (Cap. 200) could be amended to include murder and manslaughter, so that Hong Kong could have extra-territorial jurisdiction over these crimes.</p>

<p>Second, the nature of one-off special surrender arrangements raises issues which the Hong Kong Government may need to examine more closely. Countries usually prefer to conclude a formal reciprocal agreement which secures their interests on a long-term and predictable basis, rather than an ad-hoc one-off arrangement. This is because a one-off arrangement tends to arise with little or no notice, targets only one or a few persons, and lacks the protections of a reciprocal agreement. One-off arrangements are therefore the exception to the rule, and so are only made where there are legitimate reasons why a reciprocal agreement is not in place. Moreover, as evidenced in the analysis of the JR Judgment above, international extradition principles prohibit surrender if an individual will not be accorded with minimum standards of treatment in the requesting jurisdiction. This is important because once a fugitive is surrendered, it is difficult if not impossible to have redress if (s)he is treated in an unacceptable way, especially if (s)he is threatened by the irreversible harm of torture or death in the PRC, as in the case of Mr. Kim. As such, countries will not enter into reciprocal agreements with another if this could result in a breach of human rights, including the right to a fair trial and humane, decent conditions of detention in prison and the protection against torture.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline47" href="#47">47</a></p>

<p>Last but not least, considering these extradition principles regarding one-off arrangements alongside the JR Judgment above, it is at best doubtful whether people living in Hong Kong surrendered under the proposed one-off arrangements would be guaranteed a minimum standard of treatment where the PRC is the requesting jurisdiction. From the third and seventh grounds of appeal in the JR Judgment, the Court notably acknowledged that human rights abuses and torture are rampant in the PRC, and the PRC criminal justice system is both politically-motivated and compromised and lacks procedural guarantees, and so cannot guarantee the fugitive’s access to justice and a fair trial. This is especially worrying in the present climate, seeing that the Hong Kong public have repeatedly voiced their concerns on the potential for the proposed Bill to be turned into an entrenched mechanism for political persecution and to suppress freedom of speech, in light of the aforementioned fact that the PRC has signed but not ratified the ICCPR, as well as the distinction between the supposed human rights guarantees in the Constitution of the People’s Republic of China<a class="inline-reference" id="inline48" href="#48">48</a> and procedural protections in the Criminal Procedure Law of the People’s Republic of China 2012, and the actual practices of the PRC as described in the JR Judgment.</p>

<h5 id="necessary-but-not-necessarily-adequate-legal-solutions">Necessary but not necessarily adequate legal solutions</h5>

<p>Before delving into the proposed grounds of amendments and review, it should be highlighted that a full adoption of the proposals do not necessarily address the key issue (as identified in the JR Judgement under the third and seventh grounds of appeal) of discrepancy between statutory provisions guaranteeing rights related to a fair trial and the actual practice of neglecting and/or abusing the provisions to the detriment of the accused. That being said, instead of merely insisting on withdrawing the Bill, it would be useful and indeed necessary to consider possible amendments to the Bill should the Government decide to continue pushing the Bill through the Legislative Council.</p>

<h6 id="law-society-of-hong-kongs-proposed-reviews49"><u>Law Society of Hong Kong's proposed reviews</u><a class="inline-reference" id="inline49" href="#49">49</a></h6>

<p>Although a comprehensive review of Hong Kong’s extradition laws might be required which will undoubtedly take time and require extensive consultation with various stakeholders and the wider community, the LSHK recommends that additional safeguards be added to the proposed one-off special surrender arrangements, if necessary to address urgent requests to surrender fugitives.</p>

<p>With regards to the court’s role, the LSHK submits that Hong Kong courts should have more power to oversee extradition requests. The FOO s 23 currently states that any document in support of extradition can be admitted without further proof,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline50" href="#50">50</a> and prevents evidence which contradicts the allegations raised by the requesting jurisdiction from being adduced<a class="inline-reference" id="inline51" href="#51">51</a> except to identify the person being brought before the court.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline52" href="#52">52</a> The LSHK recommends that the FOO s 23 should be amended to be in line with Part III of the Magistrates Ordinance (Cap. 227), so that the defence can adduce evidence which tests the credibility of prosecution evidence. Not only would this assist the magistrate in deciding whether a prima facie case has been made out for the scheduled offence, but this would also, more importantly, ensure that the defence has the full right to be heard.</p>

<p>Certain rights must be guaranteed to surrendered fugitives, so as to ensure the minimum standard of treatment is safeguarded. The LSHK proposes that the accused Hong Kong person should have the right to dispute and resist the extradition request. In addition, the requesting state should give an undertaking that, if the fugitive is surrendered, (s)he should have rights to proper legal representation and visitation. It should also be made clear that, in the case of the PRC, requests for surrender should not be made on spurious grounds, and certificates issued by the CE to initiate a special surrender arrangement can only be issued pursuant to a formal request made by the Supreme People’s Procuratorate.</p>

<p>Finally, the LSHK submits that the Hong Kong Government should make extradition agreements under the Bill more transparent to the general public. One method to increase transparency would be to require the CE to clearly list out the criteria (s)he has considered in issuing the certificate, including but not limited to the offence not being of a political nature or being a civil dispute. The Hong Kong Government must also increase its efforts to enter into formal reciprocal agreements with jurisdictions presently without such agreements.</p>

<h6 id="an-argument-from-the-uk-human-rights-act-1998"><u>An argument from the UK Human Rights Act 1998</u></h6>

<p>In order to ensure that a decision to extradite an individual and the decision’s execution would not be prejudicial against the rights to fair trial and against torture under the ICCPR, it is submitted that insights can be drawn from the Human Rights Act 1998 (“<strong>HRA 1998</strong>”). Under section 6(1) HRA 1998, it would be unlawful for a public authority to “act in a way which is incompatible with a Convention right”; courts are also categorised as “public authorities” under the HRA.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline53" href="#53">53</a> By requiring a public authority to act compatibly with an individual’s ECHR right, the Act aims to reduce instances of questionable executive and judicial behaviour.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline54" href="#54">54</a> It also opens another avenue for appellate courts to review a court’s first-instance decision, by considering whether the court’s decision is compatible with its duty to act compatibly with a Convention right. In terms of the Bill’s context, it is submitted that an amendment to the Bill can consider requiring courts to act compatibly with the rights that individuals are entitled to in the extradition context under the HKBORO.</p>

<p>Having proposed the possibility of drawing insights from the HRA section 6 context, the approach of appellate courts to reviewing first-instance decisions under the HRA should also be briefly discussed.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline55" href="#55">55</a> Two UK Supreme Court cases are of particular significance here. Firstly, in In re B (A Child), Lord Clarke noted that in the context of a care order under the Children Act 1989, the correct approach is to “treat the exercise as an appellate exercise and not as a fresh determination of necessity or proportionality,” and that an appellate court should not intervene “absent an error of principle.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline56" href="#56">56</a> In the Bill’s context, this means that while the magistrate’s decision and judgement to extradite the suspect can be challenged on grounds of alleged incompatibility with the ICCPR, it will enjoy presumptive validity and an error of principle is necessary in order to rebut such presumption. In contrast, Lady Hale’s dissenting judgement requiring the appellate court to conduct a proportionality analysis of the first-instance judgement afresh<a class="inline-reference" id="inline57" href="#57">57</a> is based on an appellate court’s inherent duty to act compatibly with the ECHR as a public authority under s.6(1) HRA 1998.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline58" href="#58">58</a> Secondly, in R (on the application of AR) v CC of Greater Manchester Police and another, Lord Carnwath noted that the rejection of the minority view in In re B (A Child) “reflected the general policy consideration that the purpose of the appeal is to enable the reasoning of the lower court to be reviewed and errors corrected, not to provide an opportunity for the parties to reargue the same case.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline59" href="#59">59</a> It is necessary for the first-instance decision to be wrong “because of an identifiable flaw in the judge’s reasoning, such as a gap in logic, a lack of consistency, or a failure to take account of some material factor, which undermines the cogency of the conclusion.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline60" href="#60">60</a> The UK approach to reviewing lower courts’ first-instance decisions, considering it in the context of the Bill, would suggest that while the magistrate’s decision to extradite would enjoy presumptive validity upon appeal, an identifiable flaw in terms of legal reasoning, consideration of relevant factors and application of legal principles and facts may nevertheless give rise to a successful appeal.</p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p>Extradition laws and regimes require not only prudent consideration of the applicable and supporting legal principles underpinning the system, but also giving considerable weight to the actual practices of the recipient State. Kim v Ministry of Justice is a compelling illustration as to the necessity of guaranteeing comprehensive protection of fundamental human rights inherently enjoyed by a suspect in a criminal case. It has also shed light on the controversies over the Bill proposed by the Hong Kong Government, showing that there exists a significant number of legal and practical loopholes in terms of guaranteeing adequate human rights protection and ensuring that actual practices within the PRC criminal justice system are in conformity with the statutory prohibitions against torture. It has also summarised and analysed the observations made by the HKBA and LSHK, and highlighted two principal and pertinent grounds of amendment should the Bill be proposed again in the future.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline61" href="#61">61</a> While a comprehensive analysis of the JR Judgement and the issues underpinning and generated by the Bill cannot be examined in the limited space of this article, it is clear that any amendments to the Bill must not only seek to limit its applicability, but tackle more fundamental issues over human rights guarantees both in principle and practice.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline1" id="1">[1]</a>
Many thanks to the anonymous reviewers for their comments and insights, all errors remain on our own. On top of the usual disclaimer, the authors would also like to emphasise that the observations and propositions in this piece should not be construed as reflecting their stances on the necessity, validity and practicality of the Bill.</p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline2" id="2">[2]</a>
As of 16 June 2019, the Government has decided to suspend the second reading of the Bill with no timetable for restarting the process: <a href="https://www.info.gov.hk/gia/general/201906/16/P2019061600803.htm">https://www.info.gov.hk/gia/general/201906/16/P2019061600803.htm</a> accessed on 16 June 2019. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline3" id="3">[3]</a>
[2016] NZHC 1490. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline4" id="4">[4]</a>
ibid, [84]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline5" id="5">[5]</a>
[2017] NZHC 2109. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline6" id="6">[6]</a>
[2019] NZCA 209, [126]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline7" id="7">[7]</a>
ibid, [132]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline8" id="8">[8]</a>
ibid, [124]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline9" id="9">[9]</a>
ibid, [123]. This is an issue rendered further problematic in light of the court’s analysis of rights to a fair trial and legal representation in PRC under the seventh ground of appeal. This is different from another method of assessment common in judicial review cases, known as “proportionality.” The issue of proportionality review is further elaborated in “An argument from UK Human Rights Act 1998” below. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline10" id="10">[10]</a>
ibid, [134].</p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline11" id="11">[11]</a>
ibid, [137]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline12" id="12">[12]</a>
ibid, [138]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline13" id="13">[13]</a>
ibid, [154]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline14" id="14">[14]</a>
ibid, [164]-[165]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline15" id="15">[15]</a>
ibid, [179]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline16" id="16">[16]</a>
ibid, [188]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline17" id="17">[17]</a>
Or “procuratorate,” both meaning the office of a procurator or prosecutor. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline18" id="18">[18]</a>
(n 6), [190]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline19" id="19">[19]</a>
ibid, [191]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline20" id="20">[20]</a>
ibid, [217]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline21" id="21">[21]</a>
ibid, [219]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline22" id="22">[22]</a>
ibid, [221]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline23" id="23">[23]</a>
ibid, [237]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline24" id="24">[24]</a>
ibid, [238]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline25" id="25">[25]</a>
ibid, [239]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline26" id="26">[26]</a>
ibid, [241]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline27" id="27">[27]</a>
ibid, [242]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline28" id="28">[28]</a>
ibid, [255]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline29" id="29">[29]</a>
ibid. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline30" id="30">[30]</a>
In the present case, this concerns the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (“ICCPR”).</p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline31" id="31">[31]</a>
(n 6) [241], quoting from Professor Fu Hualing (University of Hong Kong)’s expert opinion. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline32" id="32">[32]</a>
ECtHR 17 January 2012, app. no. 8139/09. Endorsed by Harkins v United Kingdom ECtHR (GC) 11 January 2017, app. no. 71537/14. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline33" id="33">[33]</a>
ibid, [260]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline34" id="34">[34]</a>
(n 15). </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline35" id="35">[35]</a>
Fugitive Offenders Ordinance (Cap. 503), s 2. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline36" id="36">[36]</a>
Former British Foreign Secretary, Sir Malcom Rifkind stated that the geographical limitation was a deliberate choice to “[erect] a necessary firewall to ensure that Hong Kong’s judicial independence remains intact”: <a href="https://www.scmp.com/comment/opinion/article/3012853/there-no-loophole-hong-kongs-current-extradition-law-rather-it">https://www.scmp.com/comment/opinion/article/3012853/there-no-loophole-hong-kongs-current-extradition-law-rather-it</a> accessed on 17 June 2019. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline37" id="37">[37]</a>
(n 35), s 6(2). </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline38" id="38">[38]</a>
The Bill, s 3A. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline39" id="39">[39]</a>
(n 35), s 13. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline40" id="40">[40]</a>
ibid, s 5. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline41" id="41">[41]</a>
Article 45, Hong Kong Basic Law. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline42" id="42">[42]</a>
ibid, Article 43. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline43" id="43">[43]</a>
Robert Henry Cosby v Chief Executive of the HKSAR HCAL 118/1999, [25]. The standard of review is Wednesbury unreasonableness (at [16]). </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline44" id="44">[44]</a>
(n 35), s 10. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline45" id="45">[45]</a>
ibid, s 12. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline46" id="46">[46]</a>
<a href="http://focustaiwan.tw/news/acs/201906150015.aspx">http://focustaiwan.tw/news/acs/201906150015.aspx</a> accessed on 17 June 2019. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline47" id="47">[47]</a>
For example, Australia refused to ratify an extradition treaty with the PRC due to human rights concerns: <a href="https://www.scmp.com/news/asia/australasia/article/2082674/australia-shelves-china-extradition-treaty-after-opponents">https://www.scmp.com/news/asia/australasia/article/2082674/australia-shelves-china-extradition-treaty-after-opponents</a> accessed on 17 June 2019. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline48" id="48">[48]</a>
Constitution of the People’s Republic of China, Chapter II The Fundamental Rights and Duties of Citizens: <a href="http://www.npc.gov.cn/englishnpc/Constitution/2007-11/15/content_1372964.htm">http://www.npc.gov.cn/englishnpc/Constitution/2007-11/15/content_1372964.htm</a> accessed on 18 June 2019. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline49" id="49">[49]</a>
<a href="https://fr.scribd.com/document/412450921/Law-Society-of-Hong-Kong-submission-over-extradition-bill#download&amp;from_embed">https://fr.scribd.com/document/412450921/Law-Society-of-Hong-Kong-submission-over-extradition-bill#download&amp;from_embed</a> accessed on 17 June 2019. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline50" id="50">[50]</a>
(n 35), s 23(1). </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline51" id="51">[51]</a>
ibid, s 23(4). </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline52" id="52">[52]</a>
ibid, s 23(5). </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline53" id="53">[53]</a>
Respectively, section 6(1) and 6(3)(a) HRA 1998. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline54" id="54">[54]</a>
Legislative behaviour is not included as “public authority…does not include either House of Parliament or a person exercising functions in connection with proceedings in Parliament” (section 6(3) HRA 1998). </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline55" id="55">[55]</a>
The issue of proportionality assessments at appellate courts gives rise to complex legal issues which cannot be realistically and practically dealt with in the present case note. Interested readers may consider consulting the following academic materials: J Rivers, “The Presumption of Proportionality” (2014) 77 (3) Modern Law Review 409-433; C Chan, “Proportionality and Invariable Baseline Intensity of Review” (2013) 33(1) Legal Studies 1-21; C Chan, “Deference, Expertise and Information: Gathering Powers” (2013) 33(4) Legal Studies 598-620. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline56" id="56">[56]</a>
[2013] UKSC 33, [136]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline57" id="57">[57]</a>
ibid, [204]-[205]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline58" id="58">[58]</a>
Whether the majority or minority approach in In re B (A Child) should be the preferable approach under the amended Bill is a question beyond the scope of the present case note. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline59" id="59">[59]</a>
[2018] UKSC 47, [57]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline60" id="60">[60]</a>
ibid, [64]. </p>

<p><a class="reference" href="#inline61" id="61">[61]</a>
On the HKSAR Government’s decision to suspend the second reading of the Bill, see (n 2) above.
<br /></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Coherence and consistency: the need to avoid judicial confusion and its consequences under the Human Rights Act 1998</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/03/coherence-consistency-need-avoid-judicial-confusion/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/03/coherence-consistency-need-avoid-judicial-confusion/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Case Note: <em>In re Siobhan McLaughlin </em>[2018] UKSC 48<a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a></strong></p>

<p>The thorny nature of a declaration of incompatibility (“<strong>DoI</strong>”) under section 4 Human Rights Act 1998 (“<strong>HRA</strong>”), and its role vis-a-vis the Parliament in alerting the latter to Convention-incompatible legislations, has been of topical interest for understanding the role of the courts in the context of protection of human rights in the UK, and its role vis-a-vis Parliament in alerting the latter to Convention-incompatible legislation. It is therefore pertinent that courts adopt a principled and accessible approach in determining whether a DoI should be granted. Following that, as the courts are expected to assess the Convention compatibility of the piece(s) of legislation before them alleged to be incompatible with the Convention, it is also important that the courts adopt a consistent and principled approach under s.2 HRA 1998. This case note analyses the Supreme Court’s decision in <em>In re Siobhan McLaughlin</em>,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> which sheds light on the two aforementioned sections.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> Two arguments will be made. Firstly, examining Lady Hale’s approach to and the threshold for granting a DoI, it argues that the s.4 approach proposed is unsatisfactory and fails to clarify the confusion generated by earlier Supreme Court cases. Secondly, analysing the different judges’ approaches to consideration of Strasbourg jurisprudence under s.2 and their impacts on their respective decisions, the case note observes that a principled approach would be beneficial to the court’s assessment of Strasbourg jurisprudence under s.2, which would impact on the court’s conclusion on an application for a DoI.</p>

<h5 id="facts-and-appellate-history">Facts and appellate history</h5>

<p>Ms McLaughlin is a widow with four children. She was not married to her (now deceased) partner, Mr Adams, because of his personal preferences. Mr Adams had made sufficient national insurance contributions for Ms McLaughlin to be able to claim a bereavement payment and widowed parent’s allowance (“<strong>WPA</strong>”); she would be entitled to them under s.39A of the Social Security Contributions and Benefits (Northern Ireland) Act 1992 (“<strong>the 1992 Act</strong>”), had they been married. Section 39A provides that the section applies where (a) “a person whose spouse or civil partner dies on or after the appointed day is under pensionable age at the time of the spouse’s or civil partner’s death, or…(provision about a man whose wife died).”</p>

<p>Having her claims for bereavement payment and WPA rejected by the Northern Ireland Department for Communities, Ms McLaughlin applied for judicial review of that decision on the ground that s.39A was incompatible with Article 14 of the European Convention on Human Rights (“<strong>ECHR</strong>”), read in conjunction with either Article 8 or Article 1 of the First Protocol (“<strong>A1P1</strong>”). The claim succeeded in part before Treacy J in the High Court. The Court of Appeal held unanimously that s.39A of the 1992 Act was compatible with the Convention. Ms McLaughlin appealed.</p>

<p>Before the Supreme Court, the Appellant argued that the difference in treatment is largely based on the birth status of the children, which is a “suspect ground,” requiring particularly careful scrutiny. The marriage condition has the effect that (almost) all the children adversely affected are “illegitimate,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> and all, or almost all, the children positively affected will be “legitimate.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a> On the other hand, the Respondent submitted that the legitimate aim of the 1992 Act (including s.39A) was to promote the institutions of marriage and civil partnership by conferring eligibility to claim only on the spouse or civil partner of the person who made the contributions.</p>

<h6 id="relevant-strasbourg-jurisprudence"><u>Relevant Strasbourg jurisprudence</u></h6>

<p>In <em>Shackell v United Kingdom</em>,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> the European Court of Human Rights (“<strong>ECtHR</strong>”) declared inadmissible a complaint that denying widow’s benefits to unmarried surviving partners discriminated against the survivor and her children on the ground of her unmarried status and the children’s “illegitimacy.” Relying on the Commission’s view in <em>Lindsay v United Kingdom</em>,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> which held that marriage is different from cohabitation, the ECtHR held that the applicant’s situation was not comparable to that of a widow, although it also went on to hold that in any event the difference in treatment was justified, and hence application inadmissible.</p>

<h5 id="judgement-and-the-courts-observations-on-i-the-consideration-of-strasbourg-jurisprudence-and-ii-the-approach-on-making-a-declaration-of-incompatibility">Judgement and the court’s observations on (i) the consideration of Strasbourg jurisprudence and (ii) the approach on making a declaration of incompatibility</h5>

<h6 id="lady-hales-approach-to-sections-2-and-4-human-rights-act-1998"><u>Lady Hale's approach to sections 2 and 4 Human Rights Act 1998</u></h6>

<p>Distinguishing <em>Shackell </em>from the present case, Lady Hale noted that it cannot be regarded as “conclusively against the conclusion that for this purpose the situations are analogous.” The court in <em>Shackell</em>, unlike Treacy J at first instance in the present case, did not examine the purpose of each benefit separately and ask whether they should be distinguished when it came to the justification of unmarried parents and their children.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> Moving on to the substance and purpose of the 1992 Act, Lady Hale held that it is not a proportionate means of achieving the legitimate aim of privileging marriage to deny the Appellant and her children the benefit of Adams’ contributions on the basis of them not being married to one another.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a> The allowance under the 1992 Act existed “because of the responsibilities of the deceased and survivor towards their children,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> this view being “reinforced by international obligations” the United Kingdom is under.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a></p>

<p>Concluding that s.39A of the 1992 Act is incompatible with Article 14 ECHR when read in conjunction with Article 8, Lady Hale noted, in an ambiguous manner and apparently leading to no obvious conclusions, that the “operation of exclusion of all unmarried couples is not necessarily incompatible.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a> The test for incompatibility under s.4 “is not that the legislation must operate incompatibly in all or even nearly all cases. It is enough that it will inevitably operate incompatibly in a legally significant number of cases.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a></p>

<h6 id="lord-mances-concurrence-on-strasbourg-jurisprudence"><u>Lord Mance's concurrence on Strasbourg jurisprudence</u></h6>

<p>Agreeing with Lady Hale’s judgement, Lord Mance also made some brief observations on Strasbourg jurisprudence in the present case. Noting that the existence of marriage was a condition of eligibility for widowed mother’s allowance in <em>Shackell</em>, he then proceeded to note that the reasoning in <em>Shackell</em> ”fails to address the clear purpose of this allowance, namely to continue to cater, however broadly, for the interest of any relevant children.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a> This is a very clear instance of a purposive approach to the interpretation of s.39A, and also looking into the broader objectives of the 1992 Act as a whole.</p>

<p>Observing on the nature of the 1992 Act, Lord Mance noted that the refusal in question to partners who are neither married nor civil partners “cannot simply be regarded as a detriment to the survivor of the couple.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> The refusal would inevitably operate in a significant number of cases. As a preliminary observation, however, it should be noted that <em>Shackell</em> cannot be said to reach a contrary or totally different conclusions. The main issue, as the majority appears to strongly have in mind, is that the considerations in <em>Shackell</em> did not include the child. The considerations in <em>Shackell</em>, however, clearly included the surviving spouse - the allowance for which is also a central issue in the present case. The well-being and interest of the surviving spouse in the present case, therefore, cannot be said to exclude from the range of purpose(s) the Act may be considered to have.</p>

<h6 id="lord-hodges-dissent-on-the-applicability-of-strasbourg-jurisprudence-and-his-minority-conclusion"><u>Lord Hodge's dissent on the applicability of Strasbourg jurisprudence (and his minority conclusion)</u></h6>

<p>The main thrust of Lord Hodge’s dissent focuses on the applicability of <em>Shackell </em>to the present case, of which it led him to the conclusion that the 1992 Act is not incompatible with the ECHR. Firstly, Lord Hodge noted that <em>Shackell</em> and its line of authority provide “a clear answer to a complaint based on Article 14 taken with A1P1.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a> The ECtHR’s treatment of marriage and civil partnership as conferring a status which distinguishes them from cohabitation, while not binding on the Supreme Court,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> is a “very important component of any analysis of challenge under Article 14 taken together with Article 8…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a></p>

<p>Moving on to observe the characteristics of the WPA, Lord Hodge held that the reasoning of <em>Shackell</em>, which recognises the importance of the status of the surviving spouse, is “directly relevant and strongly supports the conclusion that the co-habiting survivor is not analogous to the Survivor who was married to or in a civil partnership with the Deceased.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a> Although the WPA is payable only if the survivor is responsible for the care of the children who were at the date of death the responsibility of one or both spouses, “it does not follow, as the majority asserts, that the purpose of the WPA is to benefit the children.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> WPA replaces the lost income of the deceased and gives the survivor the opportunity not to work or work less while he/she is responsible for the children.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> If the WPA was characterised as a benefit for the bereaved children, it might be difficult to defend the rationality of the rules stating when the WPA ceases to be payable, e.g. reaching retirement age, the surviving spouse remarrying or entering into a civil partnership with another etc.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a></p>

<h5 id="the-courts-approach-on-the-operation-of-a-declaration-of-incompatibility">The Court’s approach on the operation of a declaration of incompatibility</h5>

<p>Two elements appear to underpin the threshold for making a DoI: (i) “inevitably” breached; (ii) inevitable breaches in a “legally significant number” of cases. While (i) is indisputably correct, the basis for the formulation of (ii) is questionable. Firstly, given the assessment of a DoI is a matter of substance - as to whether the legislation itself as applied, is incompatible with a substantive right (or more) of the ECHR, it is unclear why it would be necessary to resort to a quantitative assessment before confirming that a requested DoI should be granted. It is difficult to read in a balance between individual human rights and utilitarian concerns (if any) in granting a DoI. The requirement of satisfying a vague quantitative threshold is inconsistent with the nature of assessment under s.4, which is clearly a question of principle. The formulation of “legally significant number” is also questionable in terms of its consistency with the nature and purpose of the HRA itself, as it appears to suggest a tension and/or potential conflict between utilitarianism and individual human rights: as long as the incompatibility in question would not be found in a legally significant number of cases, it would not be necessary to grant a DoI.</p>

<p>Moreover, the paragraph in <em>Christian Institute</em> cited by Lady Hale does not support an assessment on quantitative grounds: it only stated that a piece of legislation would not be declared incompatible with Convention rights if it is able to “capable of being operated in a way which is compatible with Convention rights.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a> While an evaluation of the formulation of the assessment for granting a DoI as elucidated in <em>Christian Institute</em> is beyond the scope of this case note, it is unclear how the formulation in the case supports the quantitative approach adopted by Lady Hale. Given the HRA is conceived to “bring rights home”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a> and makes Convention rights more accessible domestically, it is unclear why it would be necessary to balance the incompatibility in an individual case with other similar cases in which incompatibility may not be found.</p>

<p>More problematically, the DoI test formulation in the present case finds no support from recent Supreme Court approaches to determining whether a DoI should be granted. Firstly, in <em>R (T) v Secretary of State for the Home Department</em>, Lord Wilson noted that a DoI is a declaration “only that it is capable of operating incompatibly and, almost always, that it has operated incompatibly in the case before the court.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline25" href="#25">25</a> Moreover, given a DoI “does not affect the validity, continuing operation or enforcement of [the impugned legislation],”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline26" href="#26">26</a> it is unclear why it would be necessary to impose the additional hurdle of “legally significant’ as a matter of judicial restraint in making a DoI. Secondly, Lady Hale’s formulation also does not clarify the confusion generated by Lord Kerr’s observation in <em>Nicklinson v Ministry of Justice</em>, who noted that courts have a “constitutional authority” to make a DoI.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline27" href="#27">27</a> From <em>Nicklinson</em>, it was not clear what is the threshold for triggering the court’s ability to issue a DoI as a matter pursuant to its constitutional authority. This obfuscates the principles on which the court is authorised to make a DoI. Furthermore, it is unclear whether the authority to issue a DoI can be coined as “constitutional” in nature. This uncertainty is based on two reasons: (i) the status of the HRA as a “constitution” is disputable, given it was passed as a piece of ordinary legislation and is possible to be subject to implied repeal;<a class="inline-reference" id="inline28" href="#28">28</a> (ii) it is unclear how the nature of a DoI being of “constitutional” authority in nature would imply the need for a quantitative assessment of any sort, as Lady Hale believes to be necessary. This suggests a degree of inconsistency in how courts approach the requirement of and assessment on the need to make a DoI. If the statute is so important that it ought to be branded of being of “constitutional importance,” bearing in mind that it is intended to improve the accessibility of rights for every individual as rights holders,</p>

<h5 id="the-courts-approach-under-section-2">The court’s approach under section 2</h5>

<p>While not an explicit issue in the case, the difference between the majority and Lord Hodge in approaching <em>Shackell</em> merits attention, as it determined the judges’ respective views on the compatibility of the 1992 Act with the ECHR.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline29" href="#29">29</a> It is submitted that Lord Hodge’s approach should be preferred. Firstly, Lord Hodge’s observation of the similar aims of the legislation in question in <em>Shackell </em>and the 1992 Act reflects that both legislations share the similar purpose of providing allowances to widowed spouses. Given the strong parallel drawn in purposes, it would be confusing if the court then decides to disregard the role of Strasbourg jurisprudence in the present case. Even if <em>Shackell </em>and the present case may not share identical purposes, it would be too hasty for the majority to not consider the purposes in detail (and the overlap between them, if any) before deciding not to follow it.</p>

<p>Secondly, the majority’s analysis, most clearly reflected in Lord Mance’s consideration that the 1992 Act “cannot simply be regarded as a detriment to the survivor of the couple,” fails to articulate clearly the fundamental differences between the legislation in the present case and the <em>Shackell </em>line of authority. Instead of noting the weight that may be given to the objective of providing allowances to widowed spouses, the majority moved on quickly to consider the impact(s) of the 1992 Act on children, whom they appeared to consider to be the more important beneficiary of the impugned legislation. This appears inconsistent with the Supreme Court’s previous approach under s.2, which is most clearly articulated by Lord Neuberger in <em>Manchester City Council v Pinnock</em> - that domestic courts should follow Strasbourg jurisprudence where there is “a clear and constant line of decisions whose decisions are not inconsistent with some fundamental substantive or procedural aspect of English law, and whose reasoning does not appear to overlook or misunderstand some argument or point of principle…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline30" href="#30">30</a> While it is not denied that the 1992 Act may pursue more purposes than the legislation under question in <em>Shackell</em>, the lack of any fundamental differences between the two suggest that <em>Shackell </em>should have been followed.</p>

<h6 id="tangential-remarks-the-relationship-between-sections-2-and-4-human-rights-act-1998"><u>Tangential remarks: the relationship between sections 2 and 4 Human Rights Act 1998</u></h6>

<p>Last but not least, it is submitted that the case also sheds some light on the relationship between sections 2 and 4 HRA 1998. The difference between the majority and minority’s approach to <em>Shackell</em>, and subsequently their different conclusions on s.4, boil down to a matter of characterising the impugned legislation in question. The majority, instead of considering any significant parallels between the pieces of legislation under comparison, focused heavily on the bereavement of children in the present case; the fact that they are more concerned at the domestic statute itself risks not giving appropriate and sufficient scrutiny to the weight and/or applicability of Strasbourg jurisprudence under s.2 HRA 1998. In contrast, Lord Hodge’s more incremental approach, as analysed above, is more favourable.</p>

<p>The case also, interestingly, suggests that there is no necessary correlation between following Strasbourg jurisprudence and making a DoI. The majority, after deciding not to apply <em>Shackell</em> to the present case, found an incompatibility under s.4. In contrast, after finding <em>Shackell </em>to be directly applicable to the present case, Lord Hodge found no incompatibility under s.4. There is no necessary connection between complying with Convention standards and finding an incompatibility of the impugned domestic statute.</p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p><em>In re Siobhan McLaughlin</em> reveals that domestic courts are not necessarily certain of their approaches to sections 2 and 4 HRA 1998. The lack of a principled guidance, however, may lead to legal uncertainty in terms of the applicable tests under the respective section. This not only leads to potentially detrimental effects of “bringing rights home” as a principal task of the HRA, but also obfuscating the principles underlying the consideration of Strasbourg jurisprudence and assessments in deciding whether to grant a DoI. The lack of coherent and consistent principles show that it is necessary for courts to reconsider the principles and factors influencing the assessment under sections 2 and 4 HRA 1998 respectively, in order to ensure that litigants can be certain of the courts’ approaches in determining a Convention rights claim.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
Many thanks to Professor Conor Gearty and Nick Kilford for their comments on an earlier draft. All errors remain on my own.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
[2018] UKSC 48.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
The court did not explicitly stated an engagement of section 2 HRA 1998, but its approach to consideration of Strasbourg jurisprudence is a prime example of a court’s considerations under section 2.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
i.e. born to parents who are not married to each other</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
i.e. born to parents who are married to one another.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
ECtHR 27 April 2000, app. no. 45851/99. The ruling was confirmed in <em>Burden v United Kingdom</em> (2008) 47 EHRR 38, in which the Grand Chamber at [62]-[63] agreed with <em>Shackell</em> that marriage conferred a special status, but that was for the purpose of holding that sisters who had lived together all their adult lives were not in an analogous situation to married couples or civil partners for the purpose of inheritance tax relief</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
(1987) 9 EHRR CD 555.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
(n 2) [28].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
ibid, [38].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
ibid, [39].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
ibid, [40].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
ibid, [43].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
ibid. On this test, Lady Hale cited <em>Christian Institute v Lord Advocate</em> [2016] UKSC 51, [88]. At [88] of <em>Christian Institute</em>, Lord Neuberger noted that: “…an <em>ab ante</em> challenge to the validity of legislation on the basis of a lack of proportionality faces a high hurdle: if a legislative provision is capable of being operated in a manner which is compatible with Convention rights in that it will not give rise to an unjustified interference with article 8 rights in all or almost all cases, the legislation itself will not be incompatible with Convention rights”</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
ibid, [49].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
ibid.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
ibid, [64].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
Under s.2(1) Human Rights Act 1998, if a domestic court “must take into account” Strasbourg jurisprudence when it considers “relevant to the proceedings in which that question has arisen.”</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
(n 16).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
(n 2) [79].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
ibid, [74].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
ibid, [75].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
ibid, [76].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="23" href="#inline23">[23]</a>
(n 13).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="24" href="#inline24">[24]</a>
“Rights Brought Home: the Human Rights Bill” (October 1997) <a href="https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/263526/rights.pdf">https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/263526/rights.pdf</a> (accessed 23rd February 2019).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="25" href="#inline25">[25]</a>
[2014] UKSC 35, [52].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="26" href="#inline26">[26]</a>
ibid, [53].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="27" href="#inline27">[27]</a>
[2014] UKSC 38, [322].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="28" href="#inline28">[28]</a>
On the question of whether the Human Rights Act 1998 may constitute a “constitutional” statute and thus enjoying a “superior” status compared to other pieces of ordinary legislation, see Laws LJ in <em>Thoburn v Sunderland City Council</em> [2002] EWHC 195, at [62]. Aileen Kavanagh observes that in terms of status, the Human Rights Act lacks formal supremacy as it makes no provision making it harder to repeal than any other ordinary legislation: A Kavanagh, <em>Constitutional Review under the Human Rights Act</em> (2009), 293.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="29" href="#inline29">[29]</a>
On a related note, it is interesting to note that the judges discussed the applicability of Strasbourg jurisprudence without actually mentioning the use of s.2 HRA 1998. It is submitted that the lack of reference to the HRA when considering the applicability of Strasbourg jurisprudence is suggestive of the court’s awareness to develop domestic common law jurisprudence with comparative insights from Strasbourg, instead of relying overtly on the HRA itself. This looms in a larger background, which cannot be discussed in the limited space of this case note, of the Conservative Government’s desire to repeal the Human Rights Act with a British Bill of Rights and the court’s corresponding role and awareness of developing a domestic human rights jurisprudence regime without always having recourse to Strasbourg via  the Human Rights Act.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="30" href="#inline30">[30]</a>
[2010] UKSC 45, [48].</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>A tale of two systems: separation or separability of Hong Kong common law and Chinese socialist legal system?</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/03/tale-two-systems-separation-separability-hong-kong/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/03/tale-two-systems-separation-separability-hong-kong/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Case note: <em>Sixtus Leung v President of the Legislative Council  </em>HCAL 1160, 1164, 1165, 1171 &amp; 1178/2018<a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a></strong></p>

<p>As a special administrative region of the People’s Republic of China (“<strong>PRC</strong>”), Hong Kong’s common law system is unique: it is not subordinate to the civil law system in PRC, but the Standing Committee of the National People’s Congress (“<strong>NPCSC</strong>”), as a legislative body, has the power to issue binding interpretations on the Hong Kong Basic Law (“<strong>BL</strong>”). This presents a peculiar scenario which flouts the traditional western understanding of separation of powers: a legislature is able to make binding interpretations on judicial organs. Given the recent increases in attention paid to the relationship between the Hong Kong judiciary and the Central Government,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> it is of topical interest to examine it in light of another legal controversy concerning the relationship between Hong Kong and the PRC: the “co-location” agreement  at the West Kowloon high-speed rail station (“<strong>WKS</strong>”), which saw, for the first time, PRC laws being directly applicable in Hong Kong territory. This case note analyses the judgement of <em>Sixtus Leung v President of the Legislative Council</em>,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> and the relationship between decisions reached by the Central Government and the Hong Kong legal system. Examining the judgement’s analysis on the status of the NPCSC Decision on approving the co-location agreement (“<strong>the Decision</strong>”) and the Guangzhou-Shenzhen-Hong Kong Express Rail Link (Co-location) Ordinance’s<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> (“<strong>the</strong> <strong>Ordinance</strong>”) consistency with the BL, it will be argue that it fails to engage comprehensively and specifically with the legal and constitutional basis of the co-location agreement.</p>

<h5 id="factual-and-legal-background">Factual and legal background</h5>

<p>The Decision was delivered on 27 December 2017. For present purposes, the material parts of the Decision are as follows (as translated by the court in the judgement):</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The NPCSC is of the view that the making of an appropriate arrangement through consultation on issues relating to the establishment of a port at the West Kowloon Station and the implementation of co-location arrangement thereat by the Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region with the relevant parties of the Mainland is a clear demonstration of the exercise of a high degree of autonomy by the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region in accordance with law.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The establishment of the Mainland Port Area (…) does not affect the high degree of autonomy enjoyed by the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region in accordance with law. Out of the need to implement the co-location arrangement at WKS, it is appropriate that the Co-operation Arrangement makes provisions for the delineation of jurisdiction (including the jurisdiction of the courts).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The PRC authorities’ performance of duties and functions in accordance with PRC laws is different from the application of national laws in the entire region of Hong Kong under Article 18 of the BL.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The Ordinance formally came into force on 4 September 2018. Section 6(1) provides that, except for “reserved matters,” the Mainland Port Area (“MPA”) is to be regarded as an area lying outside Hong Kong but lying within the Mainland for the purposes of (i) application of applicable laws and (ii) delineation of jurisdiction (including the jurisdiction of courts within the area) over the MPA. Section 6(2) states that section 6(1) does not affect the administrative division of Hong Kong.</p>

<p>Five judicial review claims were brought. In summary, they concerned the constitutionality of the Ordinance under the BL and the effect of the NPCSC decision in determining the constitutionality of the Ordinance. For the purposes of the present case note, the following principles about the legal status of PRC laws in Hong Kong and an interpretation made by the NPCSC on the BL should be noted:-</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>PRC laws do not apply in Hong Kong except for those listed in Annex III: Article 18(1) and (2) BL. In the present case, Chow J noted that the applicability of PRC laws in Hong Kong is “fairly limited in scope.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Article 159(4) BL provides that amendments to the BL should not contravene the “established basic policies” of PRC regarding Hong Kong.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Hong Kong courts are bound by any relevant interpretation of the BL by the NPCSC, regardless of whether the provision in question falls within or outside the excluded provisions referred to in Article 158(3).<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="the-judgement">The Judgement</h5>

<p>Chow J began by stating the common law approach to the interpretation of BL - the court’s role is to construe the language used in the text of BL in order to ascertain the legislative intent as expressed in the language.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> It is necessary to identify the meaning borne by the language when considered in light of its context and purpose. He then noted the need to treat the BL as a “living instrument,” meeting the changing needs and circumstances of the society.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> He also referred to the Court of Appeal’s judgement in <em>Leung Sze Ho Albert v Bar Council of the Hong Kong Bar Association </em>(2015), where Poon JA noted that the court gives “due regard to its historical context but is not unduly restricted by it. The court always treats the BL as a living norm, rooted in the past but intended to be responsive to contemporaneous needs and circumstances, and gives it an interpretation that truly reflects firmly held modern views in the current social and legal landscape.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a></p>

<h6 id="legal-status-of-the-npcsc-decision-under-prc-laws-and-hong-kong-laws"><u>Legal status of the NPCSC decision under PRC laws and Hong Kong laws</u></h6>

<p>In terms of the legal status of the Decision under PRC laws, after noting that the Decision was not made pursuant to the procedure prescribed by Article 158(1), Chow J stated that “what is important is not whether it is appropriate (or inappropriate), or whether there are some other alternative methods, for the NPCSC to deal with the matter by issuing a decision, but whether the NPCSC has legal power to do so.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> He also observed that the Court of Final Appeal has, on more than one occasion, confirmed that power of the NPCSC to interpret the BL under Article 67(4) of the PRC Constitution referred to Article 158(1) is free-standing and not qualified in any way by Article 158(2) and (3).<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a></p>

<p>Turning to the legal status of the Decision under Hong Kong law, the judge observed that, while the Decision might not necessarily be properly classified as made validly pursuant to Article 158(1), the Decision must “at least rank as ‘post-enactment materials’ which the Court of Final Appeal in <em>Chong Fung Yuen </em>did not exclude as being potentially admissible or relevant for the purpose of construing the BL where its meaning is not free from ambiguity.” He also, noted, that such materials must be approached “cautiously.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a> In relation to the Hong Kong courts’ power to determine the validity of the Decision under Hong Kong laws, Chow J stated that the courts have no power to determine whether the Decision is invalid under Hong Kong laws.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a> He also noted that it would be unrealistic to believe that the NPCSC will or may reach a different conclusion after consultation with the Basic Law Committee, and therefore the Decision can be used as an aid to the interpretation of the BL.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a></p>

<h6 id="the-consistency-of-the-ordinance-with-basic-law"><u>The consistency of the Ordinance with Basic Law</u></h6>

<p>Chow J began by noting that the proper question to ask is “whether, upon a fair reading of the BL and having regard to its context and purpose, it is intended that the Co-location Arrangement as embodied in the Ordinance, involving the creation of a port subject to the jurisdiction and laws of the Mainland, is intended to the prohibited or excluded.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> He then noted that, in order to answer the question, it is necessary to have regard to the context and purpose of the BL, particularly Articles 18(1) and (2), 19(2) and 80; he identified the aforementioned provisions as having the purpose to “give effect to the ‘two systems’ part of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a> He then stated that the creation of the MPA does not appear to be inconsistent with the purpose of the BL.</p>

<p>Observing the emphasis of the Hong Kong courts on the nature of the BL as a “living instrument,” Chow J noted that “the Basic Law should be treated as being capable of growth and development over time to meet new social, economic and political realities, and construed and applied in a manner which is responsive to contemporaneous needs and circumstances over its entire life.” A reading of the BL as prohibiting the co-location agreement would involve a failure to recognise the BL as a living instrument.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> He also noted that the establishment of the MPA and the customs, immigration and quarantine controls is a manifestation of the exercise of a high degree of autonomy by Hong Kong and the recognition of the two distinct and separate systems being practiced in Hong Kong and Mainland.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> Recognising that mere expediency is not a sufficient reason to justify arrangement which is otherwise inconsistent with the BL, Chow J nevertheless noted that the arrangement is “beneficial to the overall interests of Hong Kong” is a relevant consideration when determining whether such arrangement is prohibited by the BL.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a></p>

<h5 id="analysis-of-judgement-and-broader-implications">Analysis of judgement and broader implications</h5>

<h6 id="hong-kong-basic-law-and-common-law-in-the-shadow-of-the-interpretive-power-of-the-npcsc"><u>Hong Kong Basic Law and common law in the shadow of the interpretive power of the NPCSC</u></h6>

<p>The interplay between the Hong Kong legal system (in particular, in the area of constitutional law) and a legislative interpretation or decision made by the NPCSC is a unique arrangement. Despite being open to possible criticisms of a collapse of the doctrine of separation of powers,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> this should not be overemphasised in light of the designated role of the NPCSC under the BL. The BL is, after all, a creation of the PRC Constitution.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> That being said, it is unclear how “the will of the State”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a> would be remotely relevant in statutory interpretation in the BL context. It may be suggested that the “will of the State” equates to the doctrine of parliamentary sovereignty, but it would be premature to equate the two without substantiating the reasons beneath so. While they both represent the intention of the highest legislative authority of a country, the notion of “will of the State” as reflected in the present judgement focuses sharply on interpreting the BL, while Parliamentary Sovereignty is more generally understood as the legislative, not interpretive, intention of the legislature.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a></p>

<p>Chow J’s observation that the material consideration of the Decision under PRC laws should be “whether the NPCSC has the legal power to do so” is also problematic. It fails to justify why the significant emphasis should be on the legal power of NPCSC, and why the requirement to seek interpretation in accordance with the procedural requirements under Article 158 BL should play less weight. The fact that Chow J is only deciding on the legal status of the Decision itself and itself only would be of little avail to his defence. This is because he then supported his conclusion on the need for significant emphasis on the NPCSC’s legal power (and thus accepting the Respondent’s expert evidence) by referring to decisions of the Hong Kong Court of Final Appeal. The decisions cited, namely <em>Lau Kong Yung v Director of Immigration</em><a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a> and <em>Chong Fung Yuen</em>, both only noted that the power under Article 158(1) is in “general and qualified terms.” The court in <em>Chong Fung Yuen</em> has noted that this “extends to every provision of the Basic Law.” While it is true that the NPCSC does have an unlimited and general power to interpretive the substantive provisions of the BL, the case for procedural cautions and safeguards is not fully dealt with. The fact that it is unclear whether the term “general and unqualified terms” also entails the non-necessity of any procedural requirements renders Chow J’s argumentation and analysis problematic.</p>

<p>The actual grounds for the co-location arrangement are unclear from the BL itself. The Decision only made reference to Article 7 BL once, and it merely stated, without further elaboration, that the MPA is consistent with Article 7 BL.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline25" href="#25">25</a> This position is, nevertheless, not devoid of academic support. Yap and Jiang, in arguing that co-location is constitutional under the BL, stated that Article 7 can serve as the basis for the relinquishment of legal control over land. They also noted that the Constitution needs to be flexible to some degree, and remain relevant beyond those foreseeable by the drafters. The use of “ample and general language” suggests an intention of constitutional clauses to take on meaning beyond the original expected meaning.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline26" href="#26">26</a> While this analysis engages accurately with the “living instrument” analysis under the BL and the role of courts in interpreting the BL, it still fails to respond as to why it would authorise the government to “relinquish” control; the argument advanced only presented practical justifications, and does not provide a coherent theoretical basis. Nowhere in Article 7 suggests that the Hong Kong Government can give up control of the land and natural resources within the territory. Even if the alleged constitutional authority to set up an MPA and apply PRC laws there is said to be found under the “lease or grant” part of Article 7, it still does not explain how the Hong Kong government has authority to give up control of the territory in question. The purported “implied authority” is inconsistent with the express wording of Article 7. While Chow J is, strictly speaking, not required to examine the alleged validity of authority under Article 7, the crystal clear difficulty to reconcile the co-location arrangement and Article 7 BL demonstrates the possible effects of the binding interpretive validity of the NPCSC Decision, regardless of how unfounded it may be to a lawyer with a common law background.</p>

<h5 id="the-judges-interpretation-of-living-instrument-and-implications27"><u>The judge's interpretation of "living" instrument and implications<a class="inline-reference" id="inline27" href="#27">27</a></u></h5>

<p>It must first be borne in mind that Chow J’s observations from paragraph 70 onwards are very difficult to challenge on appeal, as they mainly concern findings of fact and the judge’s personal of the high-speed rail project at WKS. That being said, it does not mean it is immune from academic criticism; however, it would be inappropriate to criticise it from the Strasbourg perspective and jurisprudence on “living instrument,” as the notion as applied in Hong Kong and Strasbourg do not share similar considerations. It is submitted that, in Chow J’s judgement, the notion and view of “best interests” are not sufficiently unpacked.</p>

<p>To begin with, Chow J’s observations that the co-location is “designed to advance the overall best interests of Hong Kong”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline28" href="#28">28</a> appears to have conflated the co-location agreement with the high-speed rail project. It was common ground between the parties that the project would be in the economic interests of Hong Kong (the question of to what extent this is true is not the scope of the present analysis), but it is clear that the co-location agreement is not strictly necessary to achieve that effect. Moving on, the interpretation of “living instrument” is very expansive. The crystal clear legal conundrums and political divisions caused by the co-location agreement (i.e. in summary, the uncertainty of the benefits of such arrangement, if any), should have certainly weighted, or at least factored, against interpreting “living instrument” broadly. None of those were taken into account, or at least into notice, in Chow J’s analysis. Last but not least, it may be criticised that Chow J’s analysis is influenced by the fact that the co-location has been implemented and already operating on a daily basis. To declare the co-location agreement unconstitutional at this point would, obviously, be impractical. This is mainly reflected in Chow J’s considerable observations on the “overall benefit” of the co-location arrangement to Hong Kong. The deeper and more important constitutional issues underlying therein, however, appears to remain unresolved.</p>

<p>The establishment of MPA and setting up of customs, immigration and quarantine control is also considered by Chow J as “itself a manifestation of the exercise of a high degree of autonomy by Hong Kong and the recognition of two distinct and separate systems.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline29" href="#29">29</a> A few comments can be made about this observation. Firstly, the observation is confusing as the Mainland Port Area is still Hong Kong territory, although it is now governed by Mainland law. The so-called distinction drawn between the two systems is (i) unrealistic, (ii) inconsistent with the previous analysis in the sense that it is Hong Kong herself only exercising a high degree of autonomy and (iii) confusing - in the sense that it conflates the principle-based concerns of the integrity of “one country, two systems” with the practicalities of implementation. The fact that something may be comparatively expedient to do so (compared to other solutions) does not mean it should be preferred without sufficient scrutiny.</p>

<p>Finally, a point should be made about the status of the Decision as “post-enactment materials” for the purpose of interpreting the BL. In the judgement, Chow J recognised that post-enactment materials are applicable in interpreting the BL where its meaning is not free from ambiguity.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline30" href="#30">30</a> The consideration of such materials, moreover, must be “approached cautiously.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline31" href="#31">31</a> In the present case, however, it is not clear what and where the “ambiguity” is. It would be too quick for Chow J at paragraph 75 to proceed on the basis that it should immediately consider it as “post-enactment materials”. It turns on the following question: if the post-enactment material in question is merely endorsed without substantiating the reasons behind (adequately), should HK courts still adopt it without further analysis? If yes, this appears to defeat the very purpose of reasoning – to see arguments being substantiated sufficiently by relevant authorities. The requirement for comprehensive and watertight reasoning is particularly pertinent in the context of common law constitutional interpretation as it emphasises incremental development of reasoning, instead of reaching a conclusion based on ill-defined terms which serve ambiguous purposes.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline32" href="#32">32</a> The role and weight of the broader political context in constitutional interpretation also should not be ignored.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline33" href="#33">33</a></p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p><em>Sixtus Leung v President of the Legislative Council</em> is another good example of the interaction of the relationship between the Hong Kong courts and the decisions of the NPCSC, and the roles played by the respective institutions. While Chow J’s analysis has followed comfortably with the precedents, the lack of particularity in the important areas of the judgement is regrettable. The judgement also, interestingly, potentially suggests the need for a more elaborate doctrine of “living instrument” in interpreting the BL. For the Hong Kong legal system, concise interpretation in constitutional matters is not only crucial in maintaining the rule of law, but more importantly, to delineate its relationship with decisions of the NPCSC, which, at least from a common law lawyer’s perspective, can generate questions as to whether the two systems are separated or separable.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
Many thanks to William Wong and Ines Chu on their insights on issues of constitutional interpretation under the Hong Kong Basic Law. Any errors or omissions remain my own.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
This is especially notable after the 2016 Legislative Council elections, when two successful candidates were “disqualified” as a result of their failure (which were adjudged to violate the BL: <em>Chief Executive of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region and Others v Leung Chung Hang and Yau Wai Ching</em> HCAL 185/2016) to adhere to the rules of the oath-taking ceremony. The NPCSC has, unprecedented then, issued an interpretation of the BL in the absence of a request for interpretation from the Court of Final Appeal.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
HCAl 1160, 1164, 1165, 1171 and 1178/2018.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
Cap. 632.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
(n 3) [43].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
<em>Chong Fung Yuen v Director of Immigration</em> FACV 26/2000, (2001) 4 HKCFAR 211, 222F-223D.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
(n 3) [49].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [51].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
CACV 246/2015, [60].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
(n 3) [56].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [58].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [61].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [62].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [75].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [68].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [69].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [70].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
<em>Ibid</em>, [71].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [72].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
The question of the structure of separation of powers in Hong Kong is a sophisticated topic which cannot be briefly summarised here. Interested readers may consider consulting B Tai, “One Country Two Systems: Two Perspectives” (2002) <em>Macau Law Journal</em> (Special Issue) 143 and A Chen, “The interpretation of Basic Law - common law and mainland Chinese perspectives” (2002) 30(3) <em>Hong Kong Law Journal</em> 380.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
The power of the NPCSC to supervise the implementation under Article 67(1) of the PRC Constitution includes its power to implement the “one country, two systems” framework, pursuant to Article 31 of the PRC Constitution.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
(n 3) Respondent’s expert evidence of Professor Wang Lei of Peking University, noted at [53(5)] of the judgement and accepted by Chow J at [58].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="23" href="#inline23">[23]</a>
For a general analysis of the nature of parliamentary sovereignty in relation to the court’s position in the British context (and in particular, in the context of the Human Rights Act 1998), see C Gearty, <em>On Fantasy Island</em> (Oxford; 2016), chapters 5-6.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="24" href="#inline24">[24]</a>
FACV 10 and 11/1999, at [57].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="25" href="#inline25">[25]</a>
(n 3) [19].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="26" href="#inline26">[26]</a>
P J yap and Z Jiang, “Co-location is Constitutional” (2018) 48 <em>Hong Kong Law Journal</em> 37.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="27" href="#inline27">[27]</a>
It should be flagged up here that the notion of “living instrument” here as applied by Hong Kong courts does not necessarily draw inspiration from Strasbourg jurisprudence. An example of the cautious approach of Hong Kong courts to Strasbourg jurisprudence can be found in <em>ZN v Secretary of State for Justice and others</em> CACV 41/2017, at [100]: “The present case, in my view, is a prime example where this court must approach the relevant jurisprudence from the European Court of Human Rights with great caution. Whilst the European court in <em>Rantsev</em> emphasised that human trafficking is a global phenomenon calling for measures to combat it and that the European Convention has to be construed as a living instrument accordingly, understandably, it looked at matters from the European prospective (paras 277 to 279)…”</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="28" href="#inline28">[28]</a>
(n 3) [70].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="29" href="#inline29">[29]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [71].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="30" href="#inline30">[30]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [61].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="31" href="#inline31">[31]</a>
<em>ibid</em>, [62].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="32" href="#inline32">[32]</a>
The importance of language and the need to approach it holistically instead of in isolation was noted in <em>Chong Fung Yuen</em> (n 6) above, at 223-224.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="33" href="#inline33">[33]</a>
See D Feldman, “Statutory Interpretation and Constitutional Legislation” (2014) LQR 473.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>“I felt cheated”[1]: a lost opportunity for upholding a right to terminate life with dignity</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/02/felt-cheated-lost-opportunity-upholding-right-terminate-life/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/02/felt-cheated-lost-opportunity-upholding-right-terminate-life/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Case note: <em>R (on the application of Conway) v Secretary of State for Justice</em> (27 November 2018)<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a></strong></p>

<p>The topical issue of assisted dying (“AD”) has shadowed over medical law and human rights law with numerous considerations, including the need to respect the patient’s right to family life and safeguarding the sanctity of life.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> Since the Supreme Court’s seminal decision in <em>R (on the application of Nicklinson) v Secretary of State of Justice,</em><a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> the spotlight is placed on the respective institutional appropriateness of the courts and Parliament in addressing AD. The recent <em>Conway</em> litigation (since 2017) has reignited optimism of a right for terminally ill patients to AD. However, the Supreme Court’s rejection of permission to appeal<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a> has unsatisfactorily extinguished the optimism. This Note analyses the Supreme Court’s approach to the contentions underlying the right to AD and its balancing exercise, arguing that it is incoherent and fails to articulate succinctly its own approach. The Note will also briefly examine the wider human rights law implications of the rejection in the medical law context. It will be argued that the Supreme Court’s rejection is an unfortunate submission to the authority of the Parliament, and fails to live up to the optimism given by <em>Nicklinson</em>.</p>

<h5 id="factual-and-legal-backgrounds">Factual and legal backgrounds</h5>

<p>Mr Noel Conway is 67 years old and has terminal motor neurone disease. In contrast to <em>Nicklinson</em>, Mr Conway’s disease is a terminal illness. Mr Nicklinson’s locked-in syndrome, whilst resulting in total paralysis, does not threaten him with imminent death. Medical evidence shows that it is possible for his breathing muscles to collapse, meaning he could die at any time. He wishes in the final six months of his life to enlist the assistance of a medical professional to bring about his death. Mr Conway sought permission to appeal for judicial review to argue for a declaration of incompatibility (“DOI”)<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> that the offence of assisted suicide<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> disproportionately infringed his Article 8(1) ECHR right. Section 2(1) SA criminalises those persons who commit an act capable of encouraging or assisting the suicide or attempted suicide of another person, and their act was intended to encourage or assist suicide or an attempt at suicide.</p>

<p>Since the decisions of the Supreme Court and the European Court of Human Rights (admissibility stage), the Parliament has considered the question of a right to die for gravely ill patients. However, all three private members bill were rejected. That being said, there were intense parliamentary debates during the second reading of the Bill.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a></p>

<h5 id="appeal-history">Appeal history</h5>

<p>Refusing the application for judicial review, the High Court noted “the difficulty of formulating a clear and reliable criterion for who is to qualify as terminally ill under the scheme…is a factor of some relevance as indicating again the difficult legislative nature of the choices to be made in fashioning any such scheme.” Given such lack of clarity, it is legitimate “for the legislature to seek to lay down clear and defensible standards in order to…avoid distressing and difficult disputes at the end of life and to avoid creating a slippery slope leading to incremental expansion over time of the categories of people to whom similar assistance of suicide might have to be provided.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a> It also took note of the Parliament’s decision to maintain section 2 as it is,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> despite the <em>Nicklinson</em> ruling.</p>

<p>In the Court of Appeal, the court made explicit notice of the moral and ethical issues underlying a right to AD.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a> The implications arising from Mr Conway’s scheme, including the inquisitorial role of a judge and the potential for expansion to non-terminal diseases, are “wide-ranging policy issues”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a> and that the Parliament is “a far better body” for determining “conflicting, and highly contested, views within our society on the ethical and moral issues and the risks and potential consequences of a change in the law…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a> This reflects the similar concerns the Supreme Court had in <em>Nicklinson</em>, albeit in a different context.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a></p>

<p>The question posed before the Supreme Court was whether Mr Conway’s case raises an arguable point of law of general public importance which ought to be heard by the court.</p>

<h5 id="the-courts-confusing-approach-to-the-balance-between-letting-someone-die-and-taking-active-steps-to-bring-about-their-death">The court’s confusing approach to the balance between “letting someone die” and “taking active steps to bring about their death”</h5>

<p>The Supreme Court began at <a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> by distinguishing between “letting someone die” and “taking active steps to bring about their death.” It then noted the contribution of the HRA to the distinction and the debate around it: “All are agreed that the ban on assisting suicide is an interference with the right to respect for private life.” It also correctly noted that there is no European consensus on the matter. This is reflected in the ECtHR judgement in <em>Nicklinson v United Kingdom</em> that contracting states are free to determine “which of the three branches of government should be responsible for taking policy and legislative decisions which fall within their margin of appreciation and it is not for this Court to involve itself in their internal institutional arrangements.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> Furthermore, the Supreme Court noted that the ultimate question is “whether the prospects of Mr Conway succeeding in his claim…are sufficient to justify to justify our giving him permission…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a></p>

<p>In a somewhat surprising turn, the Supreme Court conclusion is vague and unsatisfactory without addressing the key questions it posed in the order’s foregoing paragraphs. In paragraphs [5] and [6], the Supreme Court noted that the question is whether an “arguable point of law of general public importance” is raised, the appropriateness of a “hard and fast rule”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> banning all cases of AD, and the possibility of a DOI if the said “hard and fast rule” is incompatible with the ECHR In dodging the issue raised, the Supreme Court merely concluded that “not without some reluctance, it has been concluded that…those prospects are not sufficient to justify giving permission to appeal.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> In light of the court’s recognition that AD raises arguable points of law,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a> the court’s conclusion on the lack of sufficient prospects throws such recognition into doubt in the first place. The legal and moral conundrums surrounding AD have been well-recognised by the Parliament, domestic courts and the Strasbourg court. The clear distinction in terms of context between <em>Nicklinson</em> and the <em>Conway</em> litigation led to a sharp focus on the permissibility of AD for patients with not ordinary, but terminal illness.</p>

<p>More disconcerting is the dissonance between the court’s wide considerations and its hasty conclusion. The considerations the court set out include: (i) the moral and practical implications of AD, (ii) the role of the HRA, (iii) the nature of “a hard and fast rule,” (iv) the interplay between courts and the Parliament, and (v) the role of courts in case of finding (on a principle-level) the inappropriateness of a hard and fast rule.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> Despite neatly and correctly observing the relevant concerns in the AD debate (particularly in light of <em>Nicklinson</em>), the conclusion of a lack of prospect does not reflect the nature of the considerations mentioned. The dissonance is twofold. Firstly, it is not clear how the factors are weighed against one another in the Supreme Court’s deliberation. Some of the factors, for example (i) and (iii), are legal questions marred with significant moral considerations.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> Others, however, are questions of constitutional law posed in response to the legal-moral consideration raised by factors (i) and (iii). The notion and meaning of “prospect” in the present case do not appear well-substantiated enough to justify the refusal of appeal. Secondly, and more seriously, it throws the standard and criteria for a successful appeal into doubt. Given the obvious general public importance of the issue, it remains unclear what factors tilted the courts towards rejecting the permission. Although the court is only required to give “brief reasons” for refusing an appeal,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a> no such brief discourse of the factors was mentioned. This leaves the deliberation of the judges and reason for refusal in a mystified state.</p>

<h5 id="the-broader-implications-ofconway">The broader implications of <em>Conway</em></h5>

<p>On the surface, the prospects appear dim: the <em>Nicklinson</em> litigation (including the ECtHR decision) firmly established the role of the Parliament in deliberating and devising a framework for AD; the <em>Conway</em> litigation showed that even for patients with terminal illness, palliative care is the only viable option for them; the Parliament has also rejected (on three instances) private members’ bill for AD. Commenting on the Supreme Court’s decision in <em>Nicklinson</em>, Wicks noted that the reluctance to declare the existing law as incompatible is a “worrying new approach to the courts’ powers under the HRA.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a> This worry, whilst potentially unrealistic back in 2014, appears a more understandable perspective in light of the Supreme Court’s rejection. Moreover, given the intense nature of the parliamentary debates on the AD Bills and topical nature of AD, it is submitted that it is institutionally appropriate for the Supreme Court to take a more active approach. By issuing a DOI under section 4 HRA, it can engage with the Parliament in an institutional dialogue on such an issue. Although the nature and usefulness of such dialogue are beyond the scope of this Note,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a> such possibility should not be dismissed without detailed considerations in the first place. It should be highlighted, however, that a meaningful dialogue would at least require the Parliament to take into account the reasons underlying the DOI when it debates on any legislative amendments or enactments.</p>

<p>The key question left by <em>Nicklinson</em>, and arguably unresolved by <em>Conway</em>, is whether the Parliament is required to have “satisfactorily addressed” the question of relaxing or modifying section 2(1) SA 1961. Although the Director of Public Prosecutions, in a new set of guidelines published as a result of the <em>Nicklinson</em> litigation, stated that medical practitioners will not be prosecuted if it administers palliative care ultimately leading to the patient’s death. The right to AD itself was still scarcely scratched upon. What <em>Conway</em> does, apart from the legal conundrums presented above, is a comprehensive framework for patients who wish to exercise a right to AD. In particular, the framework recommended very strict requirements for such right to be exercised: (i) terminal illness with less than six months to live, (ii) Informed, settled and voluntary consent given by the patient, and (iii) evidence of mental capacity. Although a sophisticated framework cannot be devised by the courts, it is nevertheless possible for Parliament to consider at least discussing a proposal of a similar kind.</p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p>The highly contentious nature of AD logically implies that it is an issue that cannot be resoundingly settled in a short period of time. Given the topical interest <em>Conway</em> (and <em>Nicklinson</em>) have generated, it is submitted that courts and parliament should adopt a more active stance articulating the boundaries of such right. The Supreme Court’s refusal of permission to appeal, however, is an unfortunate step back for respecting the right to private and family life for terminally ill patients. It leaves them in a state of potential despair with their dignity jeopardised by the illness they have to suffer.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
Mr Conway’s response to the refusal. F Walsh, “‘I feel cheated’ - right to die campaigner” <em>BBC News</em> (8 December 2018) <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-46475083">https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-46475083</a> (accessed 9 December 2018)</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
Unlike other case notes, given that <em>Conway</em> litigation raises similar questions and concerns with the previous <em>Nicklinson</em> litigation, this case note will make frequent reference to <em>Nicklinson</em> in order to emphasise why the refusal is particularly unfortunate in light of the Supreme Court’s decision in <em>Nicklinson</em>.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
Respectively, Articles 8 and 2 of the European Convention on Human Rights (“ECHR”).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
[2014] UKSC 38.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
<em>R (on the application of Conway) v Secretary of State for Justice</em> (27 November 2018).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
Section 4(2), Human Rights Act 1998 (“HRA”).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
Section 2(1), Suicide Act 1961 (“SA”).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
C Hobson, “Is it now institutionally appropriate for courts to consider whether the assisted dying ban is human rights compatible? <em>Conway v Secretary of State for Justice</em>” (2018) 26(3) <em>Medical Law Review</em> 514, 523.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
[2017] EWHC 2447 (Admin), [127].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
Ibid [90].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
[2018] EWCA Civ 1431, [135]-[139].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
Ibid [178].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
Ibid [186].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
Two major factors distinguish <em>Nicklinson</em> and <em>Conway</em>: (i) when <em>Nicklinson</em> was before the Supreme Court, the Parliament was debating on an AD bill; (ii) <em>Nicklinson</em> concerned non-terminal illness (locked-in syndrome), while <em>Conway</em> concerned terminal-illness (Motor neuron disease).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
<em>Nicklinson and Lamb v United Kingdom</em>(2015) 61 EHRR 97, [84].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
(n 4) [8].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
Ibid, [6].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
Ibid [8].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
Ibid [6].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
Ibid. Factors (i) to (iii) are discussed in [6[; factors (iv) and (v) are considered in [7].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
This means that whilst the factors are <em>prima facie</em> legal questions, a satisfactory answer would necessarily have recourse to moral considerations. For example, the question of the appropriateness of a “hard and fast rule” in the present context would inquire upon the weight to be given to moral considerations over, for example, the dignity of the terminally-ill patient. For further references, please see “Law” in R Dworkin, <em>Justice for Hedgehogs</em> (HUP; Cambridge, 2011), which argues that there is a necessary conceptual connection between law and morality.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
Supreme Court practice direction 3.3.3.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="23" href="#inline23">[23]</a>
E Wicks, “The Supreme Court Judgement in <em>Nicklinson</em>: One step forward on assisted dying; two steps back on human rights” (2014) 23(1) <em>Medical Law Review</em> 144, 154.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="24" href="#inline24">[24]</a>
For readers are interested on this issue, the following cases and the related parliamentary reactions are recommended: <em>Hirst v United Kingdom (No.2)</em> (2006) 42 EHRR 1; <em>R (F) Secretary of state for the Home Department</em> [2010] UKSC 17; <em>R (Prothero) v Secretary of State for the Home Department</em> [2013] EWHC 2830 (Admin).</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>A symphony of parliamentary sovereignty</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2019/01/symphony-parliamentary-sovereignty/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2019-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2019/01/symphony-parliamentary-sovereignty/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>– Case note: <em>Case C-621/18 Wightman v Secretary of State for Exiting the European Union</em></strong></p>

<p>Since the Supreme Court’s (“SC”) landmark judgement in <em>R (on the application of Gina Miller) v Secretary of State for Exiting the European Union</em>,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a> the legal position and powers of the Westminster Parliament have been at the epicentre of the Brexit legal conundrum. The recent preliminary ruling given by the European Court of Wightman v Secretary of State for Exiting the European Union<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> has added an extra layer of complexity to it by holding that te Parliament can unilaterally revoke the notification to withdraw from the European Union (“EU”) under Article 50 of the Treaty of Lisbon (“TEU”). Agreeing with Advocate General Sánchez-Bordona’s (“AG”) opinion,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> the ECJ held that certain constitutional requirements have to be satisfied for a member state to revoke the notification unilaterally. This Note analyses the AG’s opinion and ECJ’s judgement, suggesting that it is a prudent manifestation of the doctrine of parliamentary sovereignty. It will also briefly examine the constitutional implications of the judgement on the Brexit process in terms of any requirements for revocation. It will be argued that Wightman offers, in line with Miller, a second opportunity to shape and influence the Brexit process.</p>

<h5 id="advocate-generals-opinion-and-the-european-court-of-justices-ruling">Advocate-General’s opinion and the European Court of Justice’s ruling</h5>

<p>To begin with, the AG recognised that the right of a State to be no longer bound (withdrawal or denunciation) by a treaty is “a manifestation of that State’s sovereignty.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a> By corollary of principle, the unilateral nature of withdrawal is “conducive to the possibility of unilaterally revoking the notification of that decision;” unilateral revocation is also “a manifestation of the sovereignty of the departing Member State.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a> The intention of the sovereign state is, however, “not definitive and may change.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> Any claims of such change, and therefore any revocation of the notification of withdrawal, must be expressed “in accordance with… [the sovereign state’s] constitutional requirements.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> This may be manifested in, for example, “a political change that gives rise to a change in the will of the departing State…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> This shows that the credibility of the notification of withdrawal is heavily dependent on its constitutional basis. Once any intervening political intervention undermines the credibility of the original notification, the parliamentary intention is also expected to change in order to reflect the latest public opinions.</p>

<p>The AG further strengthened the case for revocability when interpreting Article teleologically. He recognised that Article 50(1) is not a “fossilised concept,” and it respects “the national identities of the member states.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a> It also allows “a change in the sovereign will of the Member State…in order to halt a process of withdrawal from the EU which the Member State has decided to reverse.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> When the public opinions and parliamentary intentions within the Member State do not evince a clear position, the doctrine of favour socieatias may be considered as a key element in reaching a solution which is the “most consonant with the survival…of the Union.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a> This is largely in line with the TEU’s objective of achieving “an ever closer union among the peoples of Europe.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a> This is a careful delineation of the position of the EU regarding political uncertainty in a Member State, as a teleological interpretation of Article 50 was not considered as strictly necessary and should only be considered if the Government cannot advance a credible stance in favour of withdrawal. Furthermore, it should be noted that the fundamental rights enjoyed by nationals of the departing Member State as EU citizens also play a significant role in favouring a teleological interpretation of Article 50 - that revocation is possible unless the Member State’s intention of departure is crystal clear. This reflects the majority of Miller in stating that any frustration of citizens’ rights as an EU citizen can only be done by parliamentary legislation.</p>

<p>The ECJ’s ruling is generally consistent with the AG”s opinion, emphasising the special status of the TEU and the constitutional character of the EU.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a> The ECJ also explored the constitutional requirements of withdrawal. In the following sections, the ECJ’s judgement and its implications will be analysed. It will be argued that the judgement represents prudent respect for parliamentary sovereignty in the United Kingdom, and successfully protects the integrity of Article 50, despite any possible doubts over a teleological approach to interpreting it.</p>

<h5 id="analysis-of-the-european-court-of-justices-judgement">Analysis of the European Court of Justice’s judgement</h5>

<p>The question posed to the ECJ was “where, in accordance with Article 50 [TEU], a Member State has notified by the European Council of its intention to withdraw from the European Union, does EU law permit that notice to be revoked unilaterally by the notifying Member State; and if so, subject to what conditions and with what effect relative to the Member State remaining within the European Union?”</p>

<h5 id="interpretation-of-eu-law-in-particular-article-50">Interpretation of EU law (in particular, Article 50)</h5>

<p>The ECJ stated that when interpreting a provision of EU law, account should be taken “not only of its wording and the objectives it pursues, but also of its context and the provisions…as a whole.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a> From the outset, it is clear that the court is not limiting itself to the meaning of Article 50 itself, but adopting a teleological approach in attempting to unpack the meaning of the provisions in question. The emphasis on the need to consider the constitutional structure and purpose of the EU as a whole<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a> reflect what Eeckhout and Frantziou noted a “constitutionalist approach,” which is an opportunity to “affirm that the structures [of EU] have come to constitute a new mode of post-State organisation, premised on cooperation, genuine respect for common values and fundamental rights, and a supranational citizenship.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a> The revocability of the notification of withdrawal is thus not only a question surrounding the Parliament’s political will, but also the need to maintain the integrity and pursuit of objectives of the EU. Whilst a teleological approach may be criticised as giving excessive weight to the objective of European integration in the status of Article 50, it is submitted that such approach is justified as Article 50 is a key component in shaping the composition of EU membership under the TEU. To adopt a literal interpretation of Article 50 would ignore the political realities which public law responds to.</p>

<h5 id="the-intention-of-a-departing-member-state-and-the-associated-rights-stripping-implications">The intention of a departing Member State and the associated rights stripping implications</h5>

<p>Having firmly established a teleological approach as its basis of approaching the question, the ECJ agreed with the AG’s opinion that the intention of a departing Member State is “neither definitive nor irrevocable.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> Moreover, it was noted that the two objectives pursued by Article 50 are (i) “enshrining the sovereign right of a Member  State to withdraw from the EU” and (ii) “establishing a procedure to enable such a withdrawal to take place in an orderly fashion.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> At this point, it is clear that Article 50 is not merely a matter of facilitating an expedient exit for a departing Member State, but more importantly, to respect the voluntary and flexible will of it. The sovereign will of the departing State is the most significant player in the Article 50 process. Given the absence of expression provision in EU law governing the revocation of notification to withdraw, the revocation should be “subject to the rules laid down in Article 50(1) TEU for the withdrawal itself…it may be decided upon unilaterally, in accordance with the constitutional requirements of the State concerned.” Revocation is, in essence, a “sovereign decision” by the State to retain its status as a Member State of the EU; the status is neither suspended nor altered by that notification.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline19" href="#19">19</a></p>

<p>The ECJ then moved to consider implications of withdrawal. The decision to withdraw is “liable to have a considerable impact on the rights of all Union citizens, including, inter alia, their right for free movement, as regards both nationals of the Member State concerned…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> Forcing a Member State to leave after it has triggered the Article 50 process, despite a wish to remain “as expressed through its democratic process in accordance with its constitutional requirements,” would be “inconsistent with the [TEU’s] purpose of creating an ever closer union…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> The intention of the Parliament will always have the final say in determining whether United Kingdom shall remain a Member State of the EU. This also reflects the origins and intention of Article 50, which in its final draft upheld “the voluntary and unilateral nature of the withdrawal decision.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a></p>

<h5 id="constitutional-requirements">Constitutional requirements</h5>

<p>Building on the AG’s recognition that any revocation must respect “national constitutional requirements,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a> the ECJ noted that any revocation must be made in an “unequivocal and unconditional manner….after the Member State concerned has taken the revocation decision in accordance with its constitutional requirements.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a> In the United Kingdom, given the judgement in Miller, this would suggest that the “constitutional requirement” in question would be passing primary legislation in the House of Commons revoking the notification of withdrawal as made under the European Union (Notification of Withdrawal) Act 2017. Noting that the sovereign State holds the final decision to revoke the notification to withdraw, the ECJ also correctly noted that any requirement of unanimous approval by the European Council would “transform a unilateral sovereign right into a conditional right subject to an approval procedure.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline25" href="#25">25</a> This also, prudently, confers the maximum respect for the Member State in deciding on revocation. Whilst revocation has to be made in accordance with its constitutional requirements and must be made in an “unequivocal and unconditional manner” (presumably meaning that the revocation should reflect popular will), it is the sovereign State alone that can construct the validity and credibility of the revocation. The European Council would have no democratic legitimacy in deciding on the revocation decision.</p>

<h5 id="implications-of-the-courts-judgement-the-relationship-between-the-european-union-and-the-united-kingdom-and-parliamentary-sovereignty">Implications of the Court’s judgement: the relationship between the European Union and the United Kingdom and parliamentary sovereignty</h5>

<p>The unique status of this preliminary ruling is that it is also a matter of political importance and urgency. Whilst constitutional law litigation (especially in the field of human rights) may be seen as predominantly a matter of upholding principles and values, it is clear that the preliminary ruling is primarily aimed at providing an alternative gateway for the Government out of the Brexit conundrum. As the AG accurately noted, the Wightman litigation is “not merely a jurisprudential issue,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline26" href="#26">26</a> and the legal consequences of Brexit are drawing “inexorably closer.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline27" href="#27">27</a></p>

<h5 id="parliaments-position-as-delineated-under-article-5">Parliament’s position as delineated under Article 5</h5>

<p>First and foremost, the judgement affirms the centrality of Article 50 in all questions regarding the notification of withdrawal and its revocation. As the Article concerns the structure and composition of the EU itself, any interpretation would “affect the Union’s very identity as a constitutional order committed to the values laid down in Article 2 TEU.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline28" href="#28">28</a> The constitutionalist reading adopted by the court reflects a cardinal principle underpinning the relationship between the EU and its Member States: the division of competence.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline29" href="#29">29</a> The judgement resoundingly puts the competence to decide on revocation firmly in the hands of the Parliament. The Parliament is and will always be in control of the Brexit process in terms of the continuation of negotiations and any decision to revoke its withdrawal notification.</p>

<p>The judgement also reflects the overarching necessity to respect the Member State’’s constitutional process. Following Eeckhout and Frantziou’s analysis of a “constitutionalist reading,” the judgement affords prudent respect to the United Kingdom’s uncodified constitution as “a form of constitutional organisation inherently susceptible to change through politics.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline30" href="#30">30</a> Moreover, one must not ignore the distinction between the decision to withdraw (Article 50(1)) and the notification of the decision (Article 50(2)). It would be unrealistic to draw any formalistic distinction between them<a class="inline-reference" id="inline31" href="#31">31</a> as a change in political realities (e.g. a shift of popular will under Article 50(1) to remain in the EU) would necessarily, as analysed above, undermine the credibility and legitimacy of the notification to withdraw (Article 50(2)). The validity of such change can, however, only be expressed by the Parliament in an unequivocal and unconditional manner.</p>

<h5 id="the-constitutional-requirements-of-article-50-a-symmetry-with-miller">The constitutional requirements of Article 50: a symmetry with Miller?</h5>

<p>Under section 13(1)(b) of the European Union (Withdrawal) Act 2018 (“EUWA”), the House of Commons must approve a withdrawal agreement before the agreement can be considered as ratified. This provides for the implementation of the intention to leave the EU.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline32" href="#32">32</a> Nowhere it is suggested that the Parliament’s intention before ratifying any withdrawal agreement must be fixed. Following the ECJ’s reasoning, a corollary of the Member State’s sovereign right to submit the notification to withdraw would be its sovereign right to revoke the notification. In terms of substance, the revocation decision has to be made in accordance with its constitutional requirements.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline33" href="#33">33</a></p>

<p>Given the 2018 Act provides for the implementation to withdraw, revoking the notification as submitted under Article 50 would necessarily strip the Members of Parliament off their rights to implement the withdrawal decision. To revoke using prerogative power, however, would render both the withdrawal agreement and any future framework between the EU and UK otiose.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline34" href="#34">34</a> This is because the Parliament will no longer be able to approve such instruments, once agreed. In both the AG’s opinion and the ECJ’s ruling, it is clear that the relationship between the criteria for triggering and revoking Article 50 is reciprocal: both triggering and revoking Article 50 must conform to the constitutional requirements of the Member State in question - in this case, the constitutional requirements of UK itself. At this point, the shadow of Miller flickers before us: the royal prerogative may not be exercised in a way that frustrates the intention of the Parliament as expressed in a statute.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline35" href="#35">35</a> The Prime Minister would not be able to use the prerogative in a way that frustrates the Parliament’s intention of implementing the decision to withdraw from the EU, as evinced by the EUWA 2018.</p>

<p>Last but not the least, Phillipson and Young suggested that given the ECJ’s emphasis on reciprocity and the need to ensure the democratic legitimacy of revocation, the insertion of an option for a referendum under section 13 of EUWA 2018 would not be sufficient. This is an accurate observation of the essence of the Miller judgement, as the provision of a referendum option does not entail sufficient credibility for revocation. Even if a second referendum opted for remaining in the EU, the lack of fresh legislation would mean that, based on Miller, the “constitutional requirements” for revoking the notification would not be satisfied, and thus any attempt to revoke the notification via non-legislative means would be unconstitutional.</p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p>The Wightman preliminary ruling authoritatively confirms that the power to revoke the notification of withdrawal is vested solely in the hands of the Parliament. Forming a conclusive symmetry with Miller, it supplied a clear direction and the respective constitutional requirements for the Government to consider if it considers revocation should become a real option. The manifestation of parliamentary sovereignty shows at, at the end of the day, the status of the UK as a Member State of the EU is not affected - it still has full competence to decide whether to continue the negotiations or revoke its notification of withdrawal. The teleological approach to interpreting Article 50 has also provided a clear and definitive guide in approaching the question of withdrawing from the EU: the status of the UK as a Member State of the EU contributes to the composition of the EU constitutional structure, insofar as it has not left the EU yet. Ultimately, the decision to stay as a Member State of the EU or leave it, under the Article 50 framework, is a matter for and only for the Parliament to decide: a manifestation of parliamentary sovereignty.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
[2017] UKSC 5.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
<em>Case C-621/18 Wightman and another v Secretary for Exiting the European Union</em> [2018] 12 WLUK 94.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
<em>Case C-621/18 Wightman and another v Secretary for Exiting the European Union</em> [2018] 12 WLUK 94, Opinion of AG Sánchez-Bordona.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
Ibid [93].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
Ibid [94].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
Ibid [100].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
Ibid [104].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
Ibid [107].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
Ibid [131].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
Ibid [132].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
Ibid [134].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
Article 1 TEU.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
(n 3) [44].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
Ibid [47].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
(n 14).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
P Eeckhout and E Frantziou, “Brexit and Article 50 TEU: a constitutionalist reading” (2017) 54 Common Market Law Review 695, 696-697.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
(n 3) [49]. The AG made a similar suggestion in his opinion, at [99]-[102].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
Ibid [56].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
Ibid [59].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
Ibid [64].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
Ibid [67].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
Ibid [68].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="23" href="#inline23">[23]</a>
(n 4) [144].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="24" href="#inline24">[24]</a>
(n 3) [74].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="25" href="#inline25">[25]</a>
Ibid [72].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="26" href="#inline26">[26]</a>
(n 4) [41].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="27" href="#inline27">[27]</a>
Ibid [40].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="28" href="#inline28">[28]</a>
(n 17) 698.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="29" href="#inline29">[29]</a>
Ibid 702.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="30" href="#inline30">[30]</a>
Ibid 710.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="31" href="#inline31">[31]</a>
G Phillipson, “A dive into deep constitutional waters: Article 50, the Prerogative and Parliament” (2016) 79(6) Modern Law Review 1064, 1064-1069.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="32" href="#inline32">[32]</a>
G Phillipson and A L Young, “Wightman: What would be the UK’s constitutional requirements to revoke Article 50?” UK Constitutional Law Blog (10 December 2018): <a href="https://ukconstitutionallaw.org/2018/12/10/gavin-phillipson-and-alison-l-young-wightman-what-would-be-the-uks-constitutional-requirements-to-revoke-article-50/">https://ukconstitutionallaw.org/2018/12/10/gavin-phillipson-and-alison-l-young-wightman-what-would-be-the-uks-constitutional-requirements-to-revoke-article-50/</a> (last accessed 14 January 2019)</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="33" href="#inline33">[33]</a>
(n 3) [75].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="34" href="#inline34">[34]</a>
(n 33).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="35" href="#inline35">[35]</a>
(n 1) [51].</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Medical exceptionalism: Best Interests From a Human Rights Perspective</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2018/12/medical-exceptionalism-best-interests-human-rights/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2018-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2018/12/medical-exceptionalism-best-interests-human-rights/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Case note: <em>Y v An NHS Trust and others [2018] UKSC 46</em></strong><a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a></p>

<p>The question over the necessity of obtaining court order for terminating clinically assisted nutrition and hydration (“CANH”) for patients with minimal prospects of recovery reflects  two competing  concerns: (i) the right to respect the private and family life of the patient and his/her family,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a> and (ii) the necessity to ensure that the decision to terminate life support is one which is thoroughly considered by all relevant stakeholders. The Supreme Court decision in Y v An NHS Trust and others<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a> has provided an insightful analysis of the non-necessity of obtaining a court order and the logic behind this. This note will analyse the decision from a human rights perspective on two levels. Firstly, it will examine Lady Black’s observations on English and Strasbourg jurisprudence. Secondly, it will examine the decision’s broader impact on the law’s respect for the concerns of the patient and family’s decisions in treatment withdrawal decisions, and the doctor’s role therein. It will come to the conclusion that the commendable decision has offered a desirable degree of autonomy for patients and their families  in making decisions to terminate medical treatment.</p>

<h5 id="facts-and-appellate-history">Facts and appellate history</h5>

<p>The patient, Mr Y, had a prolonged disorder of consciousness (“PDOC”). Medical  examinations suggest that he was unlikely to regain consciousness. He had neither executed any advance refusals nor appointed a lasting power of attorney under section 9 of the Mental Capacity Act 2005 (“MCA 2005”). The clinical team and Y’s family agreed that it would be in his best interests for CANH to be withdrawn, with the consequence that he would die within a period of two to three weeks. At first instance, O’Farrell J held that “it is not mandatory to bring before the court the withdrawal of CANH…in circumstances where the clinical team and Mr Y’s family have agreed that it is not in his best interests that he continues to receive that treatment.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a></p>

<p>Mr Y died on 22 December 2017. Nevertheless, the Supreme Court decided to hear the leapfrog appeal because of the general importance of the issues raised. It held that there is no legal requirement for parties to go to court in circumstances where the patient’s family and the clinical team agreed that it would be in the patient’s best interests to terminate CANH treatments. Neither the common law nor the ECHR gives rise to such mandatory requirements.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a></p>

<h5 id="lady-blacks-observations-of-i-english-jurisprudence-and-ii-the-ecthrs-stance">Lady Black’s observations of (i) English jurisprudence and (ii) the ECtHR’s stance </h5>

<h6 id="english-jurisprudence"><u>English jurisprudence</u></h6>

<p>The pertinent issue to consider here is how the legal requirement engages a patient’s Article 6 rights. By making court hearings a mandatory requirement, it is arguable that such hearing allows the patient to have a final chance of defence in relation to the proposed termination of treatment. However, for unconsciousness patients, it is questionable whether such defence is necessary or helpful if the patient’s family and the clinical team are of the same opinion that any continuation of treatment would not be in his best interests. Lady Black correctly observed<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a> that previous landmark decisions of Airedale NHS Trust v Bland,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a> In re F (Medical Patient: Sterilisation)<a class="inline-reference" id="inline8" href="#8">8</a> and R (Burke) v General Medical Council<a class="inline-reference" id="inline9" href="#9">9</a> did not lay down any common law requirements for doctors, upon agreement with family members, to obtain a court declaration before CANH can be terminated. Seeking declaration was merely “recommended” “as a matter of good practice.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline10" href="#10">10</a> While the illness concerned in the present case (PDOC) is different from the aforementioned cases,<a class="inline-reference" id="inline11" href="#11">11</a> the final outcome is similar: withdrawal of treatment according to the patient’s best interests. When the patient has lost consciousness, it would yield no practical results (not to mention benefits)  to require a court hearing, when the available opinions suggest that the termination would be in his best interests. For patients who have lost consciousness at least, the argument of engagement of Article 6 is at best artificial. Lady Black aptly dismisses it.</p>

<p>The implementation of the MCA 2005 and its Code of Practice aims to ensure that decisions to terminate treatment will be made in the patient’s best interests. Confusingly, the Code states that the court “has to make” or “must be asked to make” a decision about withdrawing treatment for a patient in PVS.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline12" href="#12">12</a> In clarifying the law post-MCA 2005, Lady Black stated the Code “in…plainly attempting to convey what the cases have so far decided, cannot extend the duty of the medical team beyond what the cases do in fact decide is incumbent upon them….”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline13" href="#13">13</a> This is consistent with previous decisions holding that there is no common law requirement for medical teams to apply for the court for a formal declaration. It also illustrates the law’s appropriately permissive approach in cases where the best interests of the patient are not contested between the medical team and the patient. Given the court’s role as a last resort for parties to plead a case in favour of continuing medical treatment, if the views on best interests point unanimously towards termination of treatment, no question of erosion of the right to life arise.</p>

<h6 id="strasbourg-jurisprudence"><u>Strasbourg jurisprudence</u></h6>

<p>After observing that domestic law does not impose any legal requirements for making an application, Lady Black turned to ECHR jurisprudence. She began with Lambert v France and the relevant French regulatory framework. Elaborating on ECtHR’s stance on the non-necessity of mandatory legal requirements together with the aforementioned observations, she concluded the English provisions under MCA 2005 and its Code is a “regulatory framework” as required by the European Court. They were designed to “protect the human rights of patients and their families.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline14" href="#14">14</a> The Lambert decision, arguably the most important Strasbourg decision in this respect, “does not regard it as problematic…that a decision to withhold or withdraw CANH…should be made by a doctor, without obligatory court involvement.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline15" href="#15">15</a></p>

<p>Lady Black identified three features in the European Court’s assessment: “the existence in domestic law and practice of a regulatory framework compatible with the requirements of Article 2,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline16" href="#16">16</a> “whether account has been taking of the previously expressed wishes and those of people close to him, as well as the opinions of other medical personnel,”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline17" href="#17">17</a> and “the possibility of approaching the courts in the vent of doubts as to the best decision to take in the patient’s interest.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline18" href="#18">18</a> Of particular relevance to the present analysis is the final factor. Lady Black placed reliance in the ECtHR’s observation in the adminissibility decision in <em>Burke v United Kingdom</em> [19] that a “more stringent legal duty” would be “prescriptively burdensome” for the parties involved. Apart from considerations of principle, the practical aspects of such court involvement cannot be neglected in passing.</p>

<p>It is interesting to note that the ECHR’s focus is on a possibility to approach, instead of a requirement to approach. So long as it is possible for parties to seek judicial assistance, it is not necessary to impose any further requirements. This is not only a question of epistemology. It is, more importantly, a crucial finesse of the State’s role in protecting people’s right to life and fair trial, whilst simultaneously offering the possible maximum respect for the clinical team’s expertise and the grieving families. Although Article 2 is an absolute (non-derogable) right, this does not mean the State should be required to interpret expansively such requirement and impose unnecessary restraints on treatment decisions, which better reflects the best interests of the patient.</p>

<h5 id="reflections-on-the-decisions-impact-a-full-respect-for-patient-and-familys-human-rights">Reflections on the decision’s impact: a full respect for patient and family’s human rights?</h5>

<p>In examining the nature of court involvement, Lady Black noted that it is “necessary to exercise the restraint that is required of a court when it ventures into areas of social and ethical uncertainty, and especially when it does so in the abstract, setting out views which will be of general application…“<a class="inline-reference" id="inline20" href="#20">20</a> While judges have experience in adjudicating life and death decisions, it is “a different sort from that of the medical team which actually treats the patient…this limitation must be recognised and taken into account.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline21" href="#21">21</a> Judges are not necessarily always in the best position to adjudicate on clinical decisions and the best interests of the patient. The obligation of the State to secure the patient’s right to life cannot reasonably be seen as an omnipotent requirement to intervene in the private affairs of the family. Given the unique insights the clinical team has pertaining to patient care, courts should limit their involvement to a reasonable minimum.</p>

<p>In examining the patient’s best interests, doctors must follow the guidelines as set out under section 4 MCA 2005.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline22" href="#22">22</a> It is a holistic judgement, which, inter alia, requires consideration of the patient’s values and family members concerned of the patient’s welfare.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline23" href="#23">23</a> In extending considerations to family members, it can also be said that the right to private and family life for grieving family members can be better respected. Determinations over best interests must necessarily have regard to the views of family members. When the clinical team have reached the proposal of terminating treatment (e.g. CANH) after a comprehensive examination of the patient’s best interests, it would be unnecessary to force them to go to court again to obtain a declaratory relief to which they would agree to regardless whether court process is involved. Moreover, declaratory relief may carry potential emotional burdens for families. For some relatives, the prospect of declaratory relief may be distressing because they feel that the court is an illegitimate forum for such decisions to be made. The requirement to go to court may also be seen as an unwelcome legal intrusion into the family’s domain.<a class="inline-reference" id="inline24" href="#24">24</a></p>

<p>The general purpose of medical treatment is to allow patients to recover. If the patient has minimal or zero prospects of recovery, regardless of the type of treatment administered, it would not be of any practical benefit of it to prolong his suffering. Lady Black noted that “if, at the end of the medical process, it is apparent that the way forward is finely balanced…or a lack of agreement to a proposed course of action from those with an interest in the patient’s welfare, a court application can and should be made.”<a class="inline-reference" id="inline25" href="#25">25</a> This neatly sums up the court’s role in questions of terminating medical treatment: it should only intervene when disputes arise. If an agreement is reached between grieving family members and the medical team, the court should accordingly defer to the views of the medical team and respect the private spheres of family life.</p>

<h5 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h5>

<p>In questions of withholding and withdrawing medical treatments, courts act as a last-resort platform for resolving disputes between family members and the medical team. The sensitivity of such matters, together with the expertise of the medical team, makes it unnecessary for courts to examine every single decision before the medical team can proceed. By confirming the court’s limited role in such medical decisions, Y v An NHS Trust provides a commendable and resounding confirmation in the law’s respect for the private spheres and human rights concerns for the patient and his family members.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
Many thanks to Mythili Mishra for her research assistance.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
Article 8, European Convention on Human Rights (“ECHR”).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
[2018] UKSC 46, [8].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
[2017] EWHC 2866, [52].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
<em>Y</em> (n 3) [126].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
ibid, [93]-[94].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
[1993] 1 All ER 281.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="8" href="#inline8">[8]</a>
[1990] 2 AC 1.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="9" href="#inline9">[9]</a>
[2005] EWCA Civ 1003.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="10" href="#inline10">[10]</a>
<em>Y</em> (n 3) [94].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="11" href="#inline11">[11]</a>
Bland concerned a patient in a persistent vegetative state (“PVS”); Re F concerned a patient with mental disability; Burke concerned a patient with a degenerative condition which would ultimately deprive him of the ability to swallow.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="12" href="#inline12">[12]</a>
Code of Practice to the Mental Capacity Act 2005, [6.18].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="13" href="#inline13">[13]</a>
<em>Y</em> (n 3) [97].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="14" href="#inline14">[14]</a>
ibid [105].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="15" href="#inline15">[15]</a>
ibid [110].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="16" href="#inline16">[16]</a>
ibid.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="17" href="#inline17">[17]</a>
ibid [108].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="18" href="#inline18">[18]</a>
ibid [109].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="19" href="#inline19">[19]</a>
App No 19807/06 (ECHR, 11 July 2006).</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="20" href="#inline20">[20]</a>
<em>Y</em> (n 3) [115].</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="21" href="#inline21">[21]</a>
ibid.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="22" href="#inline22">[22]</a>
Section 4 should not be applied unless it is established that the patient in question lacks capacity.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="23" href="#inline23">[23]</a>
As noted by Wade in his criticism in D Wade, “Commentary on Charles Foster’s ‘The rebirth of medical paternalism: An NHS Trust v Y” (Journal of Medical Ethics, 31 October 2018) <a href="https://jme-bmj-com.gate3.library.lse.ac.uk/content/early/2018/10/31/medethics-2018-105200">https://jme-bmj-com.gate3.library.lse.ac.uk/content/early/2018/10/31/medethics-2018-105200</a> accessed 30 November 2018. This is a comment against Charles Foster’s claim that the case represents a resurgence of medical paternalism (C Foster, “The rebirth of medical paternalism: An NHS Trust v Y” (Journal of Medical Ethics, 9 October 2018) <a href="https://jme-bmj-com.gate3.library.lse.ac.uk/content/early/2018/10/09/medethics-2018-105098">https://jme-bmj-com.gate3.library.lse.ac.uk/content/early/2018/10/09/medethics-2018-105098</a> accessed 30 November 2018.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="24" href="#inline24">[24]</a>
S Halliday, A Formby and R Cookson, “An Assessment of the Court’s Role in the Withdrawal of Clinically Assisted Nutrition and Hydration from Patients in the Permanent Vegetative State” (2015) 23(4) Medical Law Review 556, 577.</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="25" href="#inline25">[25]</a>
(n 3) §125.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
