<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title></title>
   
   <link></link>
   <description>A student-run law journal seeking to provide a platform for high quality legal scholarship.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> </managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>European Integration, Brexit and Democracy: What do we do now?</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2018/08/european-integration-brexit-democracy/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2018-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2018/08/european-integration-brexit-democracy/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Over the past two decades, the European Union has experienced an increased disjuncture between its political vision for peace, prosperity and security and the democratic mandate of the people. This disconnect has been vociferously animated by sundry arguments of principle during the United Kingdom’s EU referendum in June 2016, the seismic decision by the UK to leave the EU as well as the continuing negotiations over exit terms between the UK government and the EU. When the European Union (Withdrawal) Act 2018 received Royal Assent two months ago,  it marked a weighty moment in Britain’s troubled history with Europe. It represented democratic resistance to the EU’s politically hegemonic tunnel vision. In this article, I want to make three arguments about an overly-scrutinised and perhaps fatigued project of the EU: European integration. First, I want to offer a theoretical explanation for faltering European integration. Second, I want to advance some reasons why we should be cautious about European integration post-Brexit. Finally, I will tentatively grapple with how European integration ought to be structured.</p>

<h5 id="i-faltering-european-integration">I. Faltering European integration</h5>

<p>Post-2009, the constitutional conundrum created by the EU’s response to the European debt crisis alienated transnational cooperation between member states. Coalesced against competing national interests which swayed in favour of larger member states and the increasing hegemony of the European Council and European Commission, deep-seated tensions emerged between market pressures and the people’s demands. The single currency had a specific ordo-liberal direction with Greece experiencing its effects first-hand. The election of Syriza in 2015 on an anti-austerity platform and the Greek Oxi referendum (where not a single region voted in favour of the bailout conditions spearheaded by the Commission) were managerially ignored by the EU. Greece was compelled to agree to stricter bailout conditions than had been posited in the referendum. Given the disequilibrium between the democratic mandate of the people and the EU’s seemingly interchangeable economic and political vision, the criticism hurled at the project of European integration is unsurprising. After all, to get rid of the EU’s institutional handcuffs is a fair reason to wish to exit the EU. Yet, the UK exited the EU without the European debt crisis as its most cogent justification. So what then triggered British disquiet about the EU? Perhaps the answer is found in Vote Leave’s alluring slogan: ‘take back control’. Behind this sits the most common objection: that the EU disturbs, disrupts and threatens British sovereignty. Yet, in reality, it has more to do with today’s uneasiness that arises from the historical constitutional nature of the EU legal order.</p>

<p>There are three key problems with the EU legal order that have less to do with its design than its purpose. First, its ‘political messianism’. Writing in 2011, Joseph Weiler identified the political messianism of the European integration project by exploring the 868-word Schuman Declaration, akin to Europe’s very own Declaration of Independence<a class="inline-reference" id="inline1" href="#1">1</a>. Its post-World War II rhetoric of peace, prosperity and the reconstruction of Europe omit that of democracy, accountability and representation. Hence, the justification for European integration was the ‘promise of a better future’<a class="inline-reference" id="inline2" href="#2">2</a>. In these terms, the European project of integration began as a peacekeeping mission, with democracy aloof. This then informs the second and third problems with the European construct: the democratic deficit and legitimacy crisis. Often intertwined and historically contingent, the median EU citizen lacks the ability to hold its leaders accountable for their decisions, is unable to directly influence the outcome of policy choices as they would be able to at national level and is increasingly distant to EU institutions, with electoral turnout rates at European Parliament elections declining with every cycle. Yet, these problems come not because the EU has failed in its mission to strengthen post-war European relationships, but because it is now tasked by its leaders to fulfil a role contemporary European society simply believes to be beyond its scope.</p>

<h5 id="ii-european-integration-post-brexit">II. European integration post-Brexit</h5>
<p>The European project of integration calls for a conceptual reassessment of the EU’s design in light of contextual factors throughout its 60-year history. The strength of the dialectical relationship between the people and the EU’s institutions with its peaks and troughs has markedly been influenced by the fluidity of crises. Nonetheless at present, there remain reasons to be positive. First, the Eurozone is no longer in a state of emergency after the stronger monitoring of banking and finance regulations cajoled the financial markets. Second, Europe’s refugee and migrant crisis is somewhat subsiding (though border deaths have surged<a class="inline-reference" id="inline3" href="#3">3</a>). Third, recent elections in the Netherlands, France and Germany have witnessed the defeat of right-wing populism (this strain of populism being a fear of the establishment). Bearing this in mind, it could be said the EU is turning a corner, and the UK’s departure from the EU will leave the 27 remaining member states readier to take on the world’s challenges. Yet, the feeling of apprehension that tickles the thought of a stronger EU lingers.</p>

<p>In GDP terms, the UK’s departure is equivalent to losing the 19 smallest member states<a class="inline-reference" id="inline4" href="#4">4</a>. On one hand, Brexit presents an opportunity for the EU to unite against British awkwardness in the continuing negotiations over exit terms. On the other, it closes the door on British scepticism that has blocked progress to an ever-closer union among the member states in areas such as defence, social policy and direct taxation. At first, it may appear like closing the door on a reputably obstructive partner is a good thing for European integration. However, the graveyards of Bosnia, national banks’ continuous overexposure to sovereign debt and the 120 million EU citizens living at risk of poverty and social exclusion is evidence that habits of cooperation and consensus-building cannot magically happen through treaty change, directives and regulations in such a short period. In this view, European integration – at least what is sought by the EU’s current leaders – is an intergenerational battle of monomaniacal proportions. Who now will question the fusion of member states on issues like the internal market, fundamental rights and the Eurozone? As such, the UK’s withdrawal from the EU signifies the loss of a vocal check and balance tempering the fervency of European integration. Although this loss is prima facie a pragmatic issue, it also presages that fast-moving and deeper integration of the EU is likely a self-fulfilling prophecy of folly.</p>

<h5 id="iii-the-future-for-european-integration">III. The future for European integration</h5>

<p>Since current European integration is not necessarily palatable to democracy and deeper integration seems unconvincing, is the answer to reform the EU or hold this middle ground (i.e. restricting national autonomy while pushing non-political integration)? I have three hesitantly skeletal points in response. First, at least for now, it is unlikely that other member states will follow the UK out of the EU. Current negotiations show the UK struggling to look like a nation capable of leading the world on key issues; internally, the UK is divided. Second, from a historical constitutional perspective, the EU was originally ‘a-democratic’. But, in many ways, the EU has become a threat to democracy – consider Greece, where the people became victims of a militant democratic model believing the tyrannical majority cannot be trusted<a class="inline-reference" id="inline5" href="#5">5</a>. As such, reforming the EU’s design is a viable solution. Some have suggested a mode of radical pluralism – a fluid system with no decided supreme authority, where laws and integration occur flexibly in an incremental process while maintaining legitimacy through national parliaments<a class="inline-reference" id="inline6" href="#6">6</a>. Although this allows for a powerful review of the EU’s constitutional identity, it may hardly lead to genuine compromise if the EU truly wishes to respect national constitutional autonomy. Consequently, this leads to the third key point. Since this middle ground is visibly unstable, stripping the EU’s treaties to their basic constitutional elements could mean retaining EU supremacy only in areas deemed to be the EU’s own constitutional identity (i.e. those elements collectively determined by the member states). Ultimately, this would mean maintaining national democracy (which allows EU citizens to hold their representatives accountable), while constitutionalising core EU principles<a class="inline-reference" id="inline7" href="#7">7</a>. Although it may not be an ideal solution, it is a little more pleasant than others.</p>

<p>Candidly, the European project of integration is too far down the line for member states to multilaterally abandon, but without some measures being taken to re-design the European construct, it may only take a few more decades for it to implode. If substantive changes are not made to the EU legal order and Brexit turns out to be a success, the effect on European integration will be significant. Yet, the same is also true of its reverse. In the present moment, perhaps all that can be said is that compared to other options available, the better able the EU can overcome the challenges it faces and demonstrate its ability to connect democratic voices with governance, European integration may not be faltered just yet.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><a class="reference" id="1" href="#inline1">[1]</a>
J Weiler, ‘The Political and Legal Culture of European Integration: An Exploratory Essay’ (2011) 9 I-CON 678-694</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="2" href="#inline2">[2]</a>
Ibid, 683</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="3" href="#inline3">[3]</a>
The International Organisation for Migration’s ‘missing migrants’ project approximates that more than 5,000 people died while crossing the Mediterranean in 2016, which is up from an estimated 3,700 deaths in 2015. See: https://missingmigrants.iom.int/region/mediterranean</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="4" href="#inline4">[4]</a>
For more information concerning the impact of the UK’s withdrawal from the EU on European integration, see: Tim Oliver and others, ‘The Impact of The UK’S Withdrawal on EU Integration’ (Policy Department for Citizens’ Rights and Constitutional Affairs 2018)</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="5" href="#inline5">[5]</a>
For a discussion about reimagining the European integration project through constitutional pluralism, see: M Wilkinson, ‘Constitutional Pluralism: Chronicle of a Death Foretold?’ (2017) European Law Journal (forthcoming)</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="6" href="#inline6">[6]</a>
N Krisch, ‘Who is Afraid of Radical Pluralism? Legal Order and Political Stability in the Postnational Space’ (2011) 24 Ratio Juris 38</p>

<p><a class="reference" id="7" href="#inline7">[7]</a>
For further analysis of scaling back EU treaties, see: D Grimm, ‘The Democratic Costs of Constitutionalization: The European Case’ (2015) 21 European Law Journal 460-473</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Employees or Independent Contractors: What Defines a “Worker”?</title>
	  <link>/blog-v2//2018/08/employees-independent-contractors-defines-worker/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2018-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog-v2//2018/08/employees-independent-contractors-defines-worker/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><em>Pimlico Plumbers Limited v Smith</em> [2018] UKSC 29 deals with several important issues concerning an intermediate category of working people falling between an “employee” under a contract of service and those who work for others as independent contractors. The final appeal decision clarifies the meaning of “worker” under section 230(3)(b) of the Employment Rights Act 1996 (‘ERA’), Regulation 2(1) of the Working Time Regulations 1998 (‘the Regulations’) and section 83(2) of the Equality Act 2010 (‘the Equality Act’).</p>

<p>Mr Smith is a plumbing and heating engineer. Pimlico Plumbers (‘Pimlico’) is a London-based plumbing business. For almost six years, Mr Smith carried out work for Pimlico. Under the two agreements he had entered into, Pimlico was not obliged to provide Mr Smith work, and he was not obliged to accept any work provided. Tragically, in 2011, Mr Smith suffered a heart attack. After requesting for a three-day week from Pimlico on his doctor’s advice, he was sacked. Following this, he brought claims against Pimlico in an employment tribunal for unfair dismissal, unlawful wage deductions, unpaid annual leave and disability discrimination. The tribunal concluded that he was not an “employee” within the meaning of section 230(1) of the ERA to bring an unfair dismissal claim. However, he was a “worker” under section 230(3)(b) of the ERA and regulation 2(1) of the Regulations. Further, he had been in “employment” under section 83(2) of Equality Act. Pimlico Plumbers appealed these three decisions at the EAT and Court of Appeal. These attempts were unsuccessful, and their arguments again failed before a unanimous Supreme Court (Lord Wilson, Lady Hale, Lord Hughes, Lady Black and Lord Lloyd-Jones).</p>

<p>Under section 230(3) of the ERA, a “worker” is not only defined as, at (a) an individual who is employed under a contract of service, but also at (b), as:</p>

<p>“an individual who has entered into or works under … any other contract … whereby the individual undertakes to … perform personally any work or services for another party to the contract whose status is not by virtue of the contract that of a client or customer of any profession or business undertaking carried on by the individual …”</p>

<p>Reconciling the definition of “workers” against its legislative backdrop, the Supreme Court found that regulation 2(1) of the Regulations defined “worker” in identical terms to section 230(3)(b) of the ERA. At first glance, the definition of “employment” under the Equality Act appears to be different to the concept of “worker” within the meaning of section 230(3)(b) of the ERA and regulation 2(1) of the Regulations. However, following Lady Hale’s observations in <em>Bates van Winkelhof v Clyde &amp; Co LLP</em> [2014] UKSC 32, Lord Wilson noted that this was in fact a distinction without difference. He pointed to Lady Hale’s observations to demonstrate that the operation of section 83(2)(a) of the Equality Act yielded similar economical results to section 230(3)(b) of the ERA and regulation 2(1) of the Regulations, and that this was conceptually legitimate to treat the three decisions as being founded on the question of whether Mr Smith was a “worker” under section 230(3)(b) of the ERA. However, Lord Wilson failed to address how exactly <em>van Winkelhof</em> equated the definition of a “worker” under section 230(3)(b) of the ERA with section 83(2)(a) of the Equality Act. In many ways, this was a lost opportunity, especially with concern to the restrictive approach of <em>Jivraj v Hashwani</em> [2011] UKSC 40 when interpreting “employment” under section 83(2)(a) of the Equality Act.</p>

<p>There were two key legal tests Mr Smith had to satisfy if he was to qualify as a “worker” under section 230(3)(b) of the ERA. The first was that Mr Smith had undertaken to “perform personally” his work for Pimlico, and the second that Pimlico was not to be regarded as Mr Smith’s client or customer. Under the first test, the Court was concerned as to whether Mr Smith’s right to substitute another Pimlico operative was inconsistent with his obligation of personal performance. Ultimately, the employment tribunal, the EAT and the Court of Appeal did not consider Mr Smith’s right to substitute as negating his obligation of personal performance. Challenging this analysis, Pimlico directed the Court’s attention to <em>Halawi v WDFG UK Ltd (t/a World Duty Free)</em> [2014] EWCA Civ 1387 and <em>Mirror Group Newspapers Ltd v Gunning</em> [1986] ICR 145 but these cases did nothing to assist in determining where the boundary lay between the right to substitute and personal performance. Rather, it was in the analysis of <em>James v Redcats (Brands) Ltd</em> [2007] ICR 1006 and <em>Jivraj</em> where the Court held that it was helpful to assess the significance of Mr Smith’s right to substitute by analysing “whether the <em>dominant feature</em> of the contract remained personal performance on his part”.This is a welcome clarificatory approach by the Supreme Court in the assessment of personal performance as it means the lower courts and tribunals should favour to analyse, <em>not</em> merely the purpose of the contract, but its main substance. On the facts of <em>Pimlico Plumbers</em>, the Court found that the right to substitute was “so insignificant as not to be worthy of recognition”. Mr Smith warranting his competence and skills, the requirement for him to uphold a high standard of conduct and that he must carry his Pimlico ID card at all times when working for the Company cumulatively went to show that he had undertaken to “perform personally” his work for Pimlico. Pimlico’s argument that these requirements were capable of applying to anyone who substituted for him was unpersuasive to the Court because it stretched their “natural meaning beyond breaking-point”. Hence, the fact that the contractual right to substitute was limited to other Pimlico operatives was important, as this type of substitute would have had to equally fulfil Pimlico’s “suite of heavy obligations”. It is worth noting that the Court’s analysis had little to do with the law, but is a reminder that contradictory objectives in contractual drafting only causes confusion, and in this context, concurrently benefits the “worker”.</p>

<p>Under the second test, the question was whether the extent of Pimlico’s contractual obligation to offer Mr Smith work and the extent of his obligation to accept the work offered to him evidenced a lack of subordination consistent with Pimlico being no more than his client or customer (the Court applied <em>Windle v Secretary of State for Justice</em>[2016] ICR 721, at [23], per Underhill LJ). The Supreme Court held that the EAT and Court of Appeal were entitled to find that Pimlico had a contractual obligation to offer Mr Smith work if it was available, whereas Mr Smith’s obligation was to keep himself available for up to 40 hours a week to accept any work Pimlico might offer him (but without prejudice to his right to decline what he is offered). Hence, it was legitimate to find that there was an “umbrella contract” between Pimlico and Mr Smith. This was an understandable approach for the Supreme Court to adopt, however the extension of mutuality of obligation beyond employee status is deeply problematic (see: J Prassl, “Pimlico Plumbers, Uber Drivers, Cycle Couriers, and Court Translators: Who is a Worker?” (2017) 33 LQR (forthcoming)). Pimlico made a number of arguments including that: Mr Smith was entitled to reject any work offered and the financial risks and advantages followed from Mr Smith’s work for Pimlico. However, the Court felt that other features of the contract “strongly mitigated” against recognising Pimlico as a client or customer of Mr Smith. In scathing words, Lord Wilson stated that the “severe terms as to when and how much [Pimlico] was obliged to pay him…betrayed a grip on his economy inconsistent with his being a truly independent contractor”. In consequence, it was the Supreme Court’s view that Pimlico could not be regarded as Mr Smith’s client or customer.</p>

<p><em>Pimlico Plumbers</em> arrives at a time when the Courts are favouring worker-protective outcomes. Cases such as <em>Windle</em>, and <em>Aslam &amp; Farrar v Uber</em> (2202550/2015) have incrementally played a clarificatory role in the status of a “worker”. Hence, <em>Pimlico Plumbers</em> is uncontroversial in the sense that whether Mr Smith was a “worker” under section 230(3)(b) of the ERA was always a question of fact for the tribunal. However, what will be of interest (especially to the gig economy) is that section 230(3)(b) now means that independent contractors or those engaged in ‘self-employed’ contracts are capable of being recognised as “workers” and can benefit from the legal rights arising from that recognition. <em>Pimlico Plumbers</em> also raises other issues concerning the compatibility between worker status and self-employment under tax law, but this is a question to be answered at another time.</p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
